January

Friday, January 1

Go, . . . and make disciples of people of all the nations.—[Matt. 28:19].

All of God’s faithful servants want to learn how they can “fully accomplish” the ministry that they have been given to do. ([2 Tim. 4:5]) After all, this work is more important and more urgent than any other occupation in life. However, it can be a challenge to spend as much time in the ministry as we would like. Other important activities demand our time and energy. We may have to work secularly many hours a day to provide the necessities of life for ourselves and our family. We may struggle with other family responsibilities, sickness, depression, or the aches and pains of advancing age. If our circumstances limit the amount of time we can spend in Jehovah’s service, we should not feel discouraged. Jesus knew that not every one of us would be able to produce the same amount of Kingdom fruitage. ([Matt. 13:23]) Jehovah highly values everything we do in his service as long as we are doing our best.—[Heb. 6:10-12]. w19.04 2 ¶1-3

^ (Matt. 28:19) Go, therefore, and make disciples of people of all the nations, baptizing them in the name of the Father and of the Son and of the holy spirit,

^ (2 Tim. 4:5) You, though, keep your senses in all things, endure hardship, do the work of an evangelizer,* fully accomplish your ministry.

Or “keep preaching the good news.”

^ (Matt. 13:23) As for the one sown upon the fine soil, this is the one hearing the word and getting the sense of it, who really does bear fruit and produces, this one 100 times more, that one 60, the other 30.”

^ (Heb. 6:10-12) For God is not unrighteous so as to forget your work and the love you showed for his name by ministering and continuing to minister to the holy ones. 11 But we desire each one of you to show the same industriousness so as to have the full assurance of the hope down to the end, 12 so that you may not become sluggish, but be imitators of those who through faith and patience inherit the promises.

Saturday, January 2

The Devil . . . is a liar and the father of the lie.—[John 8:44].

Satan’s lies about the dead slander Jehovah. Those lies include the false teaching that the dead suffer fiery torment. Such teachings slander God! How so? In effect, they attribute to him, the God of love, the personality of the Devil. ([1 John 4:8]) How does that make you feel? More important, how does it make Jehovah feel? After all, he hates all forms of cruelty. ([Jer. 19:5]) Satan’s lies about death undermine belief in Christ’s ransom sacrifice. ([Matt. 20:28]) Another satanic lie is that humans have an immortal soul. If that were true, everyone would live forever. Christ would not have had to give his life as a ransom for us to gain everlasting life. Keep in mind that Christ’s sacrifice is the greatest expression of love ever shown to the human family. ([John 3:16;][15:13]) Imagine how Jehovah and his Son must feel about teachings that undermine that precious gift! w19.04 14 ¶1; 16 ¶8-9

^ (John 8:44) You are from your father the Devil, and you wish to do the desires of your father. That one was a murderer when he began, and he did not stand fast in the truth, because truth is not in him. When he speaks the lie, he speaks according to his own disposition, because he is a liar and the father of the lie.

^ (1 John 4:8) Whoever does not love has not come to know God, because God is love.

^ (Jer. 19:5) They built the high places of Baʹal in order to burn their sons in the fire as whole burnt offerings to Baʹal, something that I had not commanded or spoken of and that had never even come into my heart.”’*

Or “had never entered my thoughts.”

^ (Matt. 20:28) Just as the Son of man came, not to be ministered to, but to minister and to give his life as a ransom in exchange for many.”

^ (John 3:16) “For God loved the world so much that he gave his only-begotten Son, so that everyone exercising faith in him might not be destroyed but have everlasting life.

^ (John 15:13) No one has love greater than this, that someone should surrender his life in behalf of his friends.

Tuesday, January 5

Make sure of the more important things.—[Phil. 1:10].

What should our priorities include? We should certainly spend time each day studying God’s Word. The amount of material now scheduled for the congregation’s weekly Bible reading has been reduced in order to give us more time to meditate on what we read and to do extra research. Our goal should be, not merely to cover the assigned material, but to allow the Bible’s message to touch our hearts and to draw us closer to Jehovah. ([Ps. 19:14]) The Watchtower Study is a study of the Bible. Therefore, pay particular attention to the scriptures, especially those that will be read when the congregation considers the material. Take special note of how the key words or phrases in the scriptures support the point being made in the paragraph. Moreover, take time to meditate on the scriptures that you read, and reflect on how you can personally apply them in your life.—[Josh. 1:8]. w19.05 27 ¶5; 28 ¶9

^ (Phil. 1:10) that you may make sure of the more important things, so that you may be flawless and not stumbling others up to the day of Christ;

^ (Ps. 19:14) May the words of my mouth and the meditation of my heart Be pleasing to you, O Jehovah, my Rock and my Redeemer.

^ (Josh. 1:8) This book of the Law should not depart from your mouth, and you must read it in an undertone* day and night, in order to observe carefully all that is written in it; for then your way will be successful and then you will act wisely.

Or “meditate on it.”

Friday, January 8

It is beauty on his part to overlook an offense.—[Prov. 19:11].

Jehovah did not intend for any of us to have the problems and stresses we face today. So it is understandable if a faithful servant of Jehovah speaks thoughtlessly when under great stress. ([Job 6:2, 3]) Even if he says inaccurate things about Jehovah or about us, we should not quickly become angry at him or judge him for saying such things. At times, a person who is coping with a stressful problem also needs to receive some form of counsel or helpful discipline. ([Gal. 6:1]) How can elders handle this challenge? They do well to imitate Elihu, who listened to Job with great empathy. ([Job 33:6, 7]) Elihu offered his counsel only after he understood Job’s thinking. Elders who follow Elihu’s example will listen carefully and try to understand the person’s situation. Then, when they offer counsel, they are more likely to reach the heart of their listener. w19.06 22-23 ¶10-11

^ (Prov. 19:11) The insight of a man certainly slows down his anger, And it is beauty on his part to overlook* an offense.*

Lit., “pass over.”

Or “a transgression.”

^ (Job 6:2, 3) “If only my anguish could be fully weighed And put on scales together with my calamity!  3 For now it is heavier than the sands of the seas. That is why my words have been wild talk.*

Or “rash, reckless speech.”

^ (Gal. 6:1) Brothers, even if a man takes a false step before he is aware of it, you who have spiritual qualifications try to readjust such a man in a spirit of mildness. But keep an eye on yourself, for fear you too may be tempted.

^ (Job 33:6, 7) Look! I am just like you before the true God; From the clay I too was shaped.  7 So no fear of me should terrify you, And no pressure from me should overwhelm you.

Saturday, January 9

Obey God as ruler rather than men.—[Acts 5:29].

How can you continue to worship Jehovah while under ban? The branch office will give the local elders instructions and practical suggestions. If the branch office cannot contact the elders, then the elders will help you and all in the congregation to continue your worship of Jehovah. They will give direction in harmony with the guidance found in the Bible and in our Christian publications. (Matt. 28:19, 20; Heb. 10:24, 25) Jehovah has promised that his servants will be well-fed spiritually. (Isa. 65:13, 14; Luke 12:42-44) So you can be certain that his organization will do everything possible to provide the spiritual encouragement you need. What can you do? When under ban, find a good place to hide your Bible and any other spiritual food you might have. Be careful never to leave such precious material—whether it is in printed or electronic form—in a location where it could easily be discovered. Each of us must take practical steps to remain spiritually strong. w19.07 10 ¶10-11

^ (Acts 5:29) In answer Peter and the other apostles said: “We must obey God as ruler rather than men.

^ (Matt. 28:19, 20) Go, therefore, and make disciples of people of all the nations, baptizing them in the name of the Father and of the Son and of the holy spirit, 20 teaching them to observe all the things I have commanded you. And look! I am with you all the days until the conclusion of the system of things.”

^ (Heb. 10:24, 25) And let us consider* one another so as to incite* to love and fine works, 25 not forsaking our meeting together, as some have the custom, but encouraging one another, and all the more so as you see the day drawing near.

Or “be concerned about; pay attention to.”

Or “motivate; stir up.”

^ (Isa. 65:13, 14) Therefore this is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah says: “Look! My servants will eat, but you will go hungry. Look! My servants will drink, but you will go thirsty. Look! My servants will rejoice, but you will suffer shame. 14 Look! My servants will shout joyfully because of the good condition of the heart, But you will cry out because of the pain of heart And you will wail because of a broken spirit.

^ (Luke 12:42-44) And the Lord said: “Who really is the faithful steward, the discreet one, whom his master will appoint over his body of attendants to keep giving them their measure of food supplies at the proper time? 43 Happy is that slave if his master on coming finds him doing so! 44 I tell you truthfully, he will appoint him over all his belongings.

Sunday, January 10

I have become all things to people of all sorts, so that I might by all possible means save some.—[1 Cor. 9:22].

For thousands of years, the majority of people in the world seemed to have some form of religious belief. But in recent decades a remarkable change has taken place. More and more people do not view themselves as religious. In fact, in some countries the majority of the population describe themselves as not being religious. ([Matt. 24:12]) Why? Some may be distracted by pleasures or anxieties. ([Luke 8:14]) Some have become atheists. Others believe in God but think that religion is old-fashioned, irrelevant, and incompatible with science and logical thinking. They may hear friends, teachers, or media personalities say that life evolved, but they rarely hear logical reasons for believing in God. Others are repelled by clergy who are greedy for money and power. In some places, governments officially limit religious activity. w19.07 20 ¶1-2

^ (1 Cor. 9:22) To the weak I became weak, in order to gain the weak. I have become all things to people of all sorts, so that I might by all possible means save some.

^ (Matt. 24:12) and because of the increasing of lawlessness, the love of the greater number will grow cold.

^ (Luke 8:14) As for that which fell among the thorns, these are the ones who have heard, but by being carried away by anxieties, riches, and pleasures of this life, they are completely choked and bring nothing to maturity.

Tuesday, January 12

Let your light shine before men, so that they may see your fine works.—[Matt. 5:16].

Jehovah draws people to him by means of the “fine works” of the Christian congregation. (Matt. 5:14, 15;[1 Pet. 2:12]) If your mate is not one of Jehovah’s Witnesses, has he or she met members of your congregation? Invite your mate to attend congregation meetings with you. (1 Cor. 14:24, 25) We hope that all our relatives will join us in serving Jehovah. However, despite all our efforts to help our relatives to become God’s servants, they may not come into the truth. If that is the case, we should not blame ourselves for their decision. After all, we cannot force anyone to accept our beliefs. Even so, do not underestimate the influence you can have on your relatives as they see how happy you are serving Jehovah. Pray for them. Tactfully speak to them. Do not hold back! ([Acts 20:20]) Be confident that Jehovah will bless your efforts. And if your relatives choose to listen to you, they will be saved! w19.08 18-19 ¶15-17

^ (Matt. 5:16) Likewise, let your light shine before men, so that they may see your fine works and give glory to your Father who is in the heavens.

^ (Matt. 5:14, 15) “You are the light of the world. A city cannot be hid when located on a mountain. 15 People light a lamp and set it, not under a basket, but on the lampstand, and it shines on all those in the house.

^ (1 Pet. 2:12) Maintain your conduct fine among the nations, so that when they accuse you of being wrongdoers, they may be eyewitnesses of your fine works and, as a result, glorify God in the day of his inspection.

^ (1 Cor. 14:24, 25) But if you are all prophesying and an unbeliever or an ordinary person comes in, he will be reproved and closely examined by them all. 25 The secrets of his heart then become evident, so that he will fall facedown and worship God, declaring: “God is really among you.”

^ (Acts 20:20) while I did not hold back from telling you any of the things that were profitable* nor from teaching you publicly and from house to house.

Or “for your good; for your benefit.”

Thursday, January 14

I reside in the high and holy place, but also with those crushed and lowly in spirit.—[Isa. 57:15].

In recent years, many with decades of experience have received a change of assignment. Such adjustments were not easy for these brothers and sisters to make. Obviously, they felt attached to their former assignment, in many cases one that they had cherished for years. Some went through a “grieving” process as they adjusted to their new circumstances. In time, though, they were able to adjust. Why? Above all, because of their love for Jehovah. They knew that they were dedicated to God—not to a work, a title, or an assignment. ([Col. 3:23]) They are glad to continue serving Jehovah humbly in any capacity. They “throw all [their] anxiety on him,” knowing that he cares for them. (1 Pet. 5:6, 7) When we cultivate the endearing quality of humility, we benefit both ourselves and others. We are better able to deal with life’s challenges. Above all, we draw closer to our heavenly Father. w19.09 6-7 ¶15-17

^ (Isa. 57:15) For this is what the High and Lofty One says, Who lives* forever and whose name is holy: “I reside in the high and holy place, But also with those crushed and lowly in spirit, To revive the spirit of the lowly And to revive the heart of those being crushed.

Or “resides.”

^ (Col. 3:23) Whatever you are doing, work at it whole-souled* as for Jehovah,* and not for men,

See Glossary, “Soul.”

See App. A5.

^ (1 Pet. 5:6, 7) Humble yourselves, therefore, under the mighty hand of God, so that he may exalt you in due time, 7 while you throw all your anxiety* on him, because he cares for you.

Or “cares; worries.”

Saturday, January 16

I saw . . . a great crowd . . . standing before the throne and before the Lamb.—[Rev. 7:9].

In 1935, Jehovah’s Witnesses came to realize that the great crowd do not literally have to be in heaven to stand “before the throne and before the Lamb.” Rather, their position is figurative. Even though they would live on earth, the great crowd could stand “before the throne” by recognizing Jehovah’s authority and by submitting to his sovereignty. ([Isa. 66:1]) They could stand “before the Lamb” by exercising faith in Jesus’ ransom sacrifice. Similarly, at Matthew 25:31, 32, “all the nations”—including the wicked—are said to be “gathered before” Jesus on his glorious throne. Clearly, all these nations are, not in heaven, but on earth. This adjusted understanding makes sense. It explains why the Bible does not say that the great crowd is raised to heaven. Only one group is promised everlasting life in heaven—the 144,000, who will “rule as kings over the earth” with Jesus.—[Rev. 5:10]. w19.09 28 ¶9

^ (Rev. 7:9) After this I saw, and look! a great crowd, which no man was able to number, out of all nations and tribes and peoples and tongues,* standing before the throne and before the Lamb, dressed in white robes; and there were palm branches in their hands.

Or “languages.”

^ (Isa. 66:1) This is what Jehovah says: “The heavens are my throne, and the earth is my footstool. Where, then, is the house that you could build for me, And where is my resting-place?”

^ (Matt. 25:31, 32) “When the Son of man comes in his glory, and all the angels with him, then he will sit down on his glorious throne. 32 All the nations will be gathered before him, and he will separate people one from another, just as a shepherd separates the sheep from the goats.

^ (Rev. 5:10) and you made them to be a kingdom and priests to our God, and they are to rule as kings over the earth.”

Monday, January 18

[Jehovah] is a God who requires exclusive devotion.—[Ex. 34:14].

Jehovah wants us to enjoy life, and entertainment can help us to do that. In fact, God’s Word says that “there is nothing better for a man than to eat and drink and find enjoyment in his hard work.” ([Eccl. 2:24]) However, much of the entertainment in the world can have a bad effect on us. It degrades people’s moral standards, encouraging them to tolerate—or even to love—things that God’s Word condemns. We want to give Jehovah exclusive devotion, so we cannot eat from “the table of Jehovah” and “the table of demons.” (1 Cor. 10:21, 22) Eating a meal with someone is often a sign of friendship. If we choose entertainment that promotes violence, spiritism, immorality, or other fleshly desires and attitudes, we are, in effect, sharing a meal prepared by enemies of God. As a result, we not only harm ourselves but also damage our friendship with Jehovah. w19.10 26 ¶2; 29-30 ¶11-12

^ (Ex. 34:14) You must not bow down to another god, for Jehovah is known for* requiring exclusive devotion.* Yes, he is a God who requires exclusive devotion.

Lit., “Jehovah, his name is.”

Or “not tolerating rivals.”

^ (Eccl. 2:24) There is nothing better for a man than to eat and drink and find enjoyment* in his hard work. This too, I have realized, is from the hand of the true God,

Or “cause his soul to see good.”

^ (1 Cor. 10:21, 22) You cannot be drinking the cup of Jehovah and the cup of demons; you cannot be partaking of “the table of Jehovah” and the table of demons. 22 Or ‘are we inciting Jehovah to jealousy’? We are not stronger than he is, are we?

Tuesday, January 19

Men spoke from God as they were moved by holy spirit.—[2 Pet. 1:21].

To benefit from the wind, a sailor must do two things. First, he has to put his boat in the path of the wind. After all, his boat will not move forward if the sailor remains in a harbor far away from where the wind is blowing. Second, he needs to raise and unfurl his sails as fully as possible. Obviously, even with the wind blowing, his boat will move forward only if the sails catch the wind. Similarly, we will endure in Jehovah’s service only if we have the help of holy spirit. To benefit from that spirit, we must take two steps. First, we must put ourselves squarely in the path of God’s spirit by sharing in activities that bring us under its influence. Second, we need to “raise our sails” as fully as possible by being fully engaged in these activities to the best of our ability. ([Ps. 119:32]) Holy spirit will then push us forward through waves of opposition and trials and will help us to endure faithfully. w19.11 9 ¶8; 10 ¶11

^ (2 Pet. 1:21) For prophecy was at no time brought by man’s will, but men spoke from God as they were moved* by holy spirit.

Lit., “carried along; borne along.”

^ (Ps. 119:32) I will eagerly pursue* the way of your commandments Because you make room for it in my heart.*

Lit., “will run.”

Or possibly, “you make my heart have the confidence.”

Thursday, January 21

Do not put out the fire of the spirit.—1 Thess. 5:19.

We do well to ask ourselves, ‘Am I grateful to be associated with the earthly part of Jehovah’s organization?’ Jehovah has given us convincing evidence that he is blessing his people today. We truly have much to be thankful for. (1 Thess. 5:18) How can we show our support for the organization that Jehovah is using? By following the Bible-based direction we are given in our publications and at our meetings, assemblies, and conventions. In addition, we can show our support by sharing as fully as possible in the preaching and teaching work. ([1 Cor. 15:58]) May we obtain Jehovah’s approval for our sacrifices to be accepted. May we serve Jehovah because we are grateful to him. May we continue to give our best to Jehovah because we love him with all our heart. And may we wholeheartedly support the organization that he is blessing today. In all such ways, we can show Jehovah that we cherish the privilege we have to serve him as his Witnesses! w19.11 25 ¶17-18

^ (1 Thess. 5:19) Do not put out the fire of the spirit.

^ (1 Thess. 5:18) Give thanks for everything. This is God’s will for you in Christ Jesus.

^ (1 Cor. 15:58) Therefore, my beloved brothers, be steadfast, immovable, always having plenty to do in the work of the Lord, knowing that your labor is not in vain* in connection with the Lord.

Lit., “empty.”

Friday, January 22

Whoever exercises faith in me . . . will do works greater than these.—[John 14:12].

Jesus did not mean that we would perform miracles as he did. Rather, his followers would preach and teach in a larger territory, to more people, and for a longer period of time than he did. If you have a secular job, ask yourself these questions: ‘Am I known at my workplace as a hard worker? Do I complete my work on time and to the best of my ability?’ If you can answer yes, then you will likely earn your employer’s trust. You will also make the Kingdom message more appealing to those who are observing you. When it comes to the preaching and teaching work, ask yourself these questions: ‘Am I known as a hard worker in the ministry? Do I prepare well for initial calls? Do I return promptly to talk with interested people? And do I have a regular share in various aspects of the ministry?’ If you can answer yes, you will find joy in your work. w19.12 5 ¶14-15

^ (John 14:12) Most truly I say to you, whoever exercises faith in me will also do the works that I do; and he will do works greater than these, because I am going my way to the Father.

Saturday, January 23

Each one of you must love his wife as he does himself; on the other hand, the wife should have deep respect for her husband.—[Eph. 5:33].

A couple who decide to have children do well to discuss two important questions: First, when do they want to have children? Second, how many children do they want? When is the best time for a couple to have such a discussion? And why are those two subjects so important? In most cases, before they get married, a couple do well to address the subject of having children. Why then? One good reason is that being of the same mind on this matter is important. Also, they will need to consider whether they are ready for that responsibility. Some couples have decided to wait at least a year or two after their wedding before having children because becoming parents will consume much time and energy. They reason that by waiting for a while, they will give themselves time to adjust to married life and draw closer to each other. w19.12 23 ¶4-5

^ (Eph. 5:33) Nevertheless, each one of you must love his wife as he does himself; on the other hand, the wife should have deep respect for her husband.

Sunday, January 24

A true friend . . . is a brother who is born for times of distress.—[Prov. 17:17].

Around the world, many servants of Jehovah are facing stressful, even painful, situations. Some Christians are dealing with a serious illness or with the death of a loved one. Others are enduring the intense pain of seeing a family member or close friend leave the truth. Still others are coping with the effects of natural disasters. All such brothers and sisters need comfort. How can we help them? Be a loyal friend. Loyal friends make sacrifices in order to support their brothers and sisters. For example, a brother named Peter was diagnosed with a very aggressive terminal illness. His wife, Kathryn, says: “A couple in our congregation took us to the appointment where we found out about Peter’s illness. They decided not to let us go on this painful journey alone, and they have been by our side whenever we have needed them.” How comforting it is to have true friends, who can help us to endure our trials! w20.01 8 ¶1; 9 ¶5; 10 ¶6

^ (Prov. 17:17) A true friend shows love at all times And is a brother who is born for times of distress.

Monday, January 25

They all became filled with holy spirit and started to speak in different languages.—[Acts 2:4].

If you were one of the disciples gathered in the upper room at Pentecost 33 C.E., there would be no question in your mind that you were anointed by holy spirit. ([Acts 2:5-12]) But do all those who are anointed by holy spirit receive their anointing in some spectacular manner and at the same time in their life? No. Consider the matter of timing. That group of about 120 Christians were not the only ones anointed by holy spirit on that day. Later that day, about 3,000 others also received the promised holy spirit. Their anointing occurred when they got baptized. (Acts 2:37, 38,[41]) But in the years that followed, not all anointed Christians received their anointing at their baptism. The Samaritans received their anointing sometime after their baptism. ([Acts 8:14-17]) And in what certainly was an exceptional instance, Cornelius and his household were anointed even before they got baptized.—Acts 10:44-48. w20.01 20-21 ¶2-4

^ (Acts 2:4) and they all became filled with holy spirit and started to speak in different languages, just as the spirit enabled them to speak.

^ (Acts 2:5-12) At that time devout Jews from every nation under heaven were staying in Jerusalem. 6 So when this sound occurred, a crowd gathered and was bewildered, because each one heard them speaking in his own language. 7 Indeed, they were utterly amazed and said: “See here, all these who are speaking are Gal·i·leʹans, are they not? 8 How is it, then, that each one of us is hearing his own native language? 9 Parʹthi·ans, Medes, and Eʹlam·ites, the inhabitants of Mes·o·po·taʹmi·a, Ju·deʹa and Cap·pa·doʹci·a, Ponʹtus and the province of Asia, 10 Phrygʹi·a and Pam·phylʹi·a, Egypt and the regions of Libʹy·a near Cy·reʹne, sojourners from Rome, both Jews and proselytes, 11 Creʹtans, and Arabians—we hear them speaking in our languages about the magnificent things of God.” 12 Yes, they were all astonished and perplexed, saying to one another: “What does this mean?”

^ (Acts 2:37, 38) Now when they heard this, they were stabbed to the heart, and they said to Peter and the rest of the apostles: “Men, brothers, what should we do?” 38 Peter said to them: “Repent, and let each one of you be baptized in the name of Jesus Christ for forgiveness of your sins, and you will receive the free gift of the holy spirit.

^ (Acts 2:41) So those who gladly accepted his word were baptized, and on that day about 3,000 people were added.

^ (Acts 8:14-17) When the apostles in Jerusalem heard that Sa·marʹi·a had accepted the word of God, they sent Peter and John to them; 15 and these went down and prayed for them to get holy spirit. 16 For it had not yet come upon any one of them, but they had only been baptized in the name of the Lord Jesus. 17 Then they laid their hands on them, and they began to receive holy spirit.

^ (Acts 10:44-48) While Peter was still speaking about these matters, the holy spirit came upon all those hearing the word. 45 And the circumcised believers who had come with Peter were amazed, because the free gift of the holy spirit was being poured out also on people of the nations. 46 For they heard them speaking in foreign languages and magnifying God. Then Peter responded: 47 “Can anyone deny water to prevent these from being baptized who have received the holy spirit just as we have?” 48 With that he commanded them to be baptized in the name of Jesus Christ. Then they requested him to stay for some days.

Tuesday, January 26

I have made your name known to them.—[John 17:26].

In the four Gospels alone, Jesus used the term “Father” some 165 times in reference to Jehovah. Why did Jesus speak so much about Jehovah? One reason is that people might be convinced that Jehovah is a loving Father. ([John 17:25]) Consider what we learn about Jehovah from the way that he treated his Son, Jesus. Jehovah always heard Jesus’ prayers. He not only heard Jesus’ prayers but also answered them. (John 11:41, 42) No matter what trials Jesus faced, he sensed his Father’s love and support. (Luke 22:42, 43) As a loving Father, Jehovah made sure that Jesus knew he had his Father’s backing. ([Matt. 26:53;][John 8:16]) While Jehovah did not shield Jesus from all injury, He helped him to endure trials. Jesus was assured that any harm he might suffer would be temporary. ([Heb. 12:2]) Jehovah proved that he cared for Jesus by listening to him, providing for him, training him, and supporting him.—[John 5:20;][8:28]. w20.02 3 ¶6-7, 9

^ (John 17:26) I have made your name known to them and will make it known, so that the love with which you loved me may be in them and I in union with them.”

^ (John 17:25) Righteous Father, the world has, indeed, not come to know you, but I know you, and these have come to know that you sent me.

^ (John 11:41, 42) So they took the stone away. Then Jesus raised his eyes heavenward and said: “Father, I thank you that you have heard me. 42 True, I knew that you always hear me; but I spoke on account of the crowd standing around, so that they may believe that you sent me.”

^ (Luke 22:42, 43) saying: “Father, if you want to, remove this cup from me. Nevertheless, let, not my will, but yours take place.” 43 Then an angel from heaven appeared to him and strengthened him.

^ (Matt. 26:53) Or do you think that I cannot appeal to my Father to supply me at this moment more than 12 legions of angels?

^ (John 8:16) And yet even if I do judge, my judgment is truthful, because I am not alone, but the Father who sent me is with me.

^ (Heb. 12:2) as we look intently at the Chief Agent and Perfecter of our faith, Jesus. For the joy that was set before him he endured a torture stake,* despising shame, and has sat down at the right hand of the throne of God.

See Glossary.

^ (John 5:20) For the Father has affection for the Son and shows him all the things he himself does, and he will show him works greater than these, so that you may marvel.

^ (John 8:28) Jesus then said: “After you have lifted up the Son of man, then you will know that I am he and that I do nothing of my own initiative; but just as the Father taught me, I speak these things.

Thursday, January 28

I am the least of the apostles, and I am not worthy of being called an apostle.—[1 Cor. 15:9].

The 12 apostles followed Jesus during his earthly ministry, but the apostle Paul did not become a Christian until after Jesus’ death and resurrection. Although he was eventually appointed to be “an apostle to the nations,” Paul did not qualify for the special privilege of becoming one of the 12 apostles. ([Rom. 11:13;] Acts 1:21-26) Rather than envying those 12 men and the close association they had enjoyed with Jesus, Paul remained content with what he had. If we are content and humble, we will be like Paul and show respect for the authority that Jehovah has given to others. (Acts 21:20-26) He has arranged for appointed men to take the lead in the Christian congregation. Despite their imperfections, Jehovah considers them “gifts in men.” ([Eph. 4:8,][11]) When we respect these appointed men and humbly follow their direction, we stay close to Jehovah and enjoy peace with our fellow Christians. w20.02 17 ¶13-14

^ (1 Cor. 15:9) For I am the least of the apostles, and I am not worthy of being called an apostle, because I persecuted the congregation of God.

^ (Rom. 11:13) Now I speak to you who are people of the nations. Seeing that I am an apostle to the nations, I glorify my ministry

^ (Acts 1:21-26) It is therefore necessary that of the men who accompanied us during all the time in which the Lord Jesus carried on his activities among us, 22 starting with his baptism by John until the day he was taken up from us, one of these men should become a witness with us of his resurrection.” 23 So they proposed two, Joseph called Barʹsab·bas, who was also called Justus, and Mat·thiʹas. 24 Then they prayed and said: “You, O Jehovah, who know the hearts of all, designate which one of these two men you have chosen 25 to take the place of this ministry and apostleship, from which Judas deviated to go to his own place.” 26 So they cast lots over them, and the lot fell to Mat·thiʹas, and he was counted along with the 11 apostles.

^ (Acts 21:20-26) After hearing this, they began to glorify God, but they said to him: “You see, brother, how many thousands of believers there are among the Jews, and they are all zealous for the Law. 21 But they have heard it rumored about you that you have been teaching all the Jews among the nations an apostasy from Moses, telling them not to circumcise their children or to follow the customary practices. 22 What, then, is to be done about it? They are certainly going to hear that you have arrived. 23 So do what we tell you: We have four men who have put themselves under a vow. 24 Take these men with you and cleanse yourself ceremonially together with them and take care of their expenses, so that they may have their heads shaved. Then everyone will know that there is nothing to the rumors they were told about you, but that you are walking orderly and you are also keeping the Law. 25 As for the believers from among the nations, we have sent them our decision in writing that they should keep away from what is sacrificed to idols as well as from blood, from what is strangled, and from sexual immorality.” 26 Then Paul took the men the next day and cleansed himself ceremonially along with them, and he went into the temple to give notice of when the days for the ceremonial cleansing would be completed and the offering should be presented for each one of them.

^ (Eph. 4:8) For it says: “When he ascended on high he carried away captives; he gave gifts in men.”

^ (Eph. 4:11) And he gave some as apostles, some as prophets, some as evangelizers,* some as shepherds and teachers,

Or “proclaimers of the good news.”

Friday, January 29

We love, because he first loved us.—[1 John 4:19].

Before studying with Jehovah’s Witnesses, you may have formed a deep appreciation for the Bible. And you may have developed a love for Jesus. Now that you have come to know Jehovah’s Witnesses, you might love to associate with them. But loving those good things will not necessarily make you want to dedicate yourself to Jehovah and get baptized. The primary motivation that will lead you to baptism is love for Jehovah God himself. When you love Jehovah more than all else, you will not let anything or anyone prevent you from serving him. You could view love for Jehovah as both the gateway to baptism and the guardrail that helps you stay on the path of serving God. Jesus said that we must love Jehovah with our whole heart, soul, mind, and strength. ([Mark 12:30]) How can you learn to love and respect Jehovah that deeply? Reflecting on Jehovah’s love for us moves us to love him in return. w20.03 4 ¶4-5

^ (1 John 4:19) We love, because he first loved us.

^ (Mark 12:30) and you must love Jehovah your God with your whole heart and with your whole soul and with your whole mind and with your whole strength.’

Sunday, January 31

Truth is not in him.—[John 8:44].

Satan’s lies add grief and suffering to mankind. Parents who are grieving the death of a child may be told that God has taken the child, perhaps to be an angel in heaven. Does this satanic lie lessen their pain or add to it? The false teaching of hellfire has been used to justify torture, including the burning at the stake of those who opposed church teachings. According to a book on the Spanish Inquisition, some of those responsible for this cruelty may have believed that they were only giving heretics “a taste of what perpetual hellfire would be like” so that they would repent before dying and be saved from hellfire. In a number of lands, people feel compelled to pay homage to their dead ancestors, to honor them, or to seek a blessing from them. Others want to appease their ancestors in order to avoid some form of punishment. Sadly, beliefs based on satanic lies do not bring genuine comfort. Instead, they cause needless anxiety or even fear. w19.04 14 ¶1; 16 ¶10

^ (John 8:44) You are from your father the Devil, and you wish to do the desires of your father. That one was a murderer when he began, and he did not stand fast in the truth, because truth is not in him. When he speaks the lie, he speaks according to his own disposition, because he is a liar and the father of the lie.

February

Monday, February 1

[Jehovah] loves . . . justice.—[Ps. 33:5].

“Justice,” as used in the Bible, basically means to do what God considers to be right and to do so without partiality. Consider how Jesus’ actions revealed his sense of justice. In his day, the Jewish religious leaders hated non-Jews, despised common Jews, and disrespected women. Jesus, however, was fair and impartial in dealing with all. He accepted non-Jews who approached him in faith. (Matt. 8:5-10,[13]) He preached without prejudice to all, rich and poor. ([Matt. 11:5;][Luke 19:2,][9]) He was never harsh or abusive in his treatment of women. On the contrary, he was respectful and kind to women, including those whom others viewed with scorn. (Luke 7:37-39,[44-50]) We can imitate Jesus by dealing impartially with others and preaching to all who are willing to listen—regardless of their social or religious background. Christian men follow his example by treating women with respect. w19.05 2 ¶1; 5 ¶15-17

^ (Ps. 33:5) He loves righteousness and justice. The earth is filled with Jehovah’s loyal love.

^ (Matt. 8:5-10) When he entered Ca·perʹna·um, an army officer came to him, pleading with him 6 and saying: “Sir, my servant is laid up in the house with paralysis, and he is suffering terribly.”* 7 He said to him: “When I get there, I will cure him.” 8 The army officer replied: “Sir, I am not worthy to have you come under my roof, but just say the word and my servant will be healed. 9 For I too am a man under authority, having soldiers under me, and I say to this one, ‘Go!’ and he goes, and to another, ‘Come!’ and he comes, and to my slave, ‘Do this!’ and he does it.” 10 When Jesus heard that, he was amazed and said to those following him: “I tell you the truth, with no one in Israel have I found so great a faith.

Or “is terribly afflicted.”

^ (Matt. 8:13) Then Jesus said to the army officer: “Go. Just as you have shown faith, so let it come to pass for you.” And the servant was healed in that hour.

^ (Matt. 11:5) The blind are now seeing and the lame are walking, the lepers are being cleansed and the deaf are hearing, the dead are being raised up and the poor are being told the good news.

^ (Luke 19:2) Now a man named Zac·chaeʹus was there; he was a chief tax collector, and he was rich.

^ (Luke 19:9) At this Jesus said to him: “Today salvation has come to this house, because he too is a son of Abraham.

^ (Luke 7:37-39) And look! a woman who was known in the city to be a sinner learned that he was dining* in the house of the Pharisee, and she brought an alabaster jar of perfumed oil. 38 Taking a position behind him at his feet, she wept and began to wet his feet with her tears, and she wiped them off with the hair of her head. Also, she tenderly kissed his feet and poured the perfumed oil on them. 39 Seeing this, the Pharisee who had invited him said to himself: “If this man were really a prophet, he would know who and what kind of woman it is who is touching him, that she is a sinner.”

Or “reclining at the table.”

^ (Luke 7:44-50) With that he turned to the woman and said to Simon: “Do you see this woman? I entered your house; you gave me no water for my feet. But this woman wet my feet with her tears and wiped them off with her hair. 45 You gave me no kiss, but this woman, from the hour that I came in, did not stop tenderly kissing my feet. 46 You did not pour oil on my head, but this woman poured perfumed oil on my feet. 47 Because of this, I tell you, her sins, many* though they are, are forgiven, because she loved much. But the one who is forgiven little, loves little.” 48 Then he said to her: “Your sins are forgiven.” 49 Those reclining at the table with him started to say among themselves: “Who is this man who even forgives sins?” 50 But he said to the woman: “Your faith has saved you; go in peace.”

Or “great.”

Tuesday, February 2

We became gentle in your midst, as when a nursing mother tenderly cares for her own children.—[1 Thess. 2:7].

Loyal elders today can likewise use tender, gentle words as they offer Scriptural comfort to those in need. Are elders the only ones who can give comfort to victims of abuse? No. All of us have a responsibility to “keep comforting one another.” (1 Thess. 4:18) Mature Christian sisters can be especially encouraging to sisters in need of comfort. Fittingly, Jehovah God likened himself to a mother who comforts her son. ([Isa. 66:13]) The Bible includes examples of women who provided comfort to those in distress. ([Job 42:11]) How delighted Jehovah is to see Christian women today offering comfort to fellow sisters who struggle with emotional pain! In some cases, an elder or two may discreetly ask a mature sister if she is in a position to help a suffering sister in that way. Of course, we are careful not to pry into matters that a fellow Christian prefers to keep private.—1 Thess. 4:11. w19.05 16-17 ¶10-12

^ (1 Thess. 2:7) On the contrary, we became gentle in your midst, as when a nursing mother tenderly cares for* her own children.

Or “cherishes.”

^ (1 Thess. 4:18) So keep comforting one another with these words.

^ (Isa. 66:13) As a mother comforts her son, So I will keep comforting you; And over Jerusalem you will be comforted.

^ (Job 42:11) All his brothers and sisters and all his former friends came to him and ate a meal with him in his house. They sympathized with him and comforted him over all the calamity that Jehovah had allowed to come upon him. Each of them gave him a piece of money and a gold ring.

^ (1 Thess. 4:11) Make it your aim to live quietly and to mind your own business and to work with your hands, just as we instructed you,

Thursday, February 4

Ponder over these things . . . , so that your advancement may be plainly seen by all people.—[1 Tim. 4:15].

It is important for children to be taught how to study. They need to learn how to prepare for congregation meetings, for example, or how to do research on an issue that has arisen at school. ([Heb. 5:14]) If they spend some time on study projects at home, they will be better equipped to focus on the material presented at congregation meetings, assemblies, and conventions. Of course, the length of each study period will depend on the age and temperament of the children. Our Bible students also need to learn how to study. When they are new, we are happy to see them simply underline the answers in preparation for their Bible study or for congregation meetings. But we do need to teach our Bible students how to do research and how to do meaningful study on their own. In that way, when problems arise, they will know how to get practical advice for themselves by doing research in our publications. w19.05 26 ¶2; 28 ¶10-11

^ (1 Tim. 4:15) Ponder over* these things; be absorbed in them, so that your advancement may be plainly seen by all people.

Or “Meditate on.”

^ (Heb. 5:14) But solid food belongs to mature people, to those who through use have their powers of discernment* trained to distinguish both right and wrong.

Or “their perceptive powers.”

Sunday, February 7

Jehovah, give attention to their threats, and grant to your slaves to keep speaking your word with all boldness.—[Acts 4:29].

If our work is banned, the elders will arrange for you to attend meetings in a way that will not attract unwanted attention. They may direct you to meet in small groups and may change the meeting times and locations frequently. Regarding the preaching work, circumstances will vary from one location to another. But we love Jehovah and enjoy telling others about his Kingdom, so we will find a way to preach. ([Luke 8:1]) Commenting on Jehovah’s Witnesses in the former Soviet Union, historian Emily B. Baran said: “When the state told believers that they could not evangelize their faith to others, Witnesses chatted [with] their neighbors, coworkers, and friends. When these actions landed them in labor camps, Witnesses sought out converts among their fellow prisoners.” Despite the ban, our brothers there did not stop preaching. May you have that same determination! w19.07 11 ¶12-13

^ (Acts 4:29) And now, Jehovah, give attention to their threats, and grant to your slaves to keep speaking your word with all boldness,

^ (Luke 8:1) Shortly afterward he traveled from city to city and from village to village, preaching and declaring the good news of the Kingdom of God. And the Twelve were with him,

Wednesday, February 10

Weep with those who weep.—[Rom. 12:15].

We may find it hard to know what to say to someone who is overcome by grief. Sometimes our tears say more than our words. When Jesus’ friend Lazarus died, Mary, Martha, and others wept for their beloved brother and friend. Four days later when Jesus arrived, he too “gave way to tears,” even though he knew that he was about to resurrect Lazarus. ([John 11:17,][33-35]) Jesus’ tears reflected the feelings of his Father. They also confirmed Jesus’ love for the family, which no doubt comforted Mary and Martha. Similarly, when our brothers sense our love and concern, they know that they are not alone but are surrounded by caring and supportive friends. Sometimes we must simply be a good listener. Allow your brother to pour out his heart, and do not be offended by “wild talk.” ([Job 6:2, 3]) He may be under added emotional stress because of pressure from relatives who are not Witnesses. So pray with him. Beg the “Hearer of prayer” to give him strength and clarity of mind.—[Ps. 65:2]. w19.04 18-19 ¶18-19

^ (Rom. 12:15) Rejoice with those who rejoice; weep with those who weep.

^ (John 11:17) When Jesus arrived, he found that Lazʹa·rus had already been in the tomb for four days.

^ (John 11:33-35) When Jesus saw her weeping and the Jews who had come with her weeping, he groaned within himself and became troubled. 34 He said: “Where have you laid him?” They said to him: “Lord, come and see.” 35 Jesus gave way to tears.

^ (Job 6:2, 3) “If only my anguish could be fully weighed And put on scales together with my calamity!  3 For now it is heavier than the sands of the seas. That is why my words have been wild talk.*

Or “rash, reckless speech.”

^ (Ps. 65:2) O Hearer of prayer, to you people of all sorts* will come.

Lit., “all flesh.”

Thursday, February 11

Pour out your hearts before him.—[Ps. 62:8].

Whether we serve in the field or at Bethel, we can develop deep affection for people and even for the place where we serve. If for any reason we have to leave, our heart feels torn. We miss those who stay behind, and we worry about them, especially if we had to leave because of persecution. ([Matt. 10:23;] 2 Cor. 11:28, 29) Further, taking up a new assignment—or even returning home—often means experiencing culture shock. Some who get a change of assignment may suddenly face unexpected financial challenges. They may feel uncertain, insecure, and discouraged. What can help? Stay close to Jehovah. ([Jas. 4:8]) How can we do that? By trusting in him as the “Hearer of prayer.” ([Ps. 65:2]) Jehovah can do “more than superabundantly beyond all the things we ask or conceive.” ([Eph. 3:20]) He does not limit himself to what we specifically ask for in our prayers. He may do the unexpected, beyond anything that we could ever think of, to solve our problems. w19.08 21 ¶5-6

^ (Ps. 62:8) Trust in him at all times, O people. Pour out your hearts before him. God is a refuge for us. (Selah)

^ (Matt. 10:23) When they persecute you in one city, flee to another; for truly I say to you, you will by no means complete the circuit of the cities of Israel until the Son of man arrives.

^ (2 Cor. 11:28, 29) Besides those things of an external kind, there is what rushes in on me from day to day:* the anxiety for all the congregations. 29 Who is weak, and I am not weak? Who is stumbled, and I am not incensed?

Or “the daily pressure on me.”

^ (Jas. 4:8) Draw close to God, and he will draw close to you. Cleanse your hands, you sinners, and purify your hearts, you indecisive ones.

^ (Ps. 65:2) O Hearer of prayer, to you people of all sorts* will come.

Lit., “all flesh.”

^ (Eph. 3:20) Now to the one who can, according to his power that is operating in us, do more than superabundantly beyond all the things we ask or conceive,

Friday, February 12

They gathered them together to . . . Armageddon.—[Rev. 16:16].

Some people apply the word “Armageddon” to a nuclear war or an environmental disaster. In contrast, the Bible says that Armageddon involves good news, a cause for happiness! ([Rev. 1:3]) The war of Armageddon will not destroy but save mankind! How so? By ending human rule. That war will save mankind by removing the wicked and preserving the righteous. And it will save mankind by protecting our planet from ruin. ([Rev. 11:18]) The word “Armageddon” appears just once in the Scriptures, and it comes from a Hebrew term that means “Mountain of Megiddo.” ([Rev. 16:16]; ftn.) Megiddo was a city in ancient Israel. ([Josh. 17:11]) But Armageddon does not refer to any literal place on earth. Strictly speaking, it refers to the situation to which “the kings of the entire inhabited earth” are gathered in opposition to Jehovah.—[Rev. 16:14]. w19.09 8 ¶1-3

^ (Rev. 16:16) And they gathered them together to the place that is called in Hebrew Armageddon.*

Greek, Har Ma·ge·donʹ, from a Hebrew term meaning “Mountain of Megiddo.”

^ (Rev. 1:3) Happy is the one who reads aloud and those who hear the words of this prophecy and who observe the things written in it, for the appointed time is near.

^ (Rev. 11:18) But the nations became wrathful, and your own wrath came, and the appointed time came for the dead to be judged and to reward your slaves the prophets and the holy ones and those fearing your name, the small and the great, and to bring to ruin those ruining* the earth.”

Or “to destroy those who are destroying.”

^ (Rev. 16:16) And they gathered them together to the place that is called in Hebrew Armageddon.*

Greek, Har Ma·ge·donʹ, from a Hebrew term meaning “Mountain of Megiddo.”

^ (Josh. 17:11) In the territories of Isʹsa·char and Ashʹer, Ma·nasʹseh was given Beth-sheʹan and its dependent* towns, Ibʹle·am and its dependent towns, the inhabitants of Dor and its dependent towns, the inhabitants of En-dor and its dependent towns, the inhabitants of Taʹa·nach and its dependent towns, and the inhabitants of Me·gidʹdo and its dependent towns, three of the heights.

Or “surrounding.”

^ (Rev. 16:14) They are, in fact, expressions inspired by demons and they perform signs, and they go out to the kings of the entire inhabited earth, to gather them together to the war of the great day of God the Almighty.

Saturday, February 13

She had not been able to get a cure from anyone.—[Luke 8:43].

The woman desperately needed help. She had gone to many physicians, hoping to find relief. After 12 years of misery, she still had not been healed. According to the Law, she was unclean. ([Lev. 15:25]) Then she heard that Jesus could cure those who were suffering, so she went to find him. When she found him, she touched the fringe of his outer garment, and immediately she was cured! But Jesus did more than heal her body—he restored her dignity. For example, when talking with her, he used the warm yet respectful term “daughter.” How truly refreshed, or energized, that woman must have felt! ([Luke 8:44-48]) Notice that the woman went to Jesus. She took the initiative. The same is true today—we must make the effort to “come to” Jesus. At present, Jesus will not miraculously cure the physical sicknesses of those who “come to” him. But he still extends the invitation: “Come to me, . . . and I will refresh you.”—[Matt. 11:28]. w19.09 20 ¶2-3

^ (Luke 8:43) Now there was a woman who had a flow of blood for 12 years, and she had not been able to get a cure from anyone.

^ (Lev. 15:25) “‘When a woman’s discharge of blood flows for many days when it is not the regular time of her menstruation, or if she should have a flow longer than her usual menstruation, she will be unclean during all the days of her discharge, as in the days of her menstrual impurity.

^ (Luke 8:44-48) She approached from behind and touched the fringe* of his outer garment, and immediately her flow of blood stopped. 45 So Jesus said: “Who touched me?” When they were all denying it, Peter said: “Instructor, the crowds are hemming you in and pressing against you.” 46 But Jesus said: “Someone touched me, for I know* that power went out of me.” 47 Seeing that she had not escaped notice, the woman came trembling and fell down before him and declared before all the people why she touched him and how she was healed immediately. 48 But he said to her: “Daughter, your faith has made you well.* Go in peace.”

Or “edge; border; tassel.”

Or “perceived.”

Or “has saved you.”

^ (Matt. 11:28) Come to me, all you who are toiling* and loaded down, and I will refresh you.

Or “struggling hard.” Or possibly, “weary; tired.”

Monday, February 15

There will be great tribulation such as has not occurred since the world’s beginning until now, no, nor will occur again.—[Matt. 24:21].

During the great tribulation, people will be shocked as they see everything that they once thought to be so stable in the world begin to fail. They will be in “anguish,” fearing for their very lives as they enter the darkest period of human existence. (Zeph. 1:14, 15) At that time, life will likely get more difficult even for Jehovah’s people. Because we remain no part of the world, we may suffer some hardships. We may have to go without certain necessities. “The faithful and discreet slave” has been preparing us to stay faithful through the great tribulation. ([Matt. 24:45]) This has been done in many ways, but consider one example: our timely convention programs for the years 2016-2018. Through those programs, we have been encouraged to strengthen the qualities that we need as we near Jehovah’s day. w19.10 14 ¶2; 16 ¶10; 17 ¶12

^ (Matt. 24:21) for then there will be great tribulation such as has not occurred since the world’s beginning until now, no, nor will occur again.

^ (Zeph. 1:14, 15) The great day of Jehovah is near! It is near and it is approaching very quickly!* The sound of the day of Jehovah is bitter. There a warrior cries out. 15 That day is a day of fury, A day of distress and anguish, A day of storm and desolation, A day of darkness and gloom, A day of clouds and thick gloom,

Or “hurrying rapidly!”

^ (Matt. 24:45) “Who really is the faithful and discreet slave whom his master appointed over his domestics, to give them their food at the proper time?

Tuesday, February 16

You cannot be partaking of “the table of Jehovah” and the table of demons.—[1 Cor. 10:21].

Once we swallow food, automatic processes take over and the nutrients in the food eventually become part of our bodies. A good diet can make us healthier; a poor diet will make us unhealthy. The results may not become evident overnight, but they will become evident in time. Similarly, when we choose our entertainment, we have control over what we put into our mind. After that, automatic processes take over and our mind and heart are affected. Good entertainment can refresh us; unwholesome entertainment will harm us. (Jas. 1:14, 15) The effects of bad entertainment may not be immediately evident, but they will eventually become obvious. That is why the Bible warns us: “Whatever a person is sowing, this he will also reap; because the one sowing with a view to his flesh will reap corruption from his flesh.” ([Gal. 6:7, 8]) How important it is for us to reject all entertainment that promotes things that Jehovah hates!—[Ps. 97:10]. w19.10 30 ¶12-14

^ (1 Cor. 10:21) You cannot be drinking the cup of Jehovah and the cup of demons; you cannot be partaking of “the table of Jehovah” and the table of demons.

^ (Jas. 1:14, 15) But each one is tried by being drawn out and enticed* by his own desire. 15 Then the desire, when it has become fertile,* gives birth to sin; in turn sin, when it has been carried out, brings forth death.

Or “caught as by bait.”

Lit., “has conceived.”

^ (Gal. 6:7, 8) Do not be misled: God is not one to be mocked. For whatever a person is sowing, this he will also reap; 8 because the one sowing with a view to his flesh will reap corruption from his flesh, but the one sowing with a view to the spirit will reap everlasting life from the spirit.

^ (Ps. 97:10) O you who love Jehovah, hate what is bad. He is guarding the lives* of his loyal ones; He rescues them from the hand* of the wicked.

Or “souls.”

Or “power.”

Thursday, February 18

Keep on asking, and it will be given you; keep on seeking, and you will find; keep on knocking, and it will be opened to you.—[Luke 11:9].

To receive the help of holy spirit, we must pray for it with persistence. ([Luke 11:13]) Jesus’ illustration at [Luke 11:5-9] helps us to see why Jehovah will give us holy spirit. The man in the illustration wanted to be a good host. He felt compelled to serve food to his late-night visitor but had nothing to offer him. Jesus said that the neighbor responded because of the man’s bold persistence in asking for bread. What was Jesus’ point? If an imperfect human is willing to help a persistent neighbor, how much more so will our kind heavenly Father help those who persistently ask him for holy spirit! Therefore, we can pray with confidence that Jehovah will respond to our urgent request for holy spirit. ([Ps. 10:17;][66:19]) We can be sure that in spite of Satan’s relentless efforts to defeat us, we will be victorious. w19.11 13 ¶17-19

^ (Luke 11:9) So I say to you, keep on asking, and it will be given you; keep on seeking, and you will find; keep on knocking, and it will be opened to you.

^ (Luke 11:13) Therefore, if you, although being wicked, know how to give good gifts to your children, how much more so will the Father in heaven give holy spirit to those asking him!”

^ (Luke 11:5-9) Then he said to them: “Suppose one of you has a friend and you go to him at midnight and say to him, ‘Friend, lend me three loaves, 6 because one of my friends has just come to me on a journey and I have nothing to offer him.’ 7 But that one replies from inside: ‘Stop bothering me. The door is already locked, and my young children are with me in bed. I cannot get up and give you anything.’ 8 I tell you, even if he will not get up and give him anything because of being his friend, certainly because of his bold persistence he will get up and give him whatever he needs. 9 So I say to you, keep on asking, and it will be given you; keep on seeking, and you will find; keep on knocking, and it will be opened to you.

^ (Ps. 10:17) But you will hear the request of the meek, O Jehovah. You will make their hearts firm and pay close attention to them.

^ (Ps. 66:19) But God did hear; He paid attention to my prayer.

Saturday, February 20

Complete what you started to do.—[2 Cor. 8:11].

Jehovah allows us to choose our course in life. He teaches us how to make good choices, and he helps us to succeed when we make decisions that please him. ([Ps. 119:173]) The more we apply the wisdom found in God’s Word, the better we become at making good decisions. ([Heb. 5:14]) Even when we make a wise decision, however, we may struggle to complete what we started. Consider some examples: A young brother decides to read the entire Bible. He does well for a few weeks but then stops for some reason. A sister decides to serve as a regular pioneer but keeps pushing back the date when she will begin. A body of elders makes a unanimous decision to be more involved in shepherding those in the congregation but after many months has not acted on it. These situations differ, but they have something in common. Those decisions were not fully implemented. w19.11 26 ¶1-2

^ (2 Cor. 8:11) So now, also complete what you started to do, so that your readiness to act may be completed according to the means you have available.

^ (Ps. 119:173) May your hand be ready to help me, Because I choose to obey your orders.

^ (Heb. 5:14) But solid food belongs to mature people, to those who through use have their powers of discernment* trained to distinguish both right and wrong.

Or “their perceptive powers.”

Monday, February 22

These are my fellow workers for the Kingdom of God, and they have become a source of great comfort to me.—[Col. 4:11].

The apostle Paul faced one life-threatening situation after another. (2 Cor. 11:23-28) He also had to endure “a thorn in the flesh,” possibly some sort of health problem. ([2 Cor. 12:7]) And he had to cope with disappointment when Demas, his onetime fellow worker, abandoned him “because [Demas] loved the present system of things.” ([2 Tim. 4:10]) Paul was a courageous spirit-anointed Christian who unselfishly helped others, but at times even he felt discouraged. ([Rom. 9:1, 2]) Paul received the comfort and support he needed. How? Jehovah certainly used His holy spirit to strengthen him. ([2 Cor. 4:7;][Phil. 4:13]) Jehovah also comforted him through fellow Christians. Paul described some of his fellow workers as “a source of great comfort.” ([Col. 4:11]) Among the ones he mentioned by name were Aristarchus, Tychicus, and Mark. They strengthened Paul, helping him to endure. w20.01 8 ¶2-3

^ (Col. 4:11) and Jesus who is called Justus, who are of those circumcised. Only these are my fellow workers for the Kingdom of God, and they have become a source of great comfort* to me.

Or “a strengthening aid.”

^ (2 Cor. 11:23-28) Are they ministers of Christ? I reply like a madman, I am more outstandingly one: I have done more work, been imprisoned more often, suffered countless beatings, and experienced many near-deaths. 24 Five times I received 40 strokes less one from the Jews, 25 three times I was beaten with rods, once I was stoned, three times I experienced shipwreck, a night and a day I have spent in the open sea; 26 in journeys often, in dangers from rivers, in dangers from robbers, in dangers from my own people, in dangers from the nations, in dangers in the city, in dangers in the wilderness, in dangers at sea, in dangers among false brothers, 27 in labor and toil, in sleepless nights often, in hunger and thirst, frequently without food, in cold and lacking clothing. 28 Besides those things of an external kind, there is what rushes in on me from day to day:* the anxiety for all the congregations.

Or “the daily pressure on me.”

^ (2 Cor. 12:7) just because of receiving such extraordinary revelations. To keep me from becoming overly exalted, I was given a thorn in the flesh, an angel of Satan, to keep slapping me, so that I might not be overly exalted.

^ (2 Tim. 4:10) For Deʹmas has forsaken me because he loved the present system of things,* and he has gone to Thes·sa·lo·niʹca, Cresʹcens to Ga·laʹti·a, Titus to Dal·maʹtia.

Or “present age.” See Glossary.

^ (Rom. 9:1, 2) I am telling the truth in Christ; I am not lying, as my conscience bears witness with me in holy spirit, 2 that I have great grief and unceasing pain in my heart.

^ (2 Cor. 4:7) However, we have this treasure in earthen vessels, so that the power beyond what is normal may be God’s and not from us.

^ (Phil. 4:13) For all things I have the strength through the one who gives me power.

^ (Col. 4:11) and Jesus who is called Justus, who are of those circumcised. Only these are my fellow workers for the Kingdom of God, and they have become a source of great comfort* to me.

Or “a strengthening aid.”

Tuesday, February 23

He has enlightened the eyes of your heart.—[Eph. 1:18].

Jesus indicated that it is impossible to explain exactly to someone who has not been anointed how it feels to be “born again,” or to be “born from the spirit.” ([John 3:3-8]) What change in thinking takes place when Christians are anointed? Before Jehovah anointed these Christians, they treasured the hope of living forever on earth. They looked forward with great eagerness to the time when Jehovah would remove all wickedness and make the earth a paradise. Perhaps they imagined themselves welcoming back a family member or a friend who had died. But after they were anointed, they started to think differently. Why is that? They did not become dissatisfied with that earthly hope. They did not change their mind because of emotional stress or turmoil. They did not suddenly feel that they would find living forever on earth to be boring. Instead, Jehovah used his holy spirit to change the way that they think and the hope that they cherish. w20.01 22 ¶9-11

^ (Eph. 1:18) He has enlightened the eyes of your heart, so that you may know to what hope he called you, what glorious riches he holds as an inheritance for the holy ones,

^ (John 3:3-8) In response Jesus said to him: “Most truly I say to you, unless anyone is born again, he cannot see the Kingdom of God.” 4 Nic·o·deʹmus said to him: “How can a man be born when he is old? He cannot enter into the womb of his mother a second time and be born, can he?” 5 Jesus answered: “Most truly I say to you, unless anyone is born from water and spirit, he cannot enter into the Kingdom of God. 6 What has been born from the flesh is flesh, and what has been born from the spirit is spirit. 7 Do not be amazed because I told you: You people must be born again. 8 The wind blows where it wants to, and you hear the sound of it, but you do not know where it comes from and where it is going. So it is with everyone who has been born from the spirit.”

Wednesday, February 24

Let every person be in subjection to the superior authorities.—[Rom. 13:1].

Under the Law that God gave Israel, appointed men handled not only spiritual matters but also civil and criminal cases. But under “the law of the Christ,” the elders’ role is to handle the spiritual aspects of the wrongdoing. ([Gal. 6:2]) They recognize that the secular authorities have the God-given responsibility to handle civil and criminal cases. That includes the authority to impose such penalties as fines or imprisonments. ([Rom. 13:2-4]) How do elders handle the spiritual aspects of serious wrongdoing? They use the Scriptures to weigh matters and make decisions. They keep in mind that love is the foundation of the law of the Christ. Love moves the elders to consider: What needs to be done to help any in the congregation who have been victims of the wrongdoing? Regarding the wrongdoer, love moves the elders to consider: Is he repentant? Can we help him to regain his spiritual health? w19.05 7 ¶23-24

^ (Rom. 13:1) Let every person be in subjection to the superior authorities, for there is no authority except by God; the existing authorities stand placed in their relative positions by God.

^ (Gal. 6:2) Go on carrying the burdens of one another, and in this way you will fulfill the law of the Christ.

^ (Rom. 13:2-4) Therefore, whoever opposes* the authority has taken a stand against the arrangement of God; those who have taken a stand against it will bring judgment against themselves. 3 For those rulers are an object of fear, not to the good deed, but to the bad. Do you want to be free of fear of the authority? Keep doing good, and you will have praise from it; 4 for it is God’s minister* to you for your good. But if you are doing what is bad, be in fear, for it is not without purpose that it bears the sword. It is God’s minister, an avenger to express wrath against the one practicing what is bad.

Or “resists.”

Lit., “servant.”

Thursday, February 25

I live because of the Father.—[John 6:57].

Jesus acknowledged that his Father was the Source and Sustainer of his life when he stated the above. Jesus completely trusted in his Father, and Jehovah supplied his physical needs. Most important, Jehovah cared for Jesus spiritually. ([Matt. 4:4]) Jehovah also provides for our spiritual needs. Through his Word, he has revealed the truth about himself, his purpose, the meaning of life, and the future. He showed us personal attention when we first learned the truth, using our parents or another teacher to help us come to know him. And we continue to receive kind assistance from loving congregation elders and other mature brothers and sisters. In addition, Jehovah instructs us through our congregation meetings, where we learn alongside our spiritual family. In these and other ways, Jehovah shows his fatherly interest in all of us.—[Ps. 32:8]. w20.02 3 ¶8; 5 ¶13

^ (John 6:57) Just as the living Father sent me and I live because of the Father, so also the one who feeds on me will live because of me.

^ (Matt. 4:4) But he answered: “It is written: ‘Man must live, not on bread alone, but on every word that comes from Jehovah’s mouth.’”

^ (Ps. 32:8) “I will give you insight and instruct you in the way you should go. I will give you advice with my eye upon you.

Sunday, February 28

Since we have this ministry . . . , we do not give up.—[2 Cor. 4:1].

The apostle Paul set a good example in making the ministry the most important activity in his life. When he was in Corinth during his second missionary journey, he was low on funds and had to spend some time making tents. He worked at this trade to support himself in the ministry so that he could declare the good news to the Corinthians “without cost” to them. ([2 Cor. 11:7]) Although Paul had to do some secular work, he continued to give priority to the ministry, and he preached on every Sabbath. After his circumstances improved, Paul was able to give more attention to preaching. He “began to be intensely occupied with the word, witnessing to the Jews to prove that Jesus is the Christ.” ([Acts 18:3-5;][2 Cor. 11:9]) Later, when he was under house arrest in Rome for two years, Paul witnessed to visitors and wrote letters. ([Acts 28:16,][30, 31]) Paul was determined not to allow anything to interfere with his ministry. w19.04 4 ¶9

^ (2 Cor. 4:1) Therefore, since we have this ministry through the mercy that was shown us, we do not give up.

^ (2 Cor. 11:7) Or did I commit a sin by humbling myself that you might be exalted, because I gladly declared the good news of God to you without cost?

^ (Acts 18:3-5) and because he had the same trade, he stayed at their home and worked with them, for they were tentmakers by trade. 4 He would give a talk in the synagogue every sabbath and would persuade Jews and Greeks. 5 When, now, both Silas and Timothy came down from Mac·e·doʹni·a, Paul began to be intensely occupied with the word, witnessing to the Jews to prove that Jesus is the Christ.

^ (2 Cor. 11:9) Yet, when I was present with you and I fell into need, I did not become a burden on anyone, for the brothers who came from Mac·e·doʹni·a abundantly supplied my needs. Yes, in every way I kept myself from becoming a burden to you and will continue to do so.

^ (Acts 28:16) When finally we entered Rome, Paul was permitted to stay by himself with the soldier guarding him.

^ (Acts 28:30, 31) So he remained there for an entire two years in his own rented house, and he would kindly receive all those who came to him, 31 preaching the Kingdom of God to them and teaching about the Lord Jesus Christ with the greatest freeness of speech, without hindrance.

Saturday, March 6

Be transformed by making your mind over, so that you may prove to yourselves the good and acceptable and perfect will of God.—[Rom. 12:2].

What do we need to do? By regular study, we can prove to ourselves the truths we have learned from the Bible. We can be fully convinced that Jehovah’s standards are right. Then, like a tree with solid roots, we will be firmly rooted, “stabilized in the faith.” ([Col. 2:6, 7]) Remember, no one else can stabilize your faith for you, so continue to be made new in your dominant mental attitude. Pray constantly; plead for the help of Jehovah’s spirit. Meditate deeply; continue to examine your thinking and motives. Seek good associates; surround yourself with individuals who will help you to transform your thinking. By doing so, you will counteract the poisonous effects of Satan’s world and successfully overturn “reasonings and every lofty thing raised up against the knowledge of God.”—[2 Cor. 10:5]. w19.06 13 ¶17-18

^ (Rom. 12:2) And stop being molded by this system of things, but be transformed by making your mind over, so that you may prove to yourselves the good and acceptable and perfect will of God.

^ (Col. 2:6, 7) Therefore, just as you have accepted Christ Jesus the Lord, go on walking in union with him, 7 being rooted and built up in him and being stabilized in the faith, just as you were taught, and overflowing with thanksgiving.

^ (2 Cor. 10:5) For we are overturning reasonings and every lofty thing raised up against the knowledge of God, and we are bringing every thought into captivity to make it obedient to the Christ;

Tuesday, March 9

A slave of the Lord . . . needs to be gentle toward all, qualified to teach.—[2 Tim. 2:24].

Often, people respond well to our message, not because of what we say, but because of the way we say it. They appreciate it when we are kind, tactful, and genuinely interested in them. We do not force them to hear our point of view. Instead, we try to discern the reasons for their view of religion and to be sensitive to their feelings. For instance, when speaking with Jews, Paul reasoned from the Scriptures. However, when he spoke with Greek philosophers at the Areopagus, he made no direct reference to the Bible. (Acts 17:2, 3,[22-31]) How can we follow Paul’s example? If you meet a person who does not accept the Bible, it may be best not to make direct references to it when reasoning with him. If you sense that a person might be uncomfortable being seen reading the Bible with you, try showing him scriptures in a less obvious way, such as on an electronic device. w19.07 21 ¶5-6

^ (2 Tim. 2:24) For a slave of the Lord does not need to fight, but needs to be gentle* toward all, qualified to teach, showing restraint when wronged,

Or “tactful.”

^ (Acts 17:2, 3) So according to Paul’s custom he went inside to them, and for three sabbaths he reasoned with them from the Scriptures, 3 explaining and proving by references that it was necessary for the Christ to suffer and to rise from the dead, saying: “This is the Christ, this Jesus whom I am proclaiming to you.”

^ (Acts 17:22-31) Paul now stood in the midst of the Ar·e·opʹa·gus and said: “Men of Athens, I see that in all things you seem to be more given to the fear of the deities* than others are. 23 For instance, while passing along and carefully observing your objects of veneration,* I found even an altar on which had been inscribed ‘To an Unknown God.’ Therefore, what you are unknowingly worshipping, this I am declaring to you. 24 The God who made the world and all the things in it, being, as he is, Lord of heaven and earth, does not dwell in handmade temples; 25 nor is he served by human hands as if he needed anything, because he himself gives to all people life and breath and all things. 26 And he made out of one man every nation of men to dwell on the entire surface of the earth, and he decreed the appointed times and the set limits of where men would dwell, 27 so that they would seek God, if they might grope for him and really find him, although, in fact, he is not far off from each one of us. 28 For by* him we have life and move and exist, even as some of your own poets have said, ‘For we are also his children.’* 29 “Therefore, since we are the children* of God, we should not think that the Divine Being is like gold or silver or stone, like something sculptured by the art and design of humans. 30 True, God has overlooked the times of such ignorance; but now he is declaring to all people everywhere that they should repent. 31 Because he has set a day on which he purposes to judge the inhabited earth in righteousness by a man whom he has appointed, and he has provided a guarantee to all men by resurrecting him from the dead.”

Or “more religious.”

Or “worship.”

Or “because of.” Lit., “in.”

Or “progeny.”

Or “progeny.”

Wednesday, March 10

Be careful not to let your heart be enticed to go astray and worship other gods.—[Deut. 11:16].

Satan cleverly tempted the Israelites to commit idolatry by taking advantage of their need to provide food for themselves. When the Israelites entered the Promised Land, they had to change their methods of growing food. While in Egypt, the Israelites irrigated the farmland by using water drawn from the Nile. However, the agricultural system in the Promised Land was based, not on water drawn from a huge river system, but on water gained from seasonal rains, as well as from the dew that watered the vegetation. (Deut. 11:10-15; Isa. 18:4, 5) Therefore, the Israelites had to learn new farming methods. But why did Jehovah warn against worshipping false gods while he was speaking about farming? Jehovah knew that his people would be tempted to learn useful skills from the pagan people around them and that the thinking of those Canaanite farmers was affected by their belief in Baal.—[Num. 25:3,][5;][Judg. 2:13;][1 Ki. 18:18]. w19.06 3 ¶4-6

^ (Deut. 11:16) Be careful not to let your heart be enticed to go astray and worship other gods and bow down to them.

^ (Deut. 11:10-15) “The land you are going to take possession of is not like the land of Egypt, out of which you came, where you used to sow your seed and irrigate it with your foot,* like a garden of vegetables. 11 But the land you are about to cross into and possess is a land of mountains and valley plains. It drinks the water that rains from the heavens; 12 it is a land that Jehovah your God is caring for. The eyes of Jehovah your God are constantly upon it, from the beginning of the year to the close of the year. 13 “And if you will diligently obey my commandments that I am commanding you today and love Jehovah your God and serve him with all your heart and all your soul,* 14 I will also give rain for your land at its appointed time, autumn rain and spring rain, and you will gather your grain and your new wine and your oil. 15 And I will provide vegetation in your fields for your livestock, and you will eat and be satisfied.

Or “water it with your foot,” that is, by some form of foot power, whether on a waterwheel or by forming and opening water channels.

See Glossary.

^ (Isa. 18:4, 5) For this is what Jehovah said to me: “I will remain undisturbed and look on* my established place, Like the shimmering heat along with the sunlight, Like the cloud of dew in the heat of harvest.  5 For before the harvest, When the blossom is finished and the bloom becomes a ripening grape, The shoots will be cut off with pruning shears And the tendrils will be lopped off and removed.

Or possibly, “from.”

^ (Num. 25:3) So Israel joined in worship of* the Baʹal of Peʹor, and Jehovah became enraged with Israel.

Or “attached itself to.”

^ (Num. 25:5) Then Moses said to the judges of Israel: “Each one of you should kill his men who joined in worship of* the Baʹal of Peʹor.”

Or “attached themselves to.”

^ (Judg. 2:13) They abandoned Jehovah and served Baʹal and the Ashʹto·reth images.

^ (1 Ki. 18:18) To this he said: “I have not brought trouble on Israel, but you and the house of your father have, by abandoning the commandments of Jehovah and by following the Baʹals.

Saturday, March 13

They gathered them together to . . . Armageddon.—[Rev. 16:16].

Why did Jehovah connect the final great war with Megiddo? Megiddo and the nearby Jezreel Valley were the sites of many battles. On occasion, Jehovah directly intervened in those battles. For example, “by the waters of Megiddo,” God helped Israelite Judge Barak defeat a Canaanite army led by a chief named Sisera. Barak and the prophetess Deborah thanked Jehovah for their miraculous victory. They sang: “From heaven the stars fought . . . against Sisera. . . . So let all your enemies perish, O Jehovah, but let those who love you be like the sun rising in its glory.” (Judg. 5:19-21,[31]) At Armageddon, God’s enemies will likewise perish, while those who love God will be saved. But there is one important difference between the two conflicts. At Armageddon, God’s people will not fight. They will not even be armed! Their “strength will be in keeping calm and showing trust” in Jehovah and his heavenly armies.—[Isa. 30:15;] Rev. 19:11-15. w19.09 9 ¶4-5

^ (Rev. 16:16) And they gathered them together to the place that is called in Hebrew Armageddon.*

Greek, Har Ma·ge·donʹ, from a Hebrew term meaning “Mountain of Megiddo.”

^ (Judg. 5:19-21) Kings came, they fought; The kings of Caʹnaan then fought In Taʹa·nach, by the waters of Me·gidʹdo. No spoil of silver did they take. 20 From heaven the stars fought; From their orbits they fought against Sisʹe·ra. 21 The torrent* of Kiʹshon washed them away, The ancient torrent,* the torrent* of Kiʹshon. You trampled down the powerful, O my soul.*

Or “stream.”

Or “stream.”

Or “stream.”

See Glossary.

^ (Judg. 5:31) So let all your enemies perish, O Jehovah, But let those who love you be like the sun rising in its glory.” And the land had rest* for 40 years.

Or “peace.”

^ (Isa. 30:15) For this is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah, the Holy One of Israel, says: “By returning to me and resting, you will be saved; Your strength will be in keeping calm and showing trust.” But you were unwilling.

^ (Rev. 19:11-15) I saw heaven opened, and look! a white horse. And the one seated on it is called Faithful and True, and he judges and carries on war in righteousness. 12 His eyes are a fiery flame, and on his head are many diadems.* He has a name written that no one knows but he himself, 13 and he is clothed with an outer garment stained* with blood, and he is called by the name The Word of God. 14 Also, the armies in heaven were following him on white horses, and they were clothed in white, clean, fine linen. 15 And out of his mouth protrudes a sharp, long sword with which to strike the nations, and he will shepherd them with a rod of iron. Moreover, he treads the winepress of the fury of the wrath of God the Almighty.

Or “royal headbands.”

Or possibly, “sprinkled.”

Sunday, March 14

Come to me.—[Matt. 11:28].

One way to “come to” Jesus is by learning as much as we can about the things he said and did. ([Luke 1:1-4]) Nobody else can do this for us—we must study these accounts for ourselves. We also “come to” Jesus by making the decision to get baptized and become a disciple of Christ. Another way to “come to” Jesus is by going to the congregation elders if we need help. Jesus uses these “gifts in men” to care for his sheep. ([Eph. 4:7, 8,][11;][John 21:16;] 1 Pet. 5:1-3) We must take the initiative to ask for their help. We cannot expect the elders to read our minds and know what we need. Consider what a brother named Julian says: “I asked for help, and that shepherding visit turned out to be one of the best gifts I have ever received.” Loyal elders, such as the two who visited Julian, can help us to know “the mind of Christ,” that is, to understand and imitate his thinking and attitude. ([1 Cor. 2:16;][1 Pet. 2:21]) This really is one of the best gifts they can give us. w19.09 21 ¶4-5

^ (Matt. 11:28) Come to me, all you who are toiling* and loaded down, and I will refresh you.

Or “struggling hard.” Or possibly, “weary; tired.”

^ (Luke 1:1-4) Seeing that many have undertaken to compile an account of the facts that are given full credence among us, 2 just as these were handed down to us by those who from the beginning were eyewitnesses and attendants of the message, 3 I resolved also, because I have traced all things from the start with accuracy, to write them to you in logical order, most excellent The·ophʹi·lus, 4 so that you may know fully the certainty of the things that you have been taught orally.

^ (Eph. 4:7, 8) Now undeserved kindness was given to each one of us according to how the Christ measured out the free gift. 8 For it says: “When he ascended on high he carried away captives; he gave gifts in men.”

^ (Eph. 4:11) And he gave some as apostles, some as prophets, some as evangelizers,* some as shepherds and teachers,

Or “proclaimers of the good news.”

^ (John 21:16) Again he said to him a second time: “Simon son of John, do you love me?” He replied: “Yes, Lord, you know I have affection for you.” He said to him: “Shepherd my little sheep.”

^ (1 Pet. 5:1-3) Therefore, as a fellow elder, a witness of the sufferings of the Christ and a sharer of the glory that is to be revealed, I make this appeal* to the elders among you: 2 Shepherd the flock of God under your care, serving as overseers,* not under compulsion, but willingly before God; not for love of dishonest gain, but eagerly; 3 not lording it over those who are God’s inheritance, but becoming examples to the flock.

Or “exhortation.”

Or “carefully watching over it.”

^ (1 Cor. 2:16) For “who has come to know the mind of Jehovah, so that he may instruct him?” But we do have the mind of Christ.

^ (1 Pet. 2:21) In fact, to this course you were called, because even Christ suffered for you, leaving a model for you to follow his steps closely.

Thursday, March 18

Each one is tried by being drawn out and enticed by his own desire.—[Jas. 1:14].

We must carefully control not only the type of entertainment we enjoy but also the amount of time we spend enjoying it. If we do not, we may spend more time on entertaining ourselves than we do on serving Jehovah. First, find out how much time you are actually spending on it. Why not keep a record for one week? Write on a calendar how many hours you spend watching television, surfing the Internet, and playing games on your mobile device. If you feel that you are spending an excessive amount of time, try making a schedule. Assign time to the more important things first, and then allot time for entertainment. Next, ask Jehovah to help you stick to your schedule. That way you will have the time and energy you need for personal Bible study, family worship, congregation meetings, and serving Jehovah in the preaching and teaching work. You may also be less likely to feel guilty about the time you spend on entertainment. w19.10 30 ¶14, 16; 31 ¶17

^ (Jas. 1:14) But each one is tried by being drawn out and enticed* by his own desire.

Or “caught as by bait.”

Friday, March 19

I have the desire to do what is fine but not the ability to carry it out.—[Rom. 7:18].

About 55 C.E., the Corinthians made an important decision. Learning of the needs of their brothers in Jerusalem and Judea, they resolved to donate to a combined effort to help them. ([1 Cor. 16:1;][2 Cor. 8:6]) A few months later, though, the apostle Paul learned that the Corinthians had not followed through. As a result, their gift would not likely be ready in time for it to be taken to Jerusalem along with the contributions from the other congregations. (2 Cor. 9:4, 5) The Corinthians had made a good decision, and Paul commended them for their outstanding faith and their earnest desire to be generous. But he also had to encourage them to complete what they had started. ([2 Cor. 8:7,][10, 11]) Their experience teaches us that even faithful Christians may struggle to implement a good decision. Why? Because of imperfection, we may simply procrastinate. Or unforeseen events might make it impossible for us to follow through.—[Eccl. 9:11]. w19.11 26-27 ¶3-5

^ (Rom. 7:18) For I know that in me, that is, in my flesh, there dwells nothing good; for I have the desire to do what is fine but not the ability to carry it out.

^ (1 Cor. 16:1) Now concerning the collection for the holy ones, you may follow the directions I gave to the congregations of Ga·laʹti·a.

^ (2 Cor. 8:6) So we encouraged Titus that, just as he had initiated this work among you, he should also complete this same kind giving on your part.

^ (2 Cor. 9:4, 5) Otherwise, if the Mac·e·doʹni·ans should come with me and find you not ready, we—not to mention you—should be put to shame by our confidence in you. 5 So I thought it necessary to encourage the brothers to come to you ahead of time and to get your promised bountiful gift ready in advance, so that this might be ready as a generous gift, and not as something extorted.

^ (2 Cor. 8:7) Nevertheless, just as you abound in everything, in faith and word and knowledge and all earnestness and in our love for you, may you also abound in this kind giving.

^ (2 Cor. 8:10, 11) And in this I give my opinion: This is for your benefit, seeing that already a year ago you not only initiated the action but also showed your desire to do it. 11 So now, also complete what you started to do, so that your readiness to act may be completed according to the means you have available.

^ (Eccl. 9:11) I have seen something further under the sun, that the swift do not always win the race, nor do the mighty win the battle, nor do the wise always have the food, nor do the intelligent always have the riches, nor do those with knowledge always have success, because time and unexpected events* overtake them all.

Or “unforeseen occurrence.”

Saturday, March 20

Take up the large shield of faith.—[Eph. 6:16].

Like a large shield that protects most of the body, your faith protects you from the immoral, violent, and godless influences of this corrupt system of things. As Christians, we wage a spiritual battle and our enemies include wicked spirits. ([Eph. 6:10-12]) How can you be sure that you are ready to face tests? First, you must pray for God’s help. Then, you need to use God’s Word to help you see yourself as God sees you. ([Heb. 4:12]) The Bible states: “Trust in Jehovah with all your heart, and do not rely on your own understanding.” ([Prov. 3:5, 6]) With that in mind, why not review some of the decisions you have made recently? For example, have you faced a serious financial problem? Did Jehovah’s promise recorded at [Hebrews 13:5] come to mind: “I will never leave you, and I will never abandon you”? Did that promise give you confidence that Jehovah would help you? If so, that indicates that you are keeping your shield of faith in good condition. w19.11 14 ¶1, 4

^ (Eph. 6:16) Besides all of this, take up the large shield of faith, with which you will be able to extinguish all the wicked one’s burning arrows.*

Or “missiles; darts.”

^ (Eph. 6:10-12) Finally, go on acquiring power in the Lord and in the mightiness of his strength. 11 Put on the complete suit of armor from God so that you may be able to stand firm against the crafty acts* of the Devil; 12 because we have a struggle,* not against blood and flesh, but against the governments, against the authorities, against the world rulers of this darkness, against the wicked spirit forces in the heavenly places.

Or “the schemes.”

Lit., “wrestling.”

^ (Heb. 4:12) For the word of God is alive and exerts power and is sharper than any two-edged sword and pierces even to the dividing of soul* and spirit,* and of joints from the marrow, and is able to discern thoughts and intentions of the heart.

See Glossary.

See Glossary.

^ (Prov. 3:5, 6) Trust in Jehovah with all your heart, And do not rely* on your own understanding.  6 In all your ways take notice of him, And he will make your paths straight.

Lit., “lean.”

^ (Heb. 13:5) Let your way of life be free of the love of money, while you are content with the present things. For he has said: “I will never leave you, and I will never abandon you.”

Monday, March 22

A Jubilee is what that 50th year will become for you.—[Lev. 25:11].

How did the Israelites benefit from the Jubilee? Well, suppose an Israelite had fallen into debt and, as a result, had been forced to sell his land to pay off the debt. During the Jubilee year, that land was to be returned to him. Therefore, the man could “return to his property,” and the future inheritance of his children would not be lost. In another case, a man who fell on hard times might have had to sell one of his children—or even himself—into slavery in order to pay a debt. During the Jubilee year, the slave was to “return to his family.” ([Lev. 25:10]) So no one would become a slave permanently with no hope! In addition Jehovah said: “No one among you should become poor, for Jehovah will surely bless you in the land that Jehovah your God is giving you to possess as an inheritance.” ([Deut. 15:4]) What a contrast to what is happening in the world today, where the rich often get richer and the poor, poorer! w19.12 8-9 ¶3-4

^ (Lev. 25:11) A Jubilee is what that 50th year will become for you. You will not sow seed or reap what grew on its own from leftover grain nor gather the grapes of unpruned vines.

^ (Lev. 25:10) You must sanctify the 50th year and proclaim liberty in the land to all its inhabitants. It will become a Jubilee for you, and each of you will return to his property and each of you should return to his family.

^ (Deut. 15:4) However, no one among you should become poor, for Jehovah will surely bless you in the land that Jehovah your God is giving you to possess as an inheritance,

Thursday, March 25

[Christ] was favorably heard for his godly fear.—[Heb. 5:7].

On the yearly Day of Atonement, the high priest had to burn the incense before he could offer up the sacrifices. In that way, he made sure that he would have God’s approval when offering up the sacrifices. While on earth, Jesus had to do something important—something more important than providing salvation for mankind—before he could offer up his life in sacrifice. What was that? By living a life of integrity and loyalty, Jesus had to prepare the way for Jehovah to accept his sacrifice. In that way, Jesus would prove that doing things Jehovah’s way is the right way to live. Jesus would vindicate his Father’s sovereignty, or way of ruling. Throughout his earthly life, Jesus maintained perfect obedience to Jehovah’s righteous standards. No temptation or trial could weaken his desire to defend his Father’s way of ruling.—[Phil. 2:8]. w19.11 21 ¶6-7

Memorial Bible reading: (Daytime events: Nisan 11) Luke 20:1-47

^ (Heb. 5:7) During his life on earth,* Christ offered up supplications and also petitions, with strong outcries and tears, to the One who was able to save him out of death, and he was favorably heard for his godly fear.

Lit., “In the days of his flesh.”

^ (Phil. 2:8) More than that, when he came as a man,* he humbled himself and became obedient to the point of death, yes, death on a torture stake.*

Lit., “when he was found in appearance as a man.”

See Glossary.

Friday, March 26

You are the ones who have stuck with me in my trials.—[Luke 22:28].

Throughout Jesus’ challenging ministry, the faithful apostles proved to be real friends to Jesus. ([Prov. 18:24]) Jesus valued such friends. During his ministry, none of his fleshly brothers put faith in him. ([John 7:3-5]) At one point, his relatives even thought that he had gone mad. ([Mark 3:21]) By contrast, Jesus could say the words of today’s text to the faithful apostles on the night before his death. The apostles occasionally disappointed Jesus, but he looked past their faults and saw that they had faith in him. ([Matt. 26:40;] Mark 10:13, 14; John 6:66-69) On the last night with them before he was executed, Jesus said to these loyal men: “I have called you friends, because I have made known to you all the things I have heard from my Father.” ([John 15:15]) Without a doubt, Jesus’ friends were a great source of encouragement to him. w19.04 11 ¶11-12

Memorial Bible reading: (Daytime events: Nisan 12) [Luke 22:1-6;] Mark 14:1, 2,[10, 11]

^ (Luke 22:28) “However, you are the ones who have stuck with me in my trials;

^ (Prov. 18:24) There are companions ready to crush one another, But there is a friend who sticks closer than a brother.

^ (John 7:3-5) So his brothers said to him: “Leave here and go into Ju·deʹa, so that your disciples may also see the works you are doing. 4 For no one does anything in secret when he seeks to be known publicly. If you are doing these things, show yourself to the world.” 5 His brothers were, in fact, not exercising faith in him.

^ (Mark 3:21) But when his relatives heard about it, they went out to seize him, for they were saying: “He has gone out of his mind.”

^ (Matt. 26:40) He returned to the disciples and found them sleeping, and he said to Peter: “Could you not so much as keep on the watch for one hour with me?

^ (Mark 10:13, 14) People now began bringing him young children for him to touch them, but the disciples reprimanded them. 14 At seeing this, Jesus was indignant and said to them: “Let the young children come to me; do not try to stop them, for the Kingdom of God belongs to such ones.

^ (John 6:66-69) Because of this, many of his disciples went off to the things behind and would no longer walk with him. 67 So Jesus said to the Twelve: “You do not want to go also, do you?” 68 Simon Peter answered him: “Lord, whom shall we go away to? You have sayings of everlasting life. 69 We have believed and have come to know that you are the Holy One of God.”

^ (John 15:15) I no longer call you slaves, because a slave does not know what his master does. But I have called you friends, because I have made known to you all the things I have heard from my Father.

^ (Luke 22:1-6) Now the Festival of the Unleavened Bread, which is called Passover, was getting near. 2 And the chief priests and the scribes were looking for an effective way to get rid of him, because they were afraid of the people. 3 Then Satan entered into Judas, the one called Is·carʹi·ot, who was numbered among the Twelve, 4 and he went off and talked with the chief priests and temple captains about how to betray him to them. 5 They were delighted at this and agreed to give him silver money. 6 So he consented and began looking for a good opportunity to betray him to them without a crowd around.

^ (Mark 14:1, 2) Now the Passover and the Festival of Unleavened Bread was two days later. And the chief priests and the scribes were looking for a way to seize* him by cunning* and kill him; 2 for they were saying: “Not at the festival; perhaps there might be an uproar of the people.”

Or “arrest.”

Or “deceit; craftiness.”

^ (Mark 14:10, 11) And Judas Is·carʹi·ot, one of the Twelve, went off to the chief priests in order to betray him to them. 11 When they heard it, they were delighted and promised to give him silver money. So he began seeking an opportunity to betray him.

Monday, March 29

[Jehovah] sent me to proclaim liberty to the captives . . . , to send the crushed ones away free.—[Luke 4:18].

Jesus opened the way to liberty from the oppressive doctrines taught by the religious leaders. Many Jews back then were enslaved to traditions and mistaken beliefs. (Matt. 5:31-37; 15:1-11) Those who presumed to be spiritual guides were in a sense blind. In rejecting the Messiah and the spiritual enlightenment he offered, they remained in darkness and in sin. ([John 9:1,][14-16,][35-41]) By his correct teachings and good example, Jesus made known to meek ones a spiritual liberation. ([Mark 1:22;] 2:23–3:5) Also, Jesus provided liberation by freeing mankind from enslavement to inherited sin. On the basis of Jesus’ sacrifice, God could forgive the sins of those who show faith and who accept the ransom He provided.—Heb. 10:12-18. w19.12 10 ¶8; 11 ¶10-11

Memorial Bible reading: (Daytime events: Nisan 15) Matthew 27:62-66

^ (Luke 4:18) “Jehovah’s spirit is upon me, because he anointed me to declare good news to the poor. He sent me to proclaim liberty to the captives and a recovery of sight to the blind, to send the crushed ones away free,

^ (Matt. 5:31-37) “Moreover, it was said: ‘Whoever divorces his wife, let him give her a certificate of divorce.’ 32 However, I say to you that everyone divorcing his wife, except on account of sexual immorality, makes her a subject for adultery, and whoever marries a divorced woman commits adultery. 33 “Again you heard that it was said to those of ancient times: ‘You must not swear without performing, but you must pay your vows to Jehovah.’ 34 However, I say to you: Do not swear at all, neither by heaven, for it is God’s throne; 35 nor by earth, for it is the footstool of his feet; nor by Jerusalem, for it is the city of the great King. 36 Do not swear by your head, since you cannot turn one hair white or black. 37 Just let your word ‘Yes’ mean yes, your ‘No,’ no, for what goes beyond these is from the wicked one.*

Or possibly, “from what is wicked.”

^ (John 9:1) As he was passing along, he saw a man who had been blind from birth.

^ (John 9:14-16) Incidentally, the day that Jesus made the paste and opened his eyes was the Sabbath. 15 So this time the Pharisees also began asking the man how he gained sight. He said to them: “He put a paste on my eyes, and I washed, and I can see.” 16 Some of the Pharisees then began to say: “This is not a man from God, for he does not observe the Sabbath.” Others said: “How can a man who is a sinner perform signs of that sort?” So there was a division among them.

^ (John 9:35-41) Jesus heard that they had thrown him out, and on finding him, he said: “Are you putting faith in the Son of man?” 36 The man answered: “And who is he, sir, so that I may put faith in him?” 37 Jesus said to him: “You have seen him, and in fact, he is the one speaking with you.” 38 He said: “I do put faith in him, Lord.” And he did obeisance to him. 39 Jesus then said: “For this judgment I came into this world, that those not seeing might see and those seeing might become blind.” 40 Those of the Pharisees who were with him heard these things, and they said to him: “We are not blind also, are we?” 41 Jesus said to them: “If you were blind, you would have no sin. But now you say, ‘We see.’ Your sin remains.”

^ (Mark 1:22) And they were astounded at his way of teaching, for he was teaching them as one having authority, and not as the scribes.

^ (Heb. 10:12-18) But this man offered one sacrifice for sins for all time and sat down at the right hand of God, 13 from then on waiting until his enemies should be placed as a stool for his feet. 14 For it is by one sacrificial offering that he has made those who are being sanctified perfect for all time. 15 Moreover, the holy spirit also bears witness to us, for after it has said: 16 “‘This is the covenant that I will make with them after those days,’ says Jehovah.* ‘I will put my laws in their hearts, and in their minds I will write them.’” 17 Then it says: “And I will no longer call their sins and their lawless deeds to mind.” 18 Now where there is forgiveness of these, there is no longer an offering for sin.

See App. A5.

^ (Matt. 27:62-66) The next day, which was after the Preparation, the chief priests and the Pharisees gathered together before Pilate, 63 saying: “Sir, we recall what that impostor said while he was still alive, ‘After three days I am to be raised up.’ 64 Therefore, command that the grave be made secure until the third day, so that his disciples may not come and steal him and say to the people, ‘He was raised up from the dead!’ Then this last deception will be worse than the first.” 65 Pilate said to them: “You may have a guard. Go make it as secure as you know how.” 66 So they went and made the grave secure by sealing the stone and posting a guard.

Wednesday, March 31

Thoughtless speech is like the stabs of a sword, but the tongue of the wise is a healing.—[Prov. 12:18].

One reason why Job’s three false comforters lacked compassion for him is that they saw only the outward appearance of his situation. As a result, they jumped to wrong conclusions and judged Job harshly. How can we avoid making a similar mistake? Realize that only Jehovah knows all the facts about a person’s situation. Listen carefully to what the suffering person says. Do more than hear his words; try also to feel his pain. Only then will you be able to show genuine fellow feeling for your brother or sister. Compassion will hold us back from spreading harmful gossip about the problems others are facing. A gossiper does not build up the congregation; he tears it down. ([Prov. 20:19;][Rom. 14:19]) He can injure a person who is already suffering. (Eph. 4:31, 32) How much better it is when we look for a person’s good qualities and think about how we can help him or her deal with trials! w19.06 21-22 ¶8-9

^ (Prov. 12:18) Thoughtless speech is like the stabs of a sword, But the tongue of the wise is a healing.

^ (Prov. 20:19) A slanderer goes about revealing confidential talk; Do not associate with one who loves to gossip.*

Or “who entices with his lips.”

^ (Rom. 14:19) So, then, let us pursue the things making for peace and the things that build one another up.

^ (Eph. 4:31, 32) Put away from yourselves every kind of malicious bitterness, anger, wrath, screaming, and abusive speech, as well as everything injurious. 32 But become kind to one another, tenderly compassionate, freely forgiving one another just as God also by Christ freely forgave you.

April

Thursday, April 1

A true friend shows love at all times.—[Prov. 17:17].

Aristarchus, a Macedonian Christian from Thessalonica, proved to be a loyal friend to the apostle Paul. We first read about Aristarchus when Paul visited Ephesus on his third missionary tour. While accompanying Paul, Aristarchus was captured by a mob. ([Acts 19:29]) When he was finally set free, he did not seek his own safety but loyally stayed with Paul. Some months later, in Greece, Aristarchus was still at Paul’s side even though opposers continued to threaten Paul’s life. ([Acts 20:2-4]) In about 58 C.E. when Paul was sent to Rome as a prisoner, Aristarchus accompanied him on the long journey, and together they endured shipwreck along the way. (Acts 27:1, 2,[41]) Once in Rome, he apparently spent some time in prison with Paul. ([Col. 4:10]) Little wonder that Paul felt encouraged and comforted by such a loyal companion! Like Aristarchus, we can be a loyal friend by sticking to our brothers and sisters not only in good times but also during “times of distress.” w20.01 9 ¶4-5

^ (Prov. 17:17) A true friend shows love at all times And is a brother who is born for times of distress.

^ (Acts 19:29) So the city became filled with confusion, and all together they rushed into the theater, dragging along with them Gaʹius and Ar·is·tarʹchus, Mac·e·doʹni·ans, traveling companions of Paul.

^ (Acts 20:2-4) After going through those regions and giving many words of encouragement to the ones there, he arrived in Greece. 3 He spent three months there, but because a plot was hatched against him by the Jews when he was about to set sail for Syria, he made up his mind to return through Mac·e·doʹni·a. 4 He was accompanied by Sopʹa·ter the son of Pyrʹrhus of Be·roeʹa, Ar·is·tarʹchus and Se·cunʹdus of the Thes·sa·loʹni·ans, Gaʹius of Derʹbe, Timothy and, from the province of Asia, Tychʹi·cus and Trophʹi·mus.

^ (Acts 27:1, 2) Now as it was decided for us to sail away to Italy, they handed Paul and some other prisoners over to an army officer named Julius, of the unit of Au·gusʹtus. 2 Going aboard a ship from Ad·ra·mytʹti·um that was about to sail to ports along the coast of the province of Asia, we set sail; Ar·is·tarʹchus, a Mac·e·doʹni·an from Thes·sa·lo·niʹca, was with us.

^ (Acts 27:41) When they struck a shoal washed on each side by the sea, they ran the ship aground and the bow got stuck and stayed immovable, but the stern began to be violently broken to pieces by the waves.

^ (Col. 4:10) Ar·is·tarʹchus, my fellow captive, sends you his greetings, and so does Mark, the cousin of Barʹna·bas (concerning whom you received instructions to welcome him if he comes to you),

Friday, April 2

Happy and holy is anyone having part in the first resurrection.—[Rev. 20:6].

Someone who has been anointed may feel unworthy of this precious privilege. But he does not for one minute doubt that Jehovah has chosen him. His heart bursts with joy and appreciation when he thinks of his future prospects. (1 Pet. 1:3, 4) So does this mean that anointed ones want to die? The apostle Paul answers that question. He compared their human body to a tent and said: “In fact, we who are in this tent groan, being weighed down, because we do not want to put this one off, but we want to put the other on, so that what is mortal may be swallowed up by life.” ([2 Cor. 5:4]) These Christians have not lost interest in this life, wanting it to end quickly. On the contrary, they enjoy life and want to use each day to serve Jehovah with their family and friends. Yet, no matter what they are doing, they always remember the glorious hope that they have for the future.—1 Cor. 15:53;[2 Pet. 1:4;] 1 John 3:2, 3. w20.01 23 ¶12-13

^ (Rev. 20:6) Happy and holy is anyone having part in the first resurrection; over these the second death has no authority, but they will be priests of God and of the Christ, and they will rule as kings with him for the 1,000 years.

^ (1 Pet. 1:3, 4) Praised be the God and Father of our Lord Jesus Christ, for according to his great mercy he gave us a new birth to a living hope through the resurrection of Jesus Christ from the dead, 4 to an incorruptible and undefiled and unfading inheritance. It is reserved in the heavens for you,

^ (2 Cor. 5:4) In fact, we who are in this tent groan, being weighed down, because we do not want to put this one off, but we want to put the other on, so that what is mortal may be swallowed up by life.

^ (1 Cor. 15:53) For this which is corruptible must put on incorruption, and this which is mortal must put on immortality.

^ (2 Pet. 1:4) Through these things he has granted* us the precious and very grand promises, so that through these you may become sharers in divine nature, having escaped from the world’s corruption produced by wrong desire.*

Or “freely given.”

Or “by lust.”

^ (1 John 3:2, 3) Beloved ones, we are now children of God, but it has not yet been made manifest what we will be. We do know that when he is made manifest we will be like him, because we will see him just as he is. 3 And everyone who has this hope in him purifies himself, just as that one is pure.

Monday, April 5

I love Jehovah because he hears my voice, my pleas for help.—[Ps. 116:1].

One way to respond to Jehovah’s love is by talking to him in prayer. Your love for God will grow as you tell him about your concerns and thank him for all that he does for you. And the bond between you and Jehovah will be strengthened as you see how he answers your prayers. You will become convinced that he understands you. But to grow close to Jehovah, you need to understand his way of thinking. And you need to know what he wants from you. The only way you will gain that knowledge is by studying his Word, the Bible. So learn to appreciate it. Only the Bible contains the truth about Jehovah and his purpose for you. You show that you appreciate the Bible by reading it each day, by preparing for your personal Bible study session, and by applying what you learn. ([Ps. 119:97,][99;][John 17:17]) Do you have a personal Bible reading schedule? Do you follow that schedule, making sure that you read the Bible each day? w20.03 5 ¶8-9

^ (Ps. 116:1) I love Jehovah Because he hears* my voice, my pleas for help.

Or possibly, “I love because Jehovah hears.”

^ (Ps. 119:97) How I do love your law! I ponder over* it all day long.

Or “study.”

^ (Ps. 119:99) I have more insight than all my teachers, Because I ponder over* your reminders.

Or “study.”

^ (John 17:17) Sanctify them by means of the truth; your word is truth.

Tuesday, April 6

He began to reason . . . with those who happened to be on hand.—[Acts 17:17].

If you are unable to do much walking, you might be able to sit in a public area where you can preach to passersby. Or you might be able to witness informally, write letters, or do telephone witnessing. Many publishers with severe limitations experience much joy and satisfaction in these other avenues of the preaching work. Despite health limitations, you can accomplish your ministry fully. Paul said: “For all things I have the strength through the one who gives me power.” ([Phil. 4:13]) Paul needed that power when he got sick on one of his missionary trips. He explained to the Galatians: “It was because of a physical illness that I had my first opportunity to declare the good news to you.” ([Gal. 4:13]) Similarly, your health limitations may give you opportunities to declare the good news to others, such as to doctors, nurses, and health-care providers. Many of these people are at work when publishers may be calling at their homes. w19.04 4-5 ¶10-11

^ (Acts 17:17) So he began to reason in the synagogue with the Jews and the other people who worshipped God and every day in the marketplace with those who happened to be on hand.

^ (Phil. 4:13) For all things I have the strength through the one who gives me power.

^ (Gal. 4:13) But you know that it was because of a physical illness that I had my first opportunity to declare the good news to you.

Thursday, April 8

We have a struggle . . . against the wicked spirit forces in the heavenly places.—[Eph. 6:12].

One of the most heartwarming ways in which Jehovah shows his concern for us as his servants is by helping us to resist our enemies. Our main enemies are Satan and the demons. Jehovah warns us about these enemies, and he gives us what we need to resist them. ([Eph. 6:10-13]) When we accept Jehovah’s help and rely on him completely, we can succeed in opposing the Devil. We can have the same kind of confidence that the apostle Paul had. He wrote: “If God is for us, who will be against us?” ([Rom. 8:31]) As true Christians, we are not fascinated with Satan and the demons. We focus most of our attention on learning about Jehovah and serving him. ([Ps. 25:5]) However, we do need to know the basic ways that Satan operates. Why? So that we can avoid being outwitted by him.—[2 Cor. 2:11]; ftn. w19.04 20 ¶1-2

^ (Eph. 6:12) because we have a struggle,* not against blood and flesh, but against the governments, against the authorities, against the world rulers of this darkness, against the wicked spirit forces in the heavenly places.

Lit., “wrestling.”

^ (Eph. 6:10-13) Finally, go on acquiring power in the Lord and in the mightiness of his strength. 11 Put on the complete suit of armor from God so that you may be able to stand firm against the crafty acts* of the Devil; 12 because we have a struggle,* not against blood and flesh, but against the governments, against the authorities, against the world rulers of this darkness, against the wicked spirit forces in the heavenly places. 13 For this reason take up the complete suit of armor from God, so that you may be able to resist in the wicked day and, after you have accomplished everything, to stand firm.

Or “the schemes.”

Lit., “wrestling.”

^ (Rom. 8:31) What, then, are we to say about these things? If God is for us, who will be* against us?

Or “can be; is.”

^ (Ps. 25:5) Cause me to walk in your truth and teach me, For you are my God of salvation. In you I hope all day long.

^ (2 Cor. 2:11) so that we may not be overreached by Satan, for we are not ignorant of his designs.

Saturday, April 10

Husbands, continue loving your wives, just as the Christ also loved the congregation and gave himself up for it.—[Eph. 5:25].

In the family, a husband is to love his wife “as the Christ does the congregation.” (Eph. 5:28, 29) A husband must imitate the self-sacrificing love of Christ by putting his wife’s needs and interests ahead of his own. Some men may find it difficult to show such love, perhaps because they were not raised in an environment where treating others fairly and lovingly was valued. It may be difficult for them to unlearn bad habits, but they must make these changes in order to obey the law of the Christ. A husband who shows self-sacrificing love gains his wife’s respect. A father who truly loves his children would never abuse them by what he says or does. ([Eph. 4:31]) Instead, he expresses his love and approval in ways that make his children feel safe and secure. Such a father gains the love and trust of his children. w19.05 6 ¶21

^ (Eph. 5:25) Husbands, continue loving your wives, just as the Christ also loved the congregation and gave himself up for it,

^ (Eph. 5:28, 29) In the same way husbands should love their wives as their own bodies. A man who loves his wife loves himself, 29 for no man ever hated his own body,* but he feeds and cherishes it, just as the Christ does the congregation,

Lit., “flesh.”

^ (Eph. 4:31) Put away from yourselves every kind of malicious bitterness, anger, wrath, screaming, and abusive speech, as well as everything injurious.

Sunday, April 11

Jehovah God will give him the throne of David his father, and he will rule as King over the house of Jacob forever.—Luke 1:32, 33.

What did those words of Gabriel mean to Mary? Did she take Gabriel’s words to mean that Jesus would replace King Herod—or one of his successors as the ruler in Israel? If Jesus did become king, Mary would be the queen mother, and her family would live in the royal palace. Yet, never do we read that Mary asked for a position of favor in the Kingdom. Mary was an extremely humble woman! Let us remember that our ultimate goal in studying God’s Word and our Christian publications is to draw closer to Jehovah. We also want to see more clearly “what sort of person” we are and what changes we need to make in order to please God. (Jas. 1:22-25;[4:8]) At the beginning of each study period, then, we should ask Jehovah for his spirit. We should beg him to help us to benefit fully from the material and to see ourselves as he sees us. w19.05 31 ¶18-19

^ (Luke 1:32, 33) This one will be great and will be called Son of the Most High, and Jehovah God will give him the throne of David his father, 33 and he will rule as King over the house of Jacob forever, and there will be no end to his Kingdom.”

^ (Jas. 1:22-25) However, become doers of the word and not hearers only, deceiving yourselves with false reasoning. 23 For if anyone is a hearer of the word and not a doer, this one is like a man looking at his own face* in a mirror. 24 For he looks at himself, and he goes away and immediately forgets what sort of person he is. 25 But the one who peers into the perfect law that belongs to freedom and continues in it has become, not a forgetful hearer, but a doer of the work; and he will be happy in what he does.

Or “his natural face.”

^ (Jas. 4:8) Draw close to God, and he will draw close to you. Cleanse your hands, you sinners, and purify your hearts, you indecisive ones.

Tuesday, April 13

A true friend shows love at all times and is a brother who is born for times of distress.—[Prov. 17:17].

When we do small acts of kindness to those who no longer have a marriage mate, we reassure them of our love. More than ever, they need good friends. How can you prove that you are their friend? You could invite them over for a simple meal. And you might offer to spend some time with them in recreation or in the field ministry. Another option would be to ask them occasionally to join you for family worship. If you do, you will make Jehovah happy, for he is “close to the brokenhearted” and is “a protector of widows.” ([Ps. 34:18;][68:5]) Soon, when God’s Kingdom rules the earth, all “distresses will be forgotten.” How we look forward to the time when “the former things will not be called to mind, nor will they come up into the heart.” (Isa. 65:16, 17) Until that day, let us support one another and prove by both our speech and our actions that we love all in our spiritual family.—[1 Pet. 3:8]. w19.06 25 ¶18-19

^ (Prov. 17:17) A true friend shows love at all times And is a brother who is born for times of distress.

^ (Ps. 34:18) Jehovah is close to the brokenhearted; He saves those who are crushed in spirit.*

Or “are discouraged.”

^ (Ps. 68:5) A father of the fatherless and a protector* of widows Is God in his holy dwelling.

Lit., “judge.”

^ (Isa. 65:16, 17) So that anyone who seeks a blessing for himself in the earth Will be blessed by the God of truth,* And anyone who swears an oath in the earth Will swear by the God of truth.* For the former distresses* will be forgotten; They will be concealed from my eyes. 17 For look! I am creating new heavens and a new earth; And the former things will not be called to mind,* Nor will they come up into the heart.

Or “faithfulness.” Lit., “Amen.”

Or “faithfulness.” Lit., “Amen.”

Or “troubles.”

Or “be remembered.”

^ (1 Pet. 3:8) Finally, all of you have unity of mind,* fellow feeling, brotherly affection, tender compassion, and humility.

Or “think in agreement.”

Thursday, April 15

We are [not] the masters over your faith, but we are fellow workers for your joy, for it is by your faith that you are standing.—[2 Cor. 1:24].

Jehovah has not given us authority to make personal decisions for others. Someone who makes needless rules is not protecting his brother’s safety—he is trying to become the master of his brother’s faith. Satan the Devil will not stop trying to persecute Jehovah’s faithful servants. ([1 Pet. 5:8;][Rev. 2:10]) Satan and his agents will try to ban our worship of Jehovah. However, there is no reason for us to be paralyzed by fear! ([Deut. 7:21]) Jehovah is on our side, and he will continue to support us even if our work is banned. (2 Chron. 32:7, 8) May we have the same resolve as did our first-century brothers, who told the rulers of their day: “Whether it is right in the sight of God to listen to you rather than to God, judge for yourselves. But as for us, we cannot stop speaking about the things we have seen and heard.”—Acts 4:19, 20. w19.07 13 ¶18-20

^ (2 Cor. 1:24) Not that we are the masters over your faith, but we are fellow workers for your joy, for it is by your faith that you are standing.

^ (1 Pet. 5:8) Keep your senses, be watchful! Your adversary, the Devil, walks about like a roaring lion, seeking to devour someone.*

Or “looking for someone to devour.”

^ (Rev. 2:10) Do not be afraid of the things you are about to suffer. Look! The Devil will keep on throwing some of you into prison so that you may be fully put to the test, and you will have tribulation for ten days. Prove yourself faithful even to death, and I will give you the crown of life.

^ (Deut. 7:21) Do not be struck with terror because of them, for Jehovah your God is with you, a great and awe-inspiring God.

^ (2 Chron. 32:7, 8) “Be courageous and strong. Do not be afraid or be terrified because of the king of As·syrʹi·a and all the multitude with him, for there are more with us than there are with him. 8 With him is an arm of flesh,* but with us is Jehovah our God to help us and to fight our battles.” And the people were strengthened by the words of King Hez·e·kiʹah of Judah.

Or “is human strength.”

^ (Acts 4:19, 20) But in reply Peter and John said to them: “Whether it is right in the sight of God to listen to you rather than to God, judge for yourselves. 20 But as for us, we cannot stop speaking about the things we have seen and heard.”

Saturday, April 17

God recommends his own love to us in that, while we were yet sinners, Christ died for us.—[Rom. 5:8].

How much should we love God? Jesus told a Pharisee: “You must love Jehovah your God with your whole heart and with your whole soul and with your whole mind.” (Matt. 22:36, 37) We do not want our love for God to be half-hearted. Rather, we want our love for him to grow stronger each day. We need to know God in order to love him. The Bible says: “Whoever does not love has not come to know God, because God is love.” ([1 John 4:8]) The apostle Paul indicated that our love for God would grow stronger as we gain “accurate knowledge and full discernment” of Him. ([Phil. 1:9]) When we first studied the Bible, we developed love for God based on a limited knowledge of his wonderful qualities. Then the more we learned about Jehovah, the stronger our love for him became. No wonder we view regular Bible study and meditation on God’s Word as being among the most important things in our life!—[Phil. 2:16]. w19.08 9 ¶4-5

^ (Rom. 5:8) But God recommends his own love to us* in that, while we were yet sinners, Christ died for us.

Or “demonstrates (shows) his own love for us.”

^ (Matt. 22:36, 37) “Teacher, which is the greatest commandment in the Law?” 37 He said to him: “‘You must love Jehovah your God with your whole heart and with your whole soul and with your whole mind.’

^ (1 John 4:8) Whoever does not love has not come to know God, because God is love.

^ (Phil. 1:9) And this is what I continue praying, that your love may abound still more and more with accurate knowledge and full discernment;

^ (Phil. 2:16) keeping a tight grip on the word of life. Then I may have reason for rejoicing in Christ’s day, knowing that I did not run in vain or work hard in vain.

Sunday, April 18

Two are better than one.—[Eccl. 4:9].

If you are in a new assignment, you need to make new friends. Remember that to have a friend, you need to be a friend. Share the rich experiences Jehovah has given you, and let others sense your joy in Jehovah’s service. If you had to leave your assignment because of your mate’s health, do not blame him or her. On the other hand, if you yourself had health problems, do not feel guilty, thinking that you let your mate down. Remember, you are “one flesh,” and you promised before Jehovah to care for each other under all circumstances. (Matt. 19:5, 6) If you left an assignment because of an unplanned pregnancy, make sure your child knows that he is more important to you than your assignment was. Reassure your child that you view him as “a reward” from God. ([Ps. 127:3-5]) Also, tell him about the rewarding experiences you had in your assignment. Doing so can motivate your child to use his life in Jehovah’s joyful service just as you have done. w19.08 22 ¶10-11

^ (Eccl. 4:9) Two are better than one because they have a good reward* for their hard work.

Or “greater benefit.”

^ (Matt. 19:5, 6) and said: ‘For this reason a man will leave his father and his mother and will stick to his wife, and the two will be one flesh’? 6 So that they are no longer two, but one flesh. Therefore, what God has yoked together, let no man put apart.”

^ (Ps. 127:3-5) Look! Sons* are an inheritance from Jehovah; The fruit of the womb is a reward.  4 Like arrows in the hand of a mighty man, So are the sons of one’s youth.  5 Happy is the man who fills his quiver with them. They will not be put to shame, For they will speak with enemies in the city gate.

Or “Children.”

Monday, April 19

I will show you the judgment on the great prostitute.—[Rev. 17:1].

Babylon the Great, the world empire of false religion, has brought much reproach on God’s name. She has taught lies about God. She has prostituted herself spiritually by forming alliances with earth’s rulers. She has used her power and influence to exploit her flocks. And she has spilled much blood, including the blood of God’s servants. ([Rev. 18:24;][19:2]) Jehovah will destroy “the great prostitute” by means of “the ten horns” of “a scarlet-colored wild beast.” That figurative wild beast represents the United Nations. The ten horns represent the current political powers supporting that organization. At God’s appointed time, those political powers will turn on symbolic Babylon. They “will make her devastated and naked” by plundering her wealth and exposing her wickedness. ([Rev. 17:3,][16]) That swift destruction—as if in one day—will come as a shock to those who supported her, for she has long boasted: “I will never see mourning.”—[Rev. 18:7, 8]. w19.09 10 ¶10-11

^ (Rev. 17:1) One of the seven angels who had the seven bowls came and said to me: “Come, I will show you the judgment on the great prostitute who sits on many waters,

^ (Rev. 18:24) Yes, in her was found the blood of prophets and of holy ones and of all those who have been slaughtered on the earth.”

^ (Rev. 19:2) because his judgments are true and righteous. For he has executed judgment on the great prostitute who corrupted the earth with her sexual immorality,* and he has avenged the blood of his slaves that is on her hands.”*

Greek, por·neiʹa. See Glossary.

Lit., “from her hand.”

^ (Rev. 17:3) And he carried me away in the power of the spirit into a wilderness. And I saw a woman sitting on a scarlet-colored wild beast that was full of blasphemous names and that had seven heads and ten horns.

^ (Rev. 17:16) And the ten horns that you saw and the wild beast, these will hate the prostitute and will make her devastated and naked, and they will eat up her flesh and completely burn her with fire.

^ (Rev. 18:7, 8) To the extent that she glorified herself and lived in shameless luxury, to that extent give her torment and mourning. For she keeps saying in her heart: ‘I sit as queen, and I am not a widow, and I will never see mourning.’ 8 That is why in one day her plagues will come, death and mourning and famine, and she will be completely burned with fire, because Jehovah* God, who judged her, is strong.

See App. A5.

Tuesday, April 20

Take my yoke upon you and learn from me.—[Matt. 11:29].

That invitation is open to all—Jesus will never reject anyone who sincerely wants to serve God. (John 6:37, 38) All of Christ’s followers have been given the privilege of sharing in the work that Jehovah has asked Jesus to do. We can be certain that Jesus will always be there to help us do that work. (Matt. 28:18-20) Humble people were drawn to Jesus. (Matt. 19:13, 14; Luke 7:37, 38) Why? Consider the contrast between Jesus and the Pharisees. Those religious leaders were cold and arrogant. (Matt. 12:9-14) Jesus was warm and humble. The Pharisees were ambitious and proud of their high position in society. Jesus discouraged undue ambition, and he taught his disciples to view themselves as lowly servants. ([Matt. 23:2,][6-11]) The Pharisees dominated others through fear and intimidation. ([John 9:13,][22]) Jesus refreshed others by loving acts and kind words. Have you learned these lessons from Jesus? w19.09 20 ¶1; 21 ¶7-8; 23 ¶9

^ (Matt. 11:29) Take my yoke upon you and learn from me,* for I am mild-tempered and lowly in heart, and you will find refreshment for yourselves.

Or “become my disciples (learners).”

^ (John 6:37, 38) All those whom the Father gives me will come to me, and I will never drive away the one who comes to me; 38 for I have come down from heaven to do, not my own will, but the will of him who sent me.

^ (Matt. 28:18-20) Jesus approached and spoke to them, saying: “All authority has been given me in heaven and on the earth. 19 Go, therefore, and make disciples of people of all the nations, baptizing them in the name of the Father and of the Son and of the holy spirit, 20 teaching them to observe all the things I have commanded you. And look! I am with you all the days until the conclusion of the system of things.”

^ (Matt. 19:13, 14) Then young children were brought to him for him to place his hands on them and offer prayer, but the disciples reprimanded them. 14 Jesus, however, said: “Let the young children alone, and do not try to stop them from coming to me, for the Kingdom of the heavens belongs to such ones.”

^ (Luke 7:37, 38) And look! a woman who was known in the city to be a sinner learned that he was dining* in the house of the Pharisee, and she brought an alabaster jar of perfumed oil. 38 Taking a position behind him at his feet, she wept and began to wet his feet with her tears, and she wiped them off with the hair of her head. Also, she tenderly kissed his feet and poured the perfumed oil on them.

Or “reclining at the table.”

^ (Matt. 12:9-14) After departing from that place, he went into their synagogue, 10 and look! there was a man with a withered* hand! So they asked him, “Is it lawful to cure on the Sabbath?” so that they might accuse him. 11 He said to them: “If you have one sheep and that sheep falls into a pit on the Sabbath, is there a man among you who will not grab hold of it and lift it out? 12 How much more valuable is a man than a sheep! So it is lawful to do a fine thing on the Sabbath.” 13 Then he said to the man: “Stretch out your hand.” And he stretched it out, and it was restored sound like the other hand. 14 But the Pharisees went out and conspired against him to kill him.

Or “paralyzed.”

^ (Matt. 23:2) “The scribes and the Pharisees have seated themselves in the seat of Moses.

^ (Matt. 23:6-11) They like the most prominent place at evening meals and the front seats in the synagogues 7 and the greetings in the marketplaces and to be called Rabbi by men. 8 But you, do not you be called Rabbi, for one is your Teacher, and all of you are brothers. 9 Moreover, do not call anyone your father on earth, for one is your Father, the heavenly One. 10 Neither be called leaders, for your Leader is one, the Christ. 11 But the greatest one among you must be your minister.

^ (John 9:13) They led the formerly blind man to the Pharisees.

^ (John 9:22) His parents said these things because they were in fear of the Jews, for the Jews had already come to an agreement that if anyone acknowledged him as Christ, that person should be expelled from the synagogue.

Thursday, April 22

Know this, that in the last days critical times hard to deal with will be here.—[2 Tim. 3:1].

Were you born after the year 1914? If so, you have lived your entire life during “the last days” of the present system of things. All of us have heard about the events that Jesus foretold for this time. These include wars, food shortages, earthquakes, pestilences, an increasing of lawlessness, and the persecution of Jehovah’s people. ([Matt. 24:3,][7-9,][12;] Luke 21:10-12) We have also seen people behave in the way foretold by the apostle Paul. As worshippers of Jehovah, we are convinced that we are living during “the final part of the days.” ([Mic. 4:1]) Because so much time has passed since 1914, we must now be living in the last of “the last days.” Since the end is so near, we need to know the answers to some important questions: What events will occur at the end of “the last days”? And what does Jehovah expect us to do while we wait for those events? w19.10 8 ¶1-2

^ (2 Tim. 3:1) But know this, that in the last days critical times hard to deal with will be here.

^ (Matt. 24:3) While he was sitting on the Mount of Olives, the disciples approached him privately, saying: “Tell us, when will these things be, and what will be the sign of your presence and of the conclusion of the system of things?”

^ (Matt. 24:7-9) “For nation will rise against nation and kingdom against kingdom, and there will be food shortages and earthquakes in one place after another. 8 All these things are a beginning of pangs of distress. 9 “Then people will hand you over to tribulation and will kill you, and you will be hated by all the nations on account of my name.

^ (Matt. 24:12) and because of the increasing of lawlessness, the love of the greater number will grow cold.

^ (Luke 21:10-12) Then he said to them: “Nation will rise against nation, and kingdom against kingdom. 11 There will be great earthquakes, and in one place after another food shortages and pestilences; and there will be fearful sights and from heaven great signs. 12 “But before all these things happen, people will lay their hands on you and persecute you, handing you over to the synagogues and prisons. You will be brought before kings and governors for the sake of my name.

^ (Mic. 4:1) In the final part of the days,* The mountain of the house of Jehovah Will become firmly established above the top of the mountains, And it will be raised up above the hills, And to it peoples will stream.

Or “In the last days.”

Monday, April 26

If any one of you is lacking in wisdom, let him keep asking God, for he gives generously to all.—[Jas. 1:5].

Some important decisions we would never change. For example, we stick to our decision to serve Jehovah, and we are determined to be faithful to our marriage mate. ([Matt. 16:24;][19:6]) Other decisions, though, may need to be adjusted. Why? Because circumstances change. What steps can help us to make the best decisions possible? Pray for wisdom. In some respects, we are all “lacking in wisdom.” So rely on Jehovah both when making a decision and when reviewing that decision. Jehovah will then help you to make wise choices. Do thorough research. Consult God’s Word, read the publications of Jehovah’s organization, and talk to people whom you can trust. ([Prov. 20:18]) Such research is vital before making a decision to change jobs, to move, or to choose appropriate education to help you support your ministry. w19.11 27 ¶6-8

^ (Jas. 1:5) So if any one of you is lacking in wisdom, let him keep asking God, for he gives generously to all and without reproaching,* and it will be given him.

Or “finding fault.”

^ (Matt. 16:24) Then Jesus said to his disciples: “If anyone wants to come after me, let him disown himself and pick up his torture stake and keep following me.

^ (Matt. 19:6) So that they are no longer two, but one flesh. Therefore, what God has yoked together, let no man put apart.”

^ (Prov. 20:18) By consultation,* plans will succeed,* And by skillful direction* wage your war.

Or “counsel.”

Or “be made firm.”

Or “wise guidance.”

Tuesday, April 27

Miserable man that I am! Who will rescue me from the body undergoing this death?—[Rom. 7:24].

Happily, God arranged a way for us to be rescued, or freed from sin. Jesus is the key to that liberation. In the eighth century before our Common Era, the prophet Isaiah foretold a future grand liberation. That grand liberation would accomplish far more than did the liberation during Israel’s Jubilee year. He wrote: “The spirit of the Sovereign Lord Jehovah is upon me, because Jehovah anointed me to declare good news to the meek. He sent me to bind up the brokenhearted, to proclaim liberty to the captives.” ([Isa. 61:1]) To whom does that prophecy apply? That important prophecy about liberation began to be fulfilled after Jesus started his ministry. When he went to the synagogue in his hometown of Nazareth, Jesus read those very words of Isaiah to the Jews assembled there and applied them to himself.—[Luke 4:16-19]. w19.12 9-10 ¶6-8

^ (Rom. 7:24) Miserable man that I am! Who will rescue me from the body undergoing this death?

^ (Isa. 61:1) The spirit of the Sovereign Lord Jehovah is upon me, Because Jehovah anointed me to declare good news to the meek. He sent me to bind up the brokenhearted, To proclaim liberty to the captives And the wide opening of the eyes to the prisoners,

^ (Luke 4:16-19) He then went to Nazʹa·reth, where he had been brought up, and according to his custom on the Sabbath day, he entered the synagogue and stood up to read. 17 So the scroll of the prophet Isaiah was handed to him, and he opened the scroll and found the place where it was written: 18 “Jehovah’s spirit is upon me, because he anointed me to declare good news to the poor. He sent me to proclaim liberty to the captives and a recovery of sight to the blind, to send the crushed ones away free, 19 to preach Jehovah’s acceptable year.”

Thursday, April 29

My fellow workers . . . have become a source of great comfort to me.—[Col. 4:11].

Tychicus stands out as a loyal Christian companion to the apostle Paul. ([Acts 20:4]) About 55 C.E., Paul organized the collection of relief funds for Judean Christians, and he may have let Tychicus help with this important assignment. (2 Cor. 8:18-20) Later when Paul was imprisoned in Rome for the first time, Tychicus served as his personal messenger. He delivered Paul’s letters and messages of encouragement to the congregations in Asia. ([Col. 4:7-9]) Tychicus remained Paul’s trustworthy friend. ([Titus 3:12]) Not all Christians back then were as dependable as Tychicus. About 65 C.E., during his second imprisonment, Paul wrote that many Christian men in the province of Asia avoided associating with him, possibly because they were afraid of opposers. ([2 Tim. 1:15]) In contrast, Paul could rely on Tychicus and gave him yet another assignment. ([2 Tim. 4:12]) Paul surely appreciated having a good friend like Tychicus. w20.01 10 ¶7-8

^ (Col. 4:11) and Jesus who is called Justus, who are of those circumcised. Only these are my fellow workers for the Kingdom of God, and they have become a source of great comfort* to me.

Or “a strengthening aid.”

^ (Acts 20:4) He was accompanied by Sopʹa·ter the son of Pyrʹrhus of Be·roeʹa, Ar·is·tarʹchus and Se·cunʹdus of the Thes·sa·loʹni·ans, Gaʹius of Derʹbe, Timothy and, from the province of Asia, Tychʹi·cus and Trophʹi·mus.

^ (2 Cor. 8:18-20) But we are sending along with him the brother whose praise in connection with the good news has spread through all the congregations. 19 Not only that, but he was also appointed by the congregations to be our traveling companion as we administer this kind gift for the glory of the Lord and in proof of our readiness to assist. 20 Thus we are avoiding having any man find fault with us in connection with this liberal contribution that we are administering.

^ (Col. 4:7-9) Tychʹi·cus, my beloved brother and faithful minister and fellow slave in the Lord, will tell you all the news about me. 8 I am sending him to you so that you will know how we are and that he may comfort your hearts. 9 He is coming along with O·nesʹi·mus, my faithful and beloved brother, who is from among you; they will tell you all the things happening here.

^ (Titus 3:12) When I send Arʹte·mas or Tychʹi·cus to you, do your utmost to come to me at Ni·copʹo·lis, for that is where I have decided to spend the winter.

^ (2 Tim. 1:15) You know this, that all the men in the province of Asia have turned away from me, including Phy·gelʹus and Her·mogʹe·nes.

^ (2 Tim. 4:12) But I have sent Tychʹi·cus off to Ephʹe·sus.

May

Saturday, May 1

Instruct us about what we should do with the child.—[Judg. 13:8].

What can parents do to help their children learn to love Jehovah? Pray for Jehovah’s help, as Manoah did. Also, teach by example. What you say is important; however, what you do will likely have a bigger impact on your child. We can be sure that Joseph and Mary set an excellent example for their children, including Jesus. Joseph worked hard to support his family. In addition, Joseph encouraged his household to appreciate spiritual things. (Deut. 4:9, 10) He took his family with him to Jerusalem “from year to year” to celebrate the Passover. (Luke 2:41, 42) Some fathers in his day may have viewed such a family trip as inconvenient, time-consuming, and expensive. Yet, Joseph obviously appreciated spiritual things and taught his children to do the same. Also, Mary knew the Scriptures well. By her words and actions, she no doubt taught her children to love God’s Word. w19.12 24-25 ¶9-12

^ (Judg. 13:8) Ma·noʹah pleaded with Jehovah and said: “Pardon me, Jehovah. Please let the man of the true God whom you just sent come again to instruct us about what we should do with the child who will be born.”

^ (Deut. 4:9, 10) “Just be careful and watch yourself closely,* so that you may not forget the things that your eyes have seen and so that they may not depart from your heart all the days of your life. You must also make them known to your sons and to your grandsons. 10 On the day that you stood before Jehovah your God in Horʹeb, Jehovah said to me, ‘Congregate the people together to me so that I may let them hear my words, in order that they may learn to fear me all the days that they are alive on the ground and that they may teach their sons.’

Or “and pay close attention to your soul.”

^ (Luke 2:41, 42) Now his parents were accustomed to go from year to year to Jerusalem for the festival of the Passover. 42 And when he was 12 years old, they went up according to the custom of the festival.

Sunday, May 2

I am fleshly, sold under sin.—[Rom. 7:14].

We see proof of Jehovah’s love for us in the way he responded to the problems that first arose within his earthly family. When Adam disobeyed his heavenly Father, he lost his place in Jehovah’s happy family, both for himself and for his descendants. ([Rom. 5:12]) Jehovah, however, stepped in to help. Jehovah punished Adam, but he did not leave Adam’s unborn offspring without hope. He immediately promised that obedient humans would be brought back into his family. ([Gen. 3:15;] Rom. 8:20, 21) Jehovah arranged for this on the basis of the ransom sacrifice of his beloved Son, Jesus. By giving his Son in our behalf, Jehovah proved how dearly he loves us. ([John 3:16]) He is the ideal Father. He hears our prayers and provides what we need, both materially and spiritually. He trains and supports us. He also has wonderful blessings in store for us. It warms our heart to know that our Father loves and cares for us! w20.02 6 ¶16-17; 7 ¶20

^ (Rom. 7:14) For we know that the Law is spiritual, but I am fleshly, sold under sin.

^ (Rom. 5:12) That is why, just as through one man sin entered into the world and death through sin, and so death spread to all men because they had all sinned—.

^ (Gen. 3:15) And I will put enmity* between you and the woman and between your offspring* and her offspring.* He will crush* your head, and you will strike* him in the heel.”

Or “hostility.”

Lit., “seed.”

Lit., “seed.”

Or “bruise; strike.”

Or “bruise; crush.”

^ (Rom. 8:20, 21) For the creation was subjected to futility, not by its own will, but through the one who subjected it, on the basis of hope 21 that* the creation itself will also be set free from enslavement to corruption and have the glorious freedom of the children of God.

Or “because.”

^ (John 3:16) “For God loved the world so much that he gave his only-begotten Son, so that everyone exercising faith in him might not be destroyed but have everlasting life.

Tuesday, May 4

If anyone wants to come after me, let him disown himself.—[Matt. 16:24].

When you make a dedication, you approach Jehovah in earnest prayer and tell him that you will use your life to serve him forever. When you dedicate yourself to God, you “disown” yourself. You now belong to Jehovah, which is a great privilege. ([Rom. 14:8]) You are telling him that from now on, you will be focused on serving him and not on pleasing yourself. Your dedication is a vow—a solemn promise made to God. Jehovah does not force us to make such a vow. But when we do, he expects us to fulfill it. ([Ps. 116:12,][14]) Your dedication is personal and private; it is between you and Jehovah. Baptism is public; it takes place in front of others, usually at an assembly or a convention. When you get baptized, you show others that you have already dedicated yourself to Jehovah. So your baptism lets others know that you love Jehovah your God with your whole heart, soul, mind, and strength and that you are determined to serve him forever.—[Mark 12:30]. w20.03 9 ¶4-5

^ (Matt. 16:24) Then Jesus said to his disciples: “If anyone wants to come after me, let him disown himself and pick up his torture stake and keep following me.

^ (Rom. 14:8) For if we live, we live to Jehovah, and if we die, we die to Jehovah. So both if we live and if we die, we belong to Jehovah.

^ (Ps. 116:12) With what will I repay Jehovah For all the good he has done for me?

^ (Ps. 116:14) I will pay my vows to Jehovah In the presence of all his people.

^ (Mark 12:30) and you must love Jehovah your God with your whole heart and with your whole soul and with your whole mind and with your whole strength.’

Wednesday, May 5

Let no one lead you astray.—[2 Thess. 2:3].

Satan blurs people’s view of Jehovah. After the death of Jesus’ apostles, some who claimed to be Christians began to spread false teachings. (Acts 20:29, 30) These apostates started to blur the identity of the only true God. For example, they stopped using the divine name in their copies of the Bible and preferred such expressions as “Lord.” By removing God’s personal name and replacing it with “Lord,” they made it difficult for a Bible reader to see how Jehovah is different from the other “lords” mentioned in the Scriptures. ([1 Cor. 8:5]) They used the same term, “Lord,” for Jehovah and for Jesus, making it difficult to understand that Jehovah and his Son are different individuals with distinct positions. ([John 17:3]) This confusion contributed to the development of the doctrine of the Trinity—a doctrine not taught in God’s Word. As a result, many see God as mysterious and believe that we cannot know him. What a lie!—[Acts 17:27]. w19.06 5 ¶11

^ (2 Thess. 2:3) Let no one lead you astray* in any way, because it will not come unless the apostasy comes first and the man of lawlessness gets revealed, the son of destruction.

Or “seduce you.”

^ (Acts 20:29, 30) I know that after my going away oppressive wolves will enter in among you and will not treat the flock with tenderness, 30 and from among you yourselves men will rise and speak twisted things to draw away the disciples after themselves.

^ (1 Cor. 8:5) For even though there are so-called gods, whether in heaven or on earth, just as there are many “gods” and many “lords,”

^ (John 17:3) This means everlasting life, their coming to know you, the only true God, and the one whom you sent, Jesus Christ.

^ (Acts 17:27) so that they would seek God, if they might grope for him and really find him, although, in fact, he is not far off from each one of us.

Friday, May 7

Satan . . . is misleading the entire inhabited earth.—[Rev. 12:9].

A major way in which Satan and the demons try to mislead people is through spiritism. Those who practice spiritism claim to know or control things that humans cannot normally know or control. For example, some claim to be able to know the future by using divination or astrology. Others may act as though they were speaking to those who have died. Some practice witchcraft or magic, and they may try to cast a spell on another person. A survey conducted in 18 countries in Latin America and the Caribbean found that about a third of the people surveyed believe in magic, witchcraft, or sorcery, and nearly as many believe that it is possible to communicate with spirits. Another survey was conducted in 18 countries in Africa. There, on average, more than half of the people surveyed say that they believe in witchcraft. Of course, wherever we live, we must be on guard against spiritism. w19.04 20-21 ¶3-4

^ (Rev. 12:9) So down the great dragon was hurled, the original serpent, the one called Devil and Satan, who is misleading the entire inhabited earth; he was hurled down to the earth, and his angels were hurled down with him.

Sunday, May 9

A righteous man’s supplication has a powerful effect.—[Jas. 5:16].

A person who is very low in spirit may feel unworthy to approach Jehovah in prayer. If we want to comfort such a person, we may offer a prayer with that one, using his or her name. We may express to Jehovah how dear the downhearted one is to us and to the congregation. We may ask Jehovah to soothe and comfort that precious sheep of his. Prayers of that kind can be profoundly comforting. Think before you speak. Thoughtless words can hurt. Kind words can heal. ([Prov. 12:18]) So pray to Jehovah for help to find kind, comforting, soothing words. Keep in mind that no words are more powerful than Jehovah’s own expressions contained in the Bible. ([Heb. 4:12]) When we comfort others, we remind them of Jehovah’s love. And we must never forget that Jehovah is also a God of justice. No wicked act of abuse is really hidden. Jehovah sees all, and he will not let unrepentant wrongdoers go unpunished.—[Num. 14:18]. w19.05 18 ¶18; 19 ¶19, 21

^ (Jas. 5:16) Therefore, openly confess your sins to one another and pray for one another, so that you may be healed. A righteous man’s supplication has a powerful effect.*

Lit., “has much force when it is at work.”

^ (Prov. 12:18) Thoughtless speech is like the stabs of a sword, But the tongue of the wise is a healing.

^ (Heb. 4:12) For the word of God is alive and exerts power and is sharper than any two-edged sword and pierces even to the dividing of soul* and spirit,* and of joints from the marrow, and is able to discern thoughts and intentions of the heart.

See Glossary.

See Glossary.

^ (Num. 14:18) ‘Jehovah, slow to anger and abundant in loyal love,* pardoning error and transgression, but he will by no means leave the guilty unpunished, bringing punishment for the error of fathers upon sons, upon the third generation and upon the fourth generation.’

Or “loving-kindness.”

Monday, May 10

Look out that no one takes you captive by means of the philosophy and empty deception according to human tradition.—[Col. 2:8].

Satan wants to turn us against Jehovah. To achieve his goal, he tries to influence our thinking, in effect, to bring our mind into captivity and make it obedient to him. He tries to persuade or to deceive us into following him by appealing to our desires. ([Col. 2:4]) Are we really in serious danger of being misled by Satan? Yes, we are! Remember, Paul did not write the warning recorded at Colossians 2:8 to unbelievers. He wrote it to Christians who had been anointed with holy spirit. ([Col. 1:2,][5]) Those Christians were in danger back then, and we are in even greater danger today. ([1 Cor. 10:12]) Why? Satan has been confined to the vicinity of the earth, and he is focused on misleading God’s loyal servants. ([Rev. 12:9,][12,][17]) In addition, we are living during a time when wicked men and impostors are advancing “from bad to worse.”—[2 Tim. 3:1,][13]. w19.06 2 ¶1-2

^ (Col. 2:8) Look out that no one takes you captive* by means of the philosophy and empty deception according to human tradition, according to the elementary things of the world and not according to Christ;

Or “carries you off as his prey.”

^ (Col. 2:4) I am saying this so that no one may delude you with persuasive arguments.

^ (Col. 2:8) Look out that no one takes you captive* by means of the philosophy and empty deception according to human tradition, according to the elementary things of the world and not according to Christ;

Or “carries you off as his prey.”

^ (Col. 1:2) to the holy ones and faithful brothers in union with Christ at Co·losʹsae: May you have undeserved kindness and peace from God our Father.

^ (Col. 1:5) because of the hope that is being reserved for you in the heavens. You previously heard about this hope through the message of truth of the good news

^ (1 Cor. 10:12) So let the one who thinks he is standing beware that he does not fall.

^ (Rev. 12:9) So down the great dragon was hurled, the original serpent, the one called Devil and Satan, who is misleading the entire inhabited earth; he was hurled down to the earth, and his angels were hurled down with him.

^ (Rev. 12:12) On this account be glad, you heavens and you who reside in them! Woe for the earth and for the sea, because the Devil has come down to you, having great anger, knowing that he has a short period of time.”

^ (Rev. 12:17) So the dragon became enraged at the woman and went off to wage war with the remaining ones of her offspring,* who observe the commandments of God and have the work of bearing witness concerning Jesus.

Lit., “seed.”

^ (2 Tim. 3:1) But know this, that in the last days critical times hard to deal with will be here.

^ (2 Tim. 3:13) But wicked men and impostors will advance from bad to worse, misleading and being misled.

Wednesday, May 12

Be in subjection to the older men. . . . Clothe yourselves with humility toward one another, because God opposes the haughty ones.—[1 Pet. 5:5].

Avoid being presumptuous. If we heed the direction we receive from trusted, responsible brothers, we will avoid problems. For example, in a land where the work is under ban, the responsible brothers had directed that the publishers not leave printed literature in the ministry. Yet, a pioneer brother in that location felt that he knew better and distributed literature. What was the result? Shortly after he and some others finished a period of informal witnessing, they were questioned by the police. Apparently, officials had followed them and were able to retrieve the literature they had distributed. What do we learn from this experience? We need to follow direction even if we feel that we know better. Jehovah always blesses us when we cooperate with the brothers whom he has appointed to take the lead among us.—[Heb. 13:7,][17]. w19.07 12 ¶17

^ (1 Pet. 5:5) In the same way, you younger men, be in subjection to the older men.* But all of you clothe* yourselves with humility* toward one another, because God opposes the haughty ones, but he gives undeserved kindness to the humble ones.

Or “the elders.”

Or “gird.”

Or “lowliness of mind.”

^ (Heb. 13:7) Remember those who are taking the lead among you, who have spoken the word of God to you, and as you contemplate how their conduct turns out, imitate their faith.

^ (Heb. 13:17) Be obedient to those who are taking the lead among you and be submissive, for they are keeping watch over you* as those who will render an account, so that they may do this with joy and not with sighing, for this would be damaging to you.

Or “your souls.”

Sunday, May 16

If this is how God loved us, then we are also under obligation to love one another.—[1 John 4:11].

God’s great love for us will move us to love our brothers. (1 John 4:20, 21) We might think that love for our brothers and sisters will come naturally. After all, we worship Jehovah and strive to imitate his fine qualities. We follow the example of Jesus, whose love was so great that he gave his life in our behalf. Yet, we may at times find it difficult to obey the commandment to love one another. Euodia and Syntyche were zealous sisters who had served “side by side” with the apostle Paul. Yet, they had perhaps allowed personal differences to cause a rift between them. In his letter to the congregation where those sisters served, Paul specifically named Euodia and Syntyche and gave them pointed admonition “to be of the same mind.” ([Phil. 4:2, 3]) Paul felt compelled to instruct the entire congregation: “Keep doing all things free from murmuring and arguments.”—[Phil. 2:14]. w19.08 9 ¶6-7

^ (1 John 4:11) Beloved ones, if this is how God loved us, then we are also under obligation to love one another.

^ (1 John 4:20, 21) If anyone says, “I love God,” and yet is hating his brother, he is a liar. For the one who does not love his brother, whom he has seen, cannot love God, whom he has not seen. 21 And we have this commandment from him, that whoever loves God must also love his brother.

^ (Phil. 4:2, 3) I urge Eu·oʹdi·a and I urge Synʹty·che to be of the same mind in the Lord. 3 Yes, I request you also, as a true fellow worker,* to keep assisting these women who have striven* side by side with me for the good news, along with Clement as well as the rest of my fellow workers, whose names are in the book of life.

Lit., “genuine yokefellow.”

Or “who have struggled hard.”

^ (Phil. 2:14) Keep doing all things free from murmuring and arguments,

Tuesday, May 18

I [will] sanctify myself through you before their eyes, O Gog.—[Ezek. 38:16].

Gog will trust in his “arm of flesh”—his military might. (2 Chron. 32:8) We will trust in Jehovah our God—a stand that will seem foolish to the nations. After all, the gods of the once powerful Babylon the Great did not save her from “the wild beast” and its “ten horns”! ([Rev. 17:16]) So Gog will expect an easy victory. “Like clouds covering the land,” he will attack Jehovah’s people. But Gog will soon see that he has marched into a trap. Like Pharaoh at the Red Sea, Gog will learn that he is fighting against Jehovah. ([Ex. 14:1-4;] Ezek. 38:3, 4,[18,][21-23]) Christ and his heavenly armies will defend God’s people and crush Gog’s hordes. ([Rev. 19:11,][14, 15]) But what about Jehovah’s chief enemy, Satan, whose lying propaganda led the nations to Armageddon? Jesus will hurl him and his demons into an abyss, where they will be locked away for a thousand years.—[Rev. 20:1-3]. w19.09 11-12 ¶14-15

^ (Ezek. 38:16) Like clouds covering the land, you will come against my people Israel. In the final part of the days I will bring you against my land so that the nations may know me when I sanctify myself through you before their eyes, O Gog.”’

^ (2 Chron. 32:8) With him is an arm of flesh,* but with us is Jehovah our God to help us and to fight our battles.” And the people were strengthened by the words of King Hez·e·kiʹah of Judah.

Or “is human strength.”

^ (Rev. 17:16) And the ten horns that you saw and the wild beast, these will hate the prostitute and will make her devastated and naked, and they will eat up her flesh and completely burn her with fire.

^ (Ex. 14:1-4) Jehovah now said to Moses: 2 “Tell the Israelites that they should turn back and encamp before Pi·ha·hiʹroth, between Migʹdol and the sea, within view of Baʹal-zeʹphon. You are to encamp facing it by the sea. 3 Then Pharʹaoh will say about the Israelites, ‘They are wandering in confusion in the land. The wilderness has closed in on them.’ 4 I will allow Pharʹaoh’s heart to become obstinate, and he will chase after them, and I will glorify myself by means of Pharʹaoh and all his army; and the Egyptians will certainly know that I am Jehovah.” So that is what they did.

^ (Ezek. 38:3, 4) Say, ‘This is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah says: “Here I am against you, O Gog, head chieftain* of Meʹshech and Tuʹbal. 4 I will turn you around and put hooks in your jaws and bring you out with all your army, horses and horsemen, all of them clothed in splendor, a vast assembly with large shields and bucklers,* all of them wielding swords;

Or “chief prince.”

A small shield, often carried by archers.

^ (Ezek. 38:18) “‘On that day, the day when Gog invades the land of Israel,’ declares the Sovereign Lord Jehovah, ‘my great rage will flare up.

^ (Ezek. 38:21-23) “‘I will call for a sword against him on all my mountains,’ declares the Sovereign Lord Jehovah. ‘Every man’s sword will be against his own brother. 22 I will bring my judgment against him* with pestilence and bloodshed; and I will rain down a torrential downpour and hailstones and fire and sulfur on him and on his troops and on the many peoples with him. 23 And I will certainly magnify myself and sanctify myself and make myself known before the eyes of many nations; and they will have to know that I am Jehovah.’

Or “I will bring myself into judgment with him.”

^ (Rev. 19:11) I saw heaven opened, and look! a white horse. And the one seated on it is called Faithful and True, and he judges and carries on war in righteousness.

^ (Rev. 19:14, 15) Also, the armies in heaven were following him on white horses, and they were clothed in white, clean, fine linen. 15 And out of his mouth protrudes a sharp, long sword with which to strike the nations, and he will shepherd them with a rod of iron. Moreover, he treads the winepress of the fury of the wrath of God the Almighty.

^ (Rev. 20:1-3) And I saw an angel coming down out of heaven with the key of the abyss and a great chain in his hand. 2 He seized the dragon, the original serpent, who is the Devil and Satan, and bound him for 1,000 years. 3 And he hurled him into the abyss and shut it and sealed it over him, so that he would not mislead the nations anymore until the 1,000 years were ended. After this he must be released for a little while.

Tuesday, May 25

Jehovah examines the motives.—[Prov. 16:2].

When making decisions, analyze your motives. Jehovah wants us to be honest in all things. So when we make decisions, we too want to be honest with ourselves and with others about our motives. If we were not completely honest, we would likely have difficulty sticking to the decision. For example, a young brother may decide to become a regular pioneer. After some time, however, he struggles to fulfill the hour requirement and he finds little joy in his ministry. He may have thought that his main motive for pioneering was his desire to please Jehovah. Could it be, though, that he was primarily motivated by a desire to please his parents or some person he admired? Consider the situation of a Bible student who decides to give up smoking. At first, he struggles, doing well for a week or two, but then he gives in to the urge to smoke. Finally, though, he is successful! His love for Jehovah and his desire to please Him have helped him to conquer the habit.—[Col. 1:10;][3:23]. w19.11 27 ¶9; 29 ¶10

^ (Prov. 16:2) All of a man’s ways seem right* to him, But Jehovah examines the motives.*

Lit., “pure.”

Lit., “spirits.”

^ (Col. 1:10) so as to walk worthily of Jehovah* in order to please him fully as you go on bearing fruit in every good work and increasing in the accurate knowledge of God;

See App. A5.

^ (Col. 3:23) Whatever you are doing, work at it whole-souled* as for Jehovah,* and not for men,

See Glossary, “Soul.”

See App. A5.

Thursday, May 27

If the Son sets you free, you will be truly free.—[John 8:36].

That freedom was certainly greater than what could be gained during Israel’s Jubilee year! ([Lev. 25:8-12]) For instance, a man set free during the Jubilee might again become a slave, and in any case, he would eventually die. On the day of Pentecost 33 C.E., Jehovah anointed with holy spirit the apostles and other faithful men and women. He adopted them as his sons so that in time they would be resurrected to heaven to reign with Jesus. ([Rom. 8:2,][15-17]) These were the first to benefit from the liberty that Jesus announced in the synagogue of Nazareth. (Luke 4:16-19,[21]) Those men and women were no longer enslaved to false teachings and unscriptural practices of the Jewish religious leaders. God also considered them liberated from the deadly effects of sin. The symbolic Jubilee that began with the anointing of Christ’s followers in 33 C.E. will end at the conclusion of Jesus’ Thousand Year Reign. w19.12 11 ¶11-12

^ (John 8:36) So if the Son sets you free, you will be truly free.

^ (Lev. 25:8-12) “‘You will count off seven sabbath years, seven times seven years, and the days of the seven sabbath years will amount to 49 years. 9 You will then sound the horn loudly in the seventh month, on the tenth of the month; on the Day of Atonement, you should cause the sound of the horn to be heard in all your land. 10 You must sanctify the 50th year and proclaim liberty in the land to all its inhabitants. It will become a Jubilee for you, and each of you will return to his property and each of you should return to his family. 11 A Jubilee is what that 50th year will become for you. You will not sow seed or reap what grew on its own from leftover grain nor gather the grapes of unpruned vines. 12 For it is a Jubilee. It is to be holy to you. You may eat only what the land produces by itself.

^ (Rom. 8:2) For the law of the spirit that gives life in union with Christ Jesus has set you free from the law of sin and of death.

^ (Rom. 8:15-17) For you did not receive a spirit of slavery causing fear again, but you received a spirit of adoption as sons, by which spirit we cry out: “Abba, Father!” 16 The spirit itself bears witness with our spirit that we are God’s children. 17 If, then, we are children, we are also heirs—heirs indeed of God, but joint heirs with Christ—provided we suffer together so that we may also be glorified together.

^ (Luke 4:16-19) He then went to Nazʹa·reth, where he had been brought up, and according to his custom on the Sabbath day, he entered the synagogue and stood up to read. 17 So the scroll of the prophet Isaiah was handed to him, and he opened the scroll and found the place where it was written: 18 “Jehovah’s spirit is upon me, because he anointed me to declare good news to the poor. He sent me to proclaim liberty to the captives and a recovery of sight to the blind, to send the crushed ones away free, 19 to preach Jehovah’s acceptable year.”

^ (Luke 4:21) Then he began to say to them: “Today this scripture that you just heard* is fulfilled.”

Lit., “this scripture in your ears.”

Saturday, May 29

There is a friend who sticks closer than a brother.—[Prov. 18:24].

Be a trustworthy friend. For example, we not only promise to help our brothers and sisters in need but also do practical things to assist them. ([Matt. 5:37;][Luke 16:10]) When those who need help know that they can depend on us, they are genuinely comforted. One sister explains why. She says, “You do not have the added stress of wondering whether the person who offered to help will be there on time to do what he promised.” Those coping with a trial or disappointment often find comfort by confiding in a trusted friend. But to be a trusted friend and confidant, we need to cultivate patience. When Zhanna’s husband left her, she found comfort in sharing her feelings with close friends. “They patiently listened to me,” she says, “although I probably said the same things over and over again.” You too can prove to be a good friend by being a good listener. w20.01 10-11 ¶9-11

^ (Prov. 18:24) There are companions ready to crush one another, But there is a friend who sticks closer than a brother.

^ (Matt. 5:37) Just let your word ‘Yes’ mean yes, your ‘No,’ no, for what goes beyond these is from the wicked one.*

Or possibly, “from what is wicked.”

^ (Luke 16:10) The person faithful in what is least is faithful also in much, and the person unrighteous in what is least is unrighteous also in much.

June

Tuesday, June 1

Her rival wife taunted her relentlessly in order to upset her.—[1 Sam. 1:6].

The prophet Samuel’s mother, Hannah, had to deal with some difficult problems. For many years she was unable to have children. ([1 Sam. 1:2]) In Israelite culture, a woman who was barren was believed to be cursed. This left her feeling humiliated. ([Gen. 30:1, 2]) To make matters worse for Hannah, her husband had another wife, Peninnah, who bore him children and taunted Hannah about it. Hannah did not cope well with these difficult challenges. She was so upset that “she would weep and not eat.” She became “extremely bitter” at heart. ([1 Sam. 1:7,][10]) How did Hannah find comfort? Hannah poured out her feelings to Jehovah in prayer. After she prayed, she explained her situation to High Priest Eli. He then told her: “Go in peace, and may the God of Israel grant your petition.” What was the result? Hannah “went on her way and ate, and her face was no longer downcast.” (1 Sam. 1:17, 18) Prayer helped Hannah to regain peace. w20.02 21 ¶4-5

^ (1 Sam. 1:6) Moreover, her rival wife taunted her relentlessly in order to upset her because Jehovah had not given her children.

^ (1 Sam. 1:2) He had two wives; one was named Hanʹnah, and the other was named Pe·ninʹnah. Pe·ninʹnah had children, but Hanʹnah had no children.

^ (Gen. 30:1, 2) When Rachel saw that she had borne no children to Jacob, she became jealous of her sister and began to say to Jacob: “Give me children or else I will die.” 2 At this Jacob’s anger flared up against Rachel, and he said: “Am I in the place of God, who has prevented you from having children?”*

Or “has withheld the fruit of the womb from you?”

^ (1 Sam. 1:7) That is what she would do year after year; whenever Hanʹnah went up to the house of Jehovah, her rival would taunt her so much that she would weep and not eat.

^ (1 Sam. 1:10) Hanʹnah was extremely bitter,* and she began to pray to Jehovah and to weep uncontrollably.

Or “bitter of soul.”

^ (1 Sam. 1:17, 18) Then Eʹli answered: “Go in peace, and may the God of Israel grant your petition that you have asked of him.” 18 To this she said: “Let your servant find favor in your eyes.” And the woman went on her way and ate, and her face was no longer downcast.

Thursday, June 3

Christ [left] a model for you to follow his steps closely.—[1 Pet. 2:21].

What was your reaction when you learned the following truths about the Son? Jesus is the second most important person in the universe. He is our Ransomer. He willingly gave his life for us. When we show by our actions that we have faith in the ransom, we can have our sins forgiven, develop a friendship with God, and gain everlasting life. ([John 3:16]) Jesus is our High Priest. He wants to help us to benefit from the ransom and to have a close relationship with God. ([Heb. 4:15;][7:24, 25]) As King of God’s Kingdom, he is the one through whom Jehovah will sanctify His name, end wickedness, and bring eternal blessings in the coming Paradise. (Matt. 6:9, 10;[Rev. 11:15]) Jesus is our model. He set an example for us in devoting his life to doing God’s will. ([John 4:34]) When you accept what the Bible teaches about Jesus, you come to love God’s dear Son. That love moves you to use your life to do God’s will, as Jesus did. w20.03 10 ¶12-13

^ (1 Pet. 2:21) In fact, to this course you were called, because even Christ suffered for you, leaving a model for you to follow his steps closely.

^ (John 3:16) “For God loved the world so much that he gave his only-begotten Son, so that everyone exercising faith in him might not be destroyed but have everlasting life.

^ (Heb. 4:15) For we do not have a high priest who cannot sympathize with our weaknesses, but we have one who has been tested in all respects as we have, but without sin.

^ (Heb. 7:24, 25) but because he continues alive forever, his priesthood has no successors. 25 So he is able also to save completely those who are approaching God through him, because he is always alive to plead for them.

^ (Matt. 6:9, 10) “You must pray, then, this way: “‘Our Father in the heavens, let your name be sanctified. 10 Let your Kingdom come. Let your will take place, as in heaven, also on earth.

^ (Rev. 11:15) The seventh angel blew his trumpet. And there were loud voices in heaven, saying: “The kingdom of the world has become the Kingdom of our Lord and of his Christ, and he will rule as king forever and ever.”

^ (John 4:34) Jesus said to them: “My food is to do the will of him who sent me and to finish his work.

Saturday, June 5

I am Jehovah; I do not change.—[Mal. 3:6].

Jehovah hates spiritism! He told the Israelites: “There should not be found in you anyone who makes his son or his daughter pass through the fire, anyone who employs divination, anyone practicing magic, anyone who looks for omens, a sorcerer, anyone binding others with a spell, anyone who consults a spirit medium or a fortune-teller, or anyone who inquires of the dead. For whoever does these things is detestable to Jehovah.” (Deut. 18:10-12) Christians are not under the Law that Jehovah gave to the Israelites. However, we know that his feelings about spiritism have not changed. Jehovah warns us against spiritism because he knows that Satan uses it to harm people. Satan uses spiritism to promote lies—including the lie that the dead are alive in some other realm. ([Eccl. 9:5]) Satan also uses spiritism to keep people in fear and to turn them away from Jehovah. His aim is that people who practice spiritism will trust in wicked spirits instead of in Jehovah. w19.04 21 ¶5-6

^ (Mal. 3:6) “For I am Jehovah; I do not change.* And you are sons of Jacob; you have not yet come to your finish.

Or “I have not changed.”

^ (Deut. 18:10-12) There should not be found in you anyone who makes his son or his daughter pass through the fire, anyone who employs divination, anyone practicing magic, anyone who looks for omens, a sorcerer, 11 anyone binding others with a spell, anyone who consults a spirit medium or a fortune-teller, or anyone who inquires of the dead. 12 For whoever does these things is detestable to Jehovah, and on account of these detestable practices Jehovah your God is driving them away from before you.

^ (Eccl. 9:5) For the living know* that they will die, but the dead know nothing at all, nor do they have any more reward,* because all memory of them is forgotten.

Or “are conscious.”

Or “wages.”

Sunday, June 6

If you are doing what is bad, be in fear.—[Rom. 13:4].

Child abuse is a grave sin. The child abuser hurts the child in devastating ways. He betrays the child’s trust, robbing the child of his or her security. Children must be protected from such a wicked deed, and those who have been victimized by it need comfort and help. (1 Thess. 5:14) When someone who is a part of the congregation becomes guilty of child abuse, he brings reproach on the congregation. ([Matt. 5:16;][1 Pet. 2:12]) We do not tolerate in our midst individuals who unrepentantly commit wicked deeds and who bring reproach on the good name of the congregation. If someone in the congregation becomes guilty of violating a criminal law, such as by committing child abuse, he is sinning against the secular authorities. (Compare [Acts 25:8].) While the elders are not authorized to enforce the law of the land, they do not shield any perpetrator of child abuse from the legal consequences of his sin. w19.05 9 ¶4-7

^ (Rom. 13:4) for it is God’s minister* to you for your good. But if you are doing what is bad, be in fear, for it is not without purpose that it bears the sword. It is God’s minister, an avenger to express wrath against the one practicing what is bad.

Lit., “servant.”

^ (1 Thess. 5:14) On the other hand, we urge you, brothers, to warn* the disorderly, speak consolingly to those who are depressed,* support the weak, be patient toward all.

Or “admonish.”

Or “those who are discouraged.” Lit., “those of little soul.”

^ (Matt. 5:16) Likewise, let your light shine before men, so that they may see your fine works and give glory to your Father who is in the heavens.

^ (1 Pet. 2:12) Maintain your conduct fine among the nations, so that when they accuse you of being wrongdoers, they may be eyewitnesses of your fine works and, as a result, glorify God in the day of his inspection.

^ (Acts 25:8) But Paul said in defense: “Neither against the Law of the Jews nor against the temple nor against Caesar have I committed any sin.”

Monday, June 7

The wisdom of this world is foolishness with God.—[1 Cor. 3:19].

We can face any challenge—all because Jehovah is our Grand Instructor. (Isa. 30:20, 21) His Word gives us everything we need to be “fully competent” and “completely equipped for every good work.” ([2 Tim. 3:17]) When we live by Bible teachings, we become wiser than those who promote “the wisdom of this world.” (Ps. 119:97-100) Regrettably, the wisdom of the world often appeals to our fleshly desires. So we might find it difficult to resist thinking and acting like those who are part of the world. For good reason, the Bible says: “Look out that no one takes you captive by means of the philosophy and empty deception according to human tradition.” ([Col. 2:8]) As the Bible foretold about the last days, people would to a remarkable degree become “lovers of pleasures.” ([2 Tim. 3:4]) The prevalence of sexually transmitted diseases, such as AIDS, is just one indication that the wisdom of the world is foolishness.—[2 Pet. 2:19]. w19.05 21 ¶1-2; 22 ¶4-5

^ (1 Cor. 3:19) For the wisdom of this world is foolishness with God, for it is written: “He catches the wise in their own cunning.”

^ (Isa. 30:20, 21) Though Jehovah will give you bread in the form of distress and water in the form of oppression, your Grand Instructor will no longer hide himself, and you will see your Grand Instructor with your own eyes. 21 And your own ears will hear a word behind you saying, “This is the way. Walk in it,” in case you should go to the right or in case you should go to the left.

^ (2 Tim. 3:17) so that the man of God may be fully competent, completely equipped for every good work.

^ (Ps. 119:97-100) How I do love your law! I ponder over* it all day long. 98 Your commandment makes me wiser than my enemies, Because it is with me forever. 99 I have more insight than all my teachers, Because I ponder over* your reminders. 100 I act with more understanding than older men, Because I observe your orders.

Or “study.”

Or “study.”

^ (Col. 2:8) Look out that no one takes you captive* by means of the philosophy and empty deception according to human tradition, according to the elementary things of the world and not according to Christ;

Or “carries you off as his prey.”

^ (2 Tim. 3:4) betrayers, headstrong, puffed up with pride, lovers of pleasures rather than lovers of God,

^ (2 Pet. 2:19) While they are promising them freedom, they themselves are slaves of corruption; for if anyone is overcome by someone, he is his slave.*

Or “overcome by something, he is its slave.”

Thursday, June 10

Throw your burden on Jehovah, and he will sustain you.—[Ps. 55:22].

Are you dealing with a stressful situation? How comforting it is for us to know that Jehovah understands our emotional struggles. He knows our limitations, and he even knows what we are thinking and feeling. ([Ps. 103:14;][139:3, 4]) By relying on Jehovah, we will receive help to deal with problems that cause us stress. Stress can cause you to think negatively, making you feel discouraged. If that happens, remember that Jehovah will help you deal with stress. How will he help you? He invites you to share your concerns with him. And he will answer your cries for help. ([Ps. 5:3;][1 Pet. 5:7]) So pray to Jehovah often about your problems. He will not speak directly to you, but he will speak to you through his Word, the Bible, and through his organization. The accounts you read in the Bible can comfort you and give you hope. Also, your brothers and sisters can encourage you.—[Rom. 15:4;] Heb. 10:24, 25. w19.06 16 ¶7-8

^ (Ps. 55:22) Throw your burden on Jehovah, And he will sustain you. Never will he allow the righteous one to fall.*

Or “stagger; totter.”

^ (Ps. 103:14) For he well knows how we are formed, Remembering that we are dust.

^ (Ps. 139:3, 4) You observe* me when I travel and when I lie down; You are familiar with all my ways.  4 There is not a word on my tongue, But look! O Jehovah, you already know it well.

Lit., “measure.”

^ (Ps. 5:3) O Jehovah, you will hear my voice in the morning; In the morning I will express my concern to you and wait expectantly.

^ (1 Pet. 5:7) while you throw all your anxiety* on him, because he cares for you.

Or “cares; worries.”

^ (Rom. 15:4) For all the things that were written beforehand were written for our instruction, so that through our endurance and through the comfort from the Scriptures we might have hope.

^ (Heb. 10:24, 25) And let us consider* one another so as to incite* to love and fine works, 25 not forsaking our meeting together, as some have the custom, but encouraging one another, and all the more so as you see the day drawing near.

Or “be concerned about; pay attention to.”

Or “motivate; stir up.”

Sunday, June 13

Wisdom is a protection just as money is a protection, but the advantage of knowledge is this: Wisdom preserves the life of its owner.—[Eccl. 7:12].

Many people are first attracted to the practical wisdom found in the Bible. In New York, a sister who visits Mandarin-speaking people says: “I try to take an interest in people and listen to them. If I learn that they are new immigrants, I might ask: ‘How are you settling in? Have you found work? Are the local people treating you well?’” Sometimes this opens the way to introduce a Bible teaching. When appropriate, the sister may add: “What would you say is the key to getting along with people? May I show you a proverb from the Bible? It says: ‘Beginning a fight is like opening a floodgate; before the quarrel breaks out, take your leave.’ Do you think that this advice could help us to get along with others?” ([Prov. 17:14]) Such conversations can help us to identify people who would welcome further visits. w19.07 23 ¶13

^ (Eccl. 7:12) For wisdom is a protection just as money is a protection, but the advantage of knowledge is this: Wisdom preserves the life of its owner.

^ (Prov. 17:14) Beginning a fight is like opening a floodgate;* Before the quarrel breaks out, take your leave.

Or “like opening a dam.” Lit., “letting out waters.”

Monday, June 14

What will happen to the one who falls with no one to help him up?—[Eccl. 4:10].

Those who have moved to a new assignment need, not pity, but understanding. They may be struggling to deal with their own health problems or those of their relative. They may be grieving over the death of a loved one. And they also may grieve, even if in private, over the loss of association with their spiritual family in their former assignment. It takes time to process such deep and often very mixed emotions. In the meantime, your support and example can help them to adjust. “In my previous assignment, I conducted Bible studies every day,” says a sister who served for many years in a foreign land. “In my new one, it was difficult even to get the opportunity to open the Bible or to show a video in the ministry. But local publishers invited me on their calls and studies. This gave me a more positive outlook. I learned to start conversations in the new territory. All of this helped me to regain joy.” w19.08 22 ¶10; 24 ¶13-14

^ (Eccl. 4:10) For if one of them falls, the other can help his partner up. But what will happen to the one who falls with no one to help him up?

Saturday, June 19

You are not in darkness, so that the day should overtake you as it would thieves.—[1 Thess. 5:4].

In his exhortation, the apostle Paul mentions “Jehovah’s day.” (1 Thess. 5:1-6) As used in this context, this refers to the time period that begins with the attack on “Babylon the Great,” the world empire of false religion, and ends with Armageddon. ([Rev. 16:14,][16;][17:5]) Paul also tells us how we can make sure that we are ready for “Jehovah’s day.” We should “not sleep on as the rest do.” We must “stay awake” and remain alert to the danger of compromising our neutrality by getting drawn into the world’s political issues. If we were to get involved, we could become “part of the world.” ([John 15:19]) We know that God’s Kingdom is the only hope for world peace. We also want to help others wake up to what the Bible foretold would happen in the world. Once the great tribulation begins, it will be too late for people to turn to Jehovah. That is why our preaching work is so urgent! w19.10 8 ¶3; 9 ¶5-6

^ (1 Thess. 5:4) But you, brothers, you are not in darkness, so that the day should overtake you as it would thieves,

^ (1 Thess. 5:1-6) Now as for the times and the seasons, brothers, you need nothing to be written to you. 2 For you yourselves know very well that Jehovah’s* day is coming exactly as a thief in the night. 3 Whenever it is that they are saying, “Peace and security!” then sudden destruction is to be instantly on them, just like birth pains on a pregnant woman, and they will by no means escape. 4 But you, brothers, you are not in darkness, so that the day should overtake you as it would thieves, 5 for you are all sons of light and sons of day. We belong neither to night nor to darkness. 6 So, then, let us not sleep on as the rest do, but let us stay awake and keep our senses.

See App. A5.

^ (Rev. 16:14) They are, in fact, expressions inspired by demons and they perform signs, and they go out to the kings of the entire inhabited earth, to gather them together to the war of the great day of God the Almighty.

^ (Rev. 16:16) And they gathered them together to the place that is called in Hebrew Armageddon.*

Greek, Har Ma·ge·donʹ, from a Hebrew term meaning “Mountain of Megiddo.”

^ (Rev. 17:5) On her forehead was written a name, a mystery: “Babylon the Great, the mother of the prostitutes and of the disgusting things of the earth.”

^ (John 15:19) If you were part of the world, the world would be fond of what is its own. Now because you are no part of the world, but I have chosen you out of the world, for this reason the world hates you.

Sunday, June 20

Take a scroll and write in it all the words that I have spoken to you against Israel and Judah.—[Jer. 36:2].

When the time came for the contents of the scroll to be revealed, Jeremiah had to rely on his friend Baruch to deliver the message. ([Jer. 36:5, 6]) Baruch courageously fulfilled his dangerous assignment. Can you imagine how proud Jeremiah must have felt when Baruch went to the temple courtyard and did what he had been asked to do? ([Jer. 36:8-10]) The princes of Judah heard what Baruch had done, and they commanded him to read the scroll aloud to them! (Jer. 36:14, 15) The princes decided to tell King Jehoiakim what Jeremiah had said. King Jehoiakim got so angry when he heard the words written by Jeremiah that he burned the scroll and ordered the arrest of Jeremiah and Baruch. However, Jeremiah took another scroll, gave it to Baruch, and as Jeremiah dictated Jehovah’s message, Baruch wrote “all the words of the scroll that King Jehoiakim of Judah had burned in the fire.”—Jer. 36:26-28,[32]. w19.11 3-4 ¶4-6

^ (Jer. 36:2) “Take a scroll* and write in it all the words that I have spoken to you against Israel and Judah and all the nations, from the first day I spoke to you in the days of Jo·siʹah to this day.

Lit., “a scroll of a book.”

^ (Jer. 36:5, 6) Then Jeremiah commanded Barʹuch: “I am confined and unable to enter the house of Jehovah. 6 So you are the one who must go in and read aloud the words of Jehovah from the scroll that you wrote at my dictation. Read them in the hearing of the people at the house of Jehovah on the day of a fast; thus you will read them to all the people of Judah who come in from their cities.

^ (Jer. 36:8-10) So Barʹuch the son of Ne·riʹah did all that Jeremiah the prophet had commanded him; he read aloud from the scroll* the words of Jehovah at the house of Jehovah. 9 Now in the fifth year of Je·hoiʹa·kim son of Jo·siʹah, the king of Judah, in the ninth month, all the people in Jerusalem and all the people who came into Jerusalem from the cities of Judah proclaimed a fast before Jehovah. 10 Barʹuch then read aloud from the scroll* the words of Jeremiah at the house of Jehovah, in the chamber* of Gem·a·riʹah the son of Shaʹphan the copyist,* in the upper courtyard, at the entrance of the new gate of the house of Jehovah, in the hearing of all the people.

Or “book.”

Or “book.”

Or “dining room.”

Or “scribe.”

^ (Jer. 36:14, 15) Then all the princes sent Je·huʹdi the son of Neth·a·niʹah the son of Shel·e·miʹah the son of Cushʹi to Barʹuch, saying: “Come and bring with you the scroll from which you read in the hearing of the people.” Barʹuch the son of Ne·riʹah took the scroll in his hand and went in to them. 15 They said to him: “Sit down, please, and read it aloud to us.” So Barʹuch read it to them.

^ (Jer. 36:26-28) Further, the king commanded Je·rahʹme·el the son of the king, Se·raiʹah the son of Azʹri·el, and Shel·e·miʹah the son of Abʹde·el to seize Barʹuch the secretary and Jeremiah the prophet, but Jehovah kept them concealed. 27 And the word of Jehovah again came to Jeremiah after the king had burned up the scroll containing the words that Barʹuch had written at Jeremiah’s dictation, saying: 28 “Take another scroll and write on it all the same words that were on the first scroll, which King Je·hoiʹa·kim of Judah burned up.

^ (Jer. 36:32) Jeremiah then took another scroll and gave it to Barʹuch the son of Ne·riʹah, the secretary, and at Jeremiah’s dictation he wrote on it all the words of the scroll* that King Je·hoiʹa·kim of Judah had burned in the fire. And many more words like those were added.

Or “book.”

Wednesday, June 23

Then sudden destruction is to be instantly on them.—[1 Thess. 5:3].

The proclamation of “peace and security” precedes “Jehovah’s day.” (1 Thess. 5:1-6) At 1 Thessalonians 5:2, “Jehovah’s day” refers to “the great tribulation.” ([Rev. 7:14]) How will we know when that tribulation is about to begin? The Bible tells us about a most unusual proclamation. It will serve as a signal announcing the great tribulation. That will be the foretold proclamation of “peace and security.” Will religious leaders participate? Possibly. Nevertheless, the proclamation will be just another demon-inspired lie. But this lie will be especially dangerous because it will give people a false sense of security just before the greatest tribulation in human history begins. Yes, “sudden destruction is to be instantly on them, just like birth pains on a pregnant woman.” What about Jehovah’s loyal servants? They may be surprised by the sudden start of Jehovah’s day, but they will not be caught off guard. w19.09 9 ¶7-8

^ (1 Thess. 5:3) Whenever it is that they are saying, “Peace and security!” then sudden destruction is to be instantly on them, just like birth pains on a pregnant woman, and they will by no means escape.

^ (1 Thess. 5:1-6) Now as for the times and the seasons, brothers, you need nothing to be written to you. 2 For you yourselves know very well that Jehovah’s* day is coming exactly as a thief in the night. 3 Whenever it is that they are saying, “Peace and security!” then sudden destruction is to be instantly on them, just like birth pains on a pregnant woman, and they will by no means escape. 4 But you, brothers, you are not in darkness, so that the day should overtake you as it would thieves, 5 for you are all sons of light and sons of day. We belong neither to night nor to darkness. 6 So, then, let us not sleep on as the rest do, but let us stay awake and keep our senses.

See App. A5.

^ (1 Thess. 5:2) For you yourselves know very well that Jehovah’s* day is coming exactly as a thief in the night.

See App. A5.

^ (Rev. 7:14) So right away I said to him: “My lord, you are the one who knows.” And he said to me: “These are the ones who come out of the great tribulation, and they have washed their robes and made them white in the blood of the Lamb.

Thursday, June 24

There is an appointed time for everything, . . . a time to search and a time to give up as lost.—[Eccl. 3:1,][6].

When making decisions, be specific. The more specific you are, the more likely you are to complete what you start. For example, you may have decided to read the Bible more often. But if you do not have a specific schedule in mind, you may not achieve your objective. Or the elders in a congregation may decide to shepherd the flock more often, but after some time, they have not followed through on that decision. To be successful, they could ask such questions as these: “Have we identified the brothers and sisters who could especially benefit from more shepherding? Have we set a specific time to visit them?” Also, be realistic. None of us have the time, resources, or energy to do everything that we would like to do. So be realistic and reasonable. When necessary, you may need to change a decision that was beyond your ability to accomplish. w19.11 29 ¶11-12

^ (Eccl. 3:1) There is an appointed time for everything, A time for every activity under the heavens:

^ (Eccl. 3:6) A time to search and a time to give up as lost; A time to keep and a time to throw away;

Saturday, June 26

These words . . . must be on your heart, and you must inculcate them in your sons.—[Deut. 6:6, 7].

“To inculcate” means “to teach and impress by frequent repetitions.” To do so, parents need to spend time regularly with their young ones. It could at times seem frustrating to have to repeat instructions to the children. However, parents can strive to see this as a way to help their children understand God’s Word and apply it. So be discerning. [Psalm 127] compares children to arrows. ([Ps. 127:4]) Just as arrows can be made from different materials and can vary in size, no two children are precisely alike. So parents need to determine how to train each of their children. A couple in modern-day Israel who successfully raised two children to serve Jehovah tell what they found to be helpful, “We conducted a Bible study with each child separately.” Of course, each family head will decide whether studying in that way is necessary or possible. w19.12 26-27 ¶18-20

^ (Deut. 6:6, 7) These words that I am commanding you today must be on your heart, 7 and you must inculcate them in* your sons and speak of them when you sit in your house and when you walk on the road and when you lie down and when you get up.

Or “repeat them to; impress them upon.”

^ (Ps. 127:0-5) A Song of the Ascents. Of Solomon. 127 Unless Jehovah builds the house, It is in vain that its builders work hard on it. Unless Jehovah guards the city, It is in vain that the guard stays awake.  2 It is in vain that you rise up early, That you stay up late, That you toil for your food, Since he provides for his loved ones while giving them sleep.  3 Look! Sons* are an inheritance from Jehovah; The fruit of the womb is a reward.  4 Like arrows in the hand of a mighty man, So are the sons of one’s youth.  5 Happy is the man who fills his quiver with them. They will not be put to shame, For they will speak with enemies in the city gate.

Or “Children.”

^ (Ps. 127:4) Like arrows in the hand of a mighty man, So are the sons of one’s youth.

Sunday, June 27

All things . . . that you want men to do to you, you also must do to them.—[Matt. 7:12].

When we are going through a hard time, how we appreciate those who offer support in practical ways! “There are so many routine things that seem to be impossible to do when you are suffering,” says Ryan, whose father died unexpectedly in a tragic accident. “Practical assistance—even when it seems very little—goes a long way.” Never underestimate how comforting your practical yet simple acts of kindness can be. The first-century disciple Mark was a busy Christian. Yet, Mark made time to comfort the apostle Paul, and Paul felt free to ask for Mark’s assistance. Angela, who had to cope with the violent death of a family member, appreciated the willingness of those who comforted her. “When friends genuinely want to help, they are approachable,” she says. “They don’t seem reluctant or hesitant.” We can ask ourselves, ‘Am I known for being willing to comfort fellow worshippers in practical ways?’ w20.01 11-12 ¶14-16

^ (Matt. 7:12) “All things, therefore, that you want men to do to you, you also must do to them. This, in fact, is what the Law and the Prophets mean.

Monday, June 28

Whoever eats the loaf or drinks the cup of the Lord unworthily will be guilty.—[1 Cor. 11:27].

How might an anointed one partake “unworthily” at the Memorial? He would do so if he ate and drank the emblems but was not living up to Jehovah’s righteous standards. ([Heb. 6:4-6;][10:26-29]) Anointed ones realize that they must stay faithful if they want to receive “the prize of the upward call of God by means of Christ Jesus.” (Phil. 3:13-16) Jehovah’s holy spirit helps his servants to be humble, not proud. ([Eph. 4:1-3;][Col. 3:10,][12]) So anointed ones do not feel that they are better than others. They know that Jehovah does not necessarily give anointed ones more holy spirit than he gives his other servants. They do not feel that they have a deeper understanding of Bible truths than anyone else. And they would never tell someone else that he too has been anointed and should start partaking at the Memorial. Instead, they humbly acknowledge that only Jehovah invites people to go to heaven. w20.01 27-28 ¶4-5

^ (1 Cor. 11:27) Therefore, whoever eats the loaf or drinks the cup of the Lord unworthily will be guilty respecting the body and the blood of the Lord.

^ (Heb. 6:4-6) For as regards those who were once enlightened and who have tasted the heavenly free gift and who have become partakers of holy spirit 5 and who have tasted the fine word of God and powers of the coming system of things,* 6 but have fallen away, it is impossible to revive them again to repentance, because they nail the Son of God to the stake again for themselves and expose him to public shame.

Or “the coming age.” See Glossary.

^ (Heb. 10:26-29) For if we practice sin willfully after having received the accurate knowledge of the truth, there is no longer any sacrifice for sins left, 27 but there is a certain fearful expectation of judgment and a burning indignation that is going to consume those in opposition. 28 Anyone who has disregarded the Law of Moses dies without compassion on the testimony of two or three. 29 How much greater punishment do you think a person will deserve who has trampled on the Son of God and who has regarded as of ordinary value the blood of the covenant by which he was sanctified, and who has outraged the spirit of undeserved kindness with contempt?

^ (Phil. 3:13-16) Brothers, I do not yet consider myself as having taken hold of it; but one thing is certain: Forgetting the things behind and stretching forward to the things ahead, 14 I am pressing on toward the goal for the prize of the upward call of God by means of Christ Jesus. 15 Therefore, let those of us who are mature be of this mental attitude, and if you are mentally inclined otherwise in any respect, God will reveal the above attitude to you. 16 At any rate, to the extent we have made progress, let us go on walking orderly in this same course.

^ (Eph. 4:1-3) Therefore I, the prisoner in the Lord, appeal to you to walk worthily of the calling with which you were called, 2 with all humility* and mildness, with patience, putting up with one another in love, 3 earnestly endeavoring to maintain the oneness of the spirit in the uniting bond of peace.

Or “lowliness of mind.”

^ (Col. 3:10) and clothe yourselves with the new personality, which through accurate knowledge is being made new according to the image of the One who created it,

^ (Col. 3:12) Accordingly, as God’s chosen ones, holy and loved, clothe yourselves with the tender affections of compassion, kindness, humility,* mildness, and patience.

Or “lowliness of mind.”

Wednesday, June 30

Shepherd the flock of God under your care, serving as overseers.—[1 Pet. 5:2].

Jehovah has entrusted elders with the important responsibility to shepherd his people. Elders can learn much from examining how Nehemiah dealt with Jehovah’s people. As governor of Judah, Nehemiah had considerable authority. ([Neh. 1:11;][2:7, 8;][5:14]) Imagine some of the challenges that Nehemiah faced. He had learned that the people had defiled the temple and were not supporting the Levites financially as the Law directed. The Jews were violating the Sabbath law, and some of the men had married foreign women. Governor Nehemiah would have to handle this difficult situation. (Neh. 13:4-30) Nehemiah did not abuse his authority by imposing his own standards on God’s people. Instead, he sought Jehovah’s guidance in earnest prayer, and he taught the people Jehovah’s Law. ([Neh. 1:4-10;][13:1-3]) Nehemiah also humbly worked alongside his brothers, even helping them to rebuild Jerusalem’s walls.—[Neh. 4:15]. w19.09 16 ¶9-10

^ (1 Pet. 5:2) Shepherd the flock of God under your care, serving as overseers,* not under compulsion, but willingly before God; not for love of dishonest gain, but eagerly;

Or “carefully watching over it.”

^ (Neh. 1:11) O Jehovah, please, let your ear be attentive to the prayer of your servant and to the prayer of your servants who take delight in fearing your name, and please, grant success to your servant today, and may this man show me compassion.” Now I was cupbearer to the king.

^ (Neh. 2:7, 8) Then I said to the king: “If it pleases the king, let letters be given me for the governors of the region Beyond the River,* granting me safe passage until I reach Judah, 8 as well as a letter to Aʹsaph the keeper of the Royal Park,* so that he may give me timber for beams for the gates of the Fortress of the House* and for the walls of the city and for the house where I will go.” So the king gave them to me, for the good hand of my God was upon me.

Or “of Trans-Euphrates.”

Or “the king’s forest.”

Or “Temple.”

^ (Neh. 5:14) Moreover, from the day that he commissioned me to become their governor in the land of Judah, from the 20th year to the 32nd year of King Ar·ta·xerxʹes, 12 years, neither I nor my brothers ate the food allowance due the governor.

^ (Neh. 1:4-10) As soon as I heard these words, I sat down and began to weep and mourn for days, and I kept fasting and praying before the God of the heavens. 5 I said: “O Jehovah, the God of the heavens, the great and awe-inspiring God who keeps his covenant and shows loyal love to those who love him and keep his commandments, 6 please, let your ear be attentive and your eyes open to listen to the prayer of your servant that I am praying to you today, day and night, concerning your servants the Israelites, all the while confessing the sins that the people of Israel have committed against you. We have sinned, both I and the house of my father. 7 We have certainly acted corruptly against you by not keeping the commandments, regulations, and judicial decisions that you gave to your servant Moses. 8 “Remember, please, the word that you commanded* your servant Moses: ‘If you act unfaithfully, I will scatter you among the peoples. 9 But if you return to me and observe my commandments and obey them, though your dispersed people should be at the end of the heavens, I will gather them from there and bring them to the place that I have chosen to have my name reside.’ 10 They are your servants and your people, whom you redeemed by your great power and by your mighty hand.

Or “the warning you gave to.”

^ (Neh. 13:1-3) On that day the book of Moses was read in the hearing of the people, and it was found written that no Amʹmon·ite or Moʹab·ite should ever enter the congregation of the true God, 2 for they had not met the Israelites with bread and water, but instead they had hired Baʹlaam against them to curse them. However, our God had changed the curse into a blessing. 3 As soon as they heard the Law, they began to separate from Israel all those of foreign descent.*

Or “mixed descent.”

^ (Neh. 4:15) Now after our enemies heard that what they were doing had become known to us and that the true God had frustrated their plan, we all went back to work on the wall.

July

Thursday, July 1

Let your petitions be made known to God.—[Phil. 4:6].

When others speak harshly or act unkindly, we may feel anxious. That is especially true if the one who hurt us is a close friend or relative. In dealing with anxiety, we can learn much from the Bible example of Hannah, who was severely taunted by her husband’s second wife. ([1 Sam. 1:12]) Like Hannah, we can talk at length to Jehovah about our anxieties and fears. Our prayers do not have to be poetic or perfectly structured. We may even find ourselves expressing bitter words that are interrupted by sobs of grief. Even so, Jehovah will never get tired of listening to us. In addition to praying about our problems, we need to remember the advice recorded at Philippians 4:6, 7. The apostle Paul specifically mentioned that we should offer prayers of thanksgiving, or gratitude. We have so many reasons to thank Jehovah—including the gift of life, his creative works, his loyal love, and the wonderful hope that he has given us. w20.02 21 ¶3; 22 ¶6

^ (Phil. 4:6) Do not be anxious over anything, but in everything by prayer and supplication along with thanksgiving, let your petitions be made known to God;

^ (1 Sam. 1:12) While she prayed for a long time before Jehovah, Eʹli was watching her mouth.

^ (Phil. 4:6, 7) Do not be anxious over anything, but in everything by prayer and supplication along with thanksgiving, let your petitions be made known to God; 7 and the peace of God that surpasses all understanding will guard your hearts and your mental powers* by means of Christ Jesus.

Or “your minds; your thoughts.”

Saturday, July 3

Pray continually.—[Matt. 26:41].

What can we pray for? We can pray for Jehovah to “give us more faith.” ([Luke 17:5;][John 14:1]) We need faith because Satan will test all who follow Jesus. ([Luke 22:31]) How will faith help us? When we have done all that we reasonably can to deal with a trial, faith will move us to leave the matter with Jehovah. Because we trust that he can handle matters better than we ever could, we have peace of mind and heart. (1 Pet. 5:6, 7) Prayer helps us to maintain our inner peace no matter what trials we face. Consider the example of Robert, a faithful elder who is now in his 80’s. He says: “The counsel at Philippians 4:6, 7 has helped me to cope with many trials in my life. I have had to deal with financial problems. And I temporarily lost my privilege of serving as an elder.” What has helped Robert to maintain inner peace? “I pray as soon as I start to feel anxious,” he says. “I believe that the more frequently and intensely I pray, the more peaceful I feel.” w19.04 9-10 ¶5-7

^ (Matt. 26:41) Keep on the watch and pray continually, so that you may not enter into temptation. The spirit, of course, is eager,* but the flesh is weak.”

Or “willing.”

^ (Luke 17:5) Now the apostles said to the Lord: “Give us more faith.”

^ (John 14:1) “Do not let your hearts be troubled. Exercise faith in God; exercise faith also in me.

^ (Luke 22:31) “Simon, Simon, look! Satan has demanded to have all of you to sift you as wheat.

^ (1 Pet. 5:6, 7) Humble yourselves, therefore, under the mighty hand of God, so that he may exalt you in due time, 7 while you throw all your anxiety* on him, because he cares for you.

Or “cares; worries.”

^ (Phil. 4:6, 7) Do not be anxious over anything, but in everything by prayer and supplication along with thanksgiving, let your petitions be made known to God; 7 and the peace of God that surpasses all understanding will guard your hearts and your mental powers* by means of Christ Jesus.

Or “your minds; your thoughts.”

Sunday, July 4

Against you—you above all—I have sinned.—[Ps. 51:4].

Child abuse is a sin against God. When a human sins against another human, he also sins against Jehovah. Consider an example from the Law that God gave Israel. The Law said that a man who robbed or defrauded his neighbor was behaving “unfaithfully toward Jehovah.” ([Lev. 6:2-4]) Certainly, then, when an individual who is a part of the congregation abuses a child—robbing that child of his or her security—he is behaving unfaithfully toward God. The abuser brings great reproach on Jehovah’s name. For that reason, abuse must be condemned for what it is—a gross sin against God. Articles in The Watchtower and Awake! have discussed how those who have been sexually abused can deal with emotional scars, how others can help and encourage them, and how parents can protect their children. Elders have received detailed Scriptural training on how to handle the sin of child abuse. The organization continues to review the way congregations handle the sin of child abuse. w19.05 9 ¶8-9

^ (Ps. 51:4) Against you—you above all*—I have sinned; What is bad in your eyes I have done. Therefore, you are righteous when you speak, You are right in your judgment.

Lit., “only you.”

^ (Lev. 6:2-4) “If someone* sins and behaves unfaithfully toward Jehovah by deceiving his neighbor in connection with something entrusted to him, or something deposited with him, or he robs or defrauds his neighbor, 3 or he finds something lost and is deceptive about it, and if he swears falsely over any such sin he may commit, this is what he should do: 4 If he has sinned and is guilty, he must return what he stole, what he extorted, what he took by fraud, what was entrusted to him, or the lost thing that he found,

Or “a soul.”

Wednesday, July 7

You will come against them like a storm, . . . you and all your troops and many peoples with you.—[Ezek. 38:9].

God will not allow the nations to destroy his people. They proudly bear his name, and they have obeyed his command to flee from Babylon the Great. (Acts 15:16, 17;[Rev. 18:4]) They have also worked hard to help others flee from her. So Jehovah’s servants will not “receive part of her plagues.” Still, their faith will be tested. ([Ezek. 38:2,][8]) After the destruction of all false religious organizations, God’s people will stand out like a lone tree that survived a fierce storm. Satan, of course, will be enraged. He will vent that rage by using demonic propaganda—“unclean inspired expressions”—to cause a coalition of nations to turn on Jehovah’s servants. (Rev. 16:13, 14) That coalition is called “Gog of the land of Magog.” When the nations launch their attack, they will have arrived at the symbolic place called Armageddon.—[Rev. 16:16]. w19.09 11 ¶12-13

^ (Ezek. 38:9) You will come against them like a storm, and you will cover the land like clouds, you and all your troops and many peoples with you.”’

^ (Acts 15:16, 17) ‘After these things I will return and raise up again the tent of David that is fallen down; I will rebuild its ruins and restore it, 17 so that the men who remain may earnestly seek Jehovah, together with people of all the nations, people who are called by my name, says Jehovah, who is doing these things,

^ (Rev. 18:4) And I heard another voice out of heaven say: “Get out of her, my people, if you do not want to share with her in her sins, and if you do not want to receive part of her plagues.

^ (Ezek. 38:2) “Son of man, set your face against Gog of the land of Maʹgog, the head chieftain* of Meʹshech and Tuʹbal, and prophesy against him.

Or “chief prince.”

^ (Ezek. 38:8) “‘“You will be given attention* after many days. In the final part of the years you will invade the land whose people have been restored from the ravages of the sword, collected together out of many peoples onto the mountains of Israel, which had long been lying devastated. The inhabitants of this land were restored from the peoples, and all of them dwell in security.

Or “summoned.”

^ (Rev. 16:13, 14) And I saw three unclean inspired expressions* that looked like frogs come out of the mouth of the dragon and out of the mouth of the wild beast and out of the mouth of the false prophet. 14 They are, in fact, expressions inspired by demons and they perform signs, and they go out to the kings of the entire inhabited earth, to gather them together to the war of the great day of God the Almighty.

Lit., “unclean spirits.”

^ (Rev. 16:16) And they gathered them together to the place that is called in Hebrew Armageddon.*

Greek, Har Ma·ge·donʹ, from a Hebrew term meaning “Mountain of Megiddo.”

Thursday, July 8

The reasonings of the wise men are futile.—[1 Cor. 3:20].

In the days of ancient Israel, Satan used false religion to promote immorality. Today, he does the same. False religion tolerates and even promotes immoral conduct. Consequently, many who claim to serve God have abandoned his clear standards of morality. The apostle Paul describes in his letter to the Romans what has been the result. ([Rom. 1:28-31]) Among “the things not fitting” are all forms of sexual immorality, including homosexuality. (Rom. 1:24-27,[32;][Rev. 2:20]) How important it is for us to stick to the Bible’s clear teachings! Human philosophy ignores or contradicts Jehovah’s righteous standards. It does not nurture the fruitage of God’s spirit but, rather, “the works of the flesh.” ([Gal. 5:19-23]) It generates pride and arrogance, and the result is that people become “lovers of themselves.” ([2 Tim. 3:2-4]) These qualities are the opposite of the meek, humble spirit that God’s servants are encouraged to have.—[2 Sam. 22:28]. w19.06 5-6 ¶12-14

^ (1 Cor. 3:20) And again: “Jehovah knows that the reasonings of the wise men are futile.”

^ (Rom. 1:28-31) Just as they did not see fit to acknowledge God,* God gave them over to a disapproved mental state, to do the things not fitting. 29 And they were filled with all unrighteousness, wickedness, greed, and badness, being full of envy, murder, strife, deceit, and malice, being whisperers, 30 backbiters, haters of God, insolent, haughty, boastful, schemers of what is harmful,* disobedient to parents, 31 without understanding, false to agreements, having no natural affection, and merciless.

Or “they did not consider it worthwhile to have accurate knowledge of God.” Lit., “they did not approve of holding God in accurate knowledge.”

Or “inventors of injurious things.”

^ (Rom. 1:24-27) Therefore, God, in keeping with the desires of their hearts, gave them up to uncleanness, so that their bodies might be dishonored among them. 25 They exchanged the truth of God for the lie and venerated* and rendered sacred service to the creation rather than the Creator, who is praised forever. Amen. 26 That is why God gave them over to disgraceful sexual passion, for their females changed the natural use of themselves into one contrary to nature; 27 likewise also the males left the natural use of the female and became violently inflamed in their lust toward one another, males with males, working what is obscene and receiving in themselves the full penalty, which was due for their error.

Or “worshipped.”

^ (Rom. 1:32) Although these know full well the righteous decree of God—that those practicing such things are deserving of death—they not only keep on doing them but also approve of those practicing them.

^ (Rev. 2:20) “‘Nevertheless, I do hold this against you, that you tolerate that woman Jezʹe·bel, who calls herself a prophetess, and she teaches and misleads my slaves to commit sexual immorality* and to eat things sacrificed to idols.

See Glossary.

^ (Gal. 5:19-23) Now the works of the flesh are plainly seen, and they are sexual immorality,* uncleanness, brazen conduct,* 20 idolatry, spiritism,* hostility, strife, jealousy, fits of anger, dissensions, divisions, sects, 21 envy, drunkenness, wild parties,* and things like these. I am forewarning you about these things, the same way I already warned you, that those who practice such things will not inherit God’s Kingdom. 22 On the other hand, the fruitage of the spirit is love, joy, peace, patience,* kindness, goodness, faith, 23 mildness, self-control. Against such things there is no law.

Greek, por·neiʹa. See Glossary.

Or “shameless conduct.” Greek, a·selʹgei·a. See Glossary.

Or “sorcery; druggery.”

Or “revelries.”

Or “long-suffering.”

^ (2 Tim. 3:2-4) For men will be lovers of themselves, lovers of money, boastful, haughty, blasphemers, disobedient to parents, unthankful, disloyal, 3 having no natural affection, not open to any agreement, slanderers, without self-control, fierce, without love of goodness, 4 betrayers, headstrong, puffed up with pride, lovers of pleasures rather than lovers of God,

^ (2 Sam. 22:28) For you save those who are humble, But your eyes are against the haughty, and you abase them.

Sunday, July 11

Go, therefore, and make disciples of people of all the nations.—[Matt. 28:19].

Some people are eager to learn Bible truths, but many we meet may seem to be indifferent at first. We may have to stimulate their interest. To be successful in the ministry, we need to have a well-thought-out strategy. Select specific subjects that will likely interest those you will meet. Then plan how you will introduce the topic. For example, you might ask a householder: “Would you mind if I ask your opinion on something? Many problems facing us today affect people around the world. Do you think that it would take a world government to solve the world’s problems?” Then you could discuss [Daniel 2:44]. Or you might say to a neighbor: “What do you think is the key to raising well-behaved children? I would like to hear your opinion.” Then discuss Deuteronomy 6:6, 7. Without a doubt, we feel intense joy when we help people become disciples of Christ. w19.07 15 ¶4, 6-7

^ (Matt. 28:19) Go, therefore, and make disciples of people of all the nations, baptizing them in the name of the Father and of the Son and of the holy spirit,

^ (Dan. 2:44) “In the days of those kings the God of heaven will set up a kingdom that will never be destroyed. And this kingdom will not be passed on to any other people. It will crush and put an end to all these kingdoms, and it alone will stand forever,

^ (Deut. 6:6, 7) These words that I am commanding you today must be on your heart, 7 and you must inculcate them in* your sons and speak of them when you sit in your house and when you walk on the road and when you lie down and when you get up.

Or “repeat them to; impress them upon.”

Monday, July 12

Can a man make gods for himself when they are not really gods?—[Jer. 16:20].

A brother with much experience preaching to nonreligious people in the Far East explains: “Typically, when a person here says, ‘I don’t believe in God,’ he means that he does not believe in worshipping traditional gods. So I usually agree that most gods are man-made and are not real. I often read Jeremiah 16:20 and ask: ‘How could we tell a real god from man-made ones?’ I listen carefully, and then I read [Isaiah 41:23]: ‘Tell us what will happen in the future, so that we may know that you are gods.’ Then I show an example of how Jehovah has foretold the future.” Another brother says: “I show them examples of Bible wisdom, fulfilled Bible prophecies, and laws that control the universe. Then I show them how all of it points to a living and wise Creator. When a person accepts the possibility that God exists, I start showing him what the Bible says about Jehovah.” w19.07 23-24 ¶14-15

^ (Jer. 16:20) Can a man make gods for himself When they are not really gods?

^ (Jer. 16:20) Can a man make gods for himself When they are not really gods?

^ (Isa. 41:23) Tell us what will happen in the future, So that we may know that you are gods. Yes, do something, good or bad, So that we may be amazed when we see it.

Sunday, July 18

Jehovah’s day is coming exactly as a thief in the night.—[1 Thess. 5:2].

In the short time remaining before his “day” begins, Jehovah expects us to keep busy in the preaching work. We need to make sure that we are “having plenty to do in the work of the Lord.” ([1 Cor. 15:58]) When Jesus spoke about all the significant things that would happen during the last days, he added: “Also, in all the nations, the good news has to be preached first.” ([Mark 13:4,][8,][10;][Matt. 24:14]) Just think: Every time you go in the ministry, you are having a share in fulfilling that Bible prophecy! Year by year, the Kingdom-preaching work is moving ahead. For example, think about the increase in the number of Kingdom proclaimers worldwide during the last days. In 1914, there were 5,155 publishers in 43 lands. Today, there are some 8.5 million publishers in 240 lands! Even so, our work is not yet over. We must keep proclaiming God’s Kingdom as the only solution to all mankind’s problems.—Ps. 145:11-13. w19.10 8 ¶3; 9-10 ¶7-8

^ (1 Thess. 5:2) For you yourselves know very well that Jehovah’s* day is coming exactly as a thief in the night.

See App. A5.

^ (1 Cor. 15:58) Therefore, my beloved brothers, be steadfast, immovable, always having plenty to do in the work of the Lord, knowing that your labor is not in vain* in connection with the Lord.

Lit., “empty.”

^ (Mark 13:4) “Tell us, when will these things be, and what will be the sign when all these things are to come to a conclusion?”

^ (Mark 13:8) “For nation will rise against nation and kingdom against kingdom; there will be earthquakes in one place after another; there will also be food shortages. These are a beginning of pangs of distress.

^ (Mark 13:10) Also, in all the nations, the good news has to be preached first.

^ (Matt. 24:14) And this good news of the Kingdom will be preached in all the inhabited earth for a witness to all the nations, and then the end will come.

^ (Ps. 145:11-13) They will proclaim the glory of your kingship And speak about your mightiness, 12 To make known to men your mighty acts And the glorious splendor of your kingship. 13 Your kingship is an eternal kingship, And your dominion endures throughout all generations.

Wednesday, July 21

This is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah says.—[Ezek. 2:4].

During the great tribulation, the message that we proclaim will likely change. Currently, we are preaching the good news of the Kingdom and we are endeavoring to make disciples. But at that time, we may well deliver a message as hard-hitting as hailstones. ([Rev. 16:21]) We may proclaim the impending doom of Satan’s world. In time, we will find out exactly what our message will be and how we will deliver it. Will we use the same methods or will we use some other methods? We will have to wait and see. In any case, it seems that we will have the privilege of boldly proclaiming Jehovah’s judgment message! ([Ezek. 2:3-5]) Quite likely, our message will provoke the nations into trying to silence us once and for all. Just as we rely on Jehovah for support in our ministry now, we will need his support then. We can be sure that our God will fill us with power to accomplish his will.—[Mic. 3:8]. w19.10 16 ¶8-9

^ (Ezek. 2:4) I am sending you to sons who are defiant* and hardhearted, and you must say to them, ‘This is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah says.’

Or “hard of face.”

^ (Rev. 16:21) Then great hailstones, each about the weight of a talent,* fell from heaven on the people, and the people blasphemed God because of the plague of hail, for the plague was unusually great.

A Greek talent equaled 20.4 kg (654 oz t). See App. B14.

^ (Ezek. 2:3-5) He went on to say to me: “Son of man, I am sending you to the people of Israel, to rebellious nations that have rebelled against me. They and their forefathers have transgressed against me down to this very day. 4 I am sending you to sons who are defiant* and hardhearted, and you must say to them, ‘This is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah says.’ 5 As for them, whether they listen or refuse to listen—for they are a rebellious house—they will certainly know that a prophet was among them.

Or “hard of face.”

^ (Mic. 3:8) As for me, I am filled with power by the spirit of Jehovah, And with justice and might, To tell to Jacob his revolt and to Israel his sin.

Friday, July 23

The plans of the diligent surely lead to success.—[Prov. 21:5].

God can give you “the power to act” and carry out a decision. ([Phil. 2:13]) So pray for the strength to act. Ask Jehovah for his holy spirit to give you the power you need. Continue praying even if an answer to your request seems to be delayed. As Jesus said: “Keep on asking, and it [holy spirit] will be given you.” ([Luke 11:9,][13]) Also, create a plan. To complete any project you start, you need a plan. Then you need to work according to that plan. Likewise, when you make a decision, list the specific steps you intend to follow to implement that decision. Breaking larger jobs into smaller tasks can help you track your progress more easily. The apostle Paul encouraged the Corinthians to set something aside for their contribution “on the first day of every week” rather than wait and try to collect funds when he arrived. ([1 Cor. 16:2]) Breaking large jobs into small tasks can also keep you from feeling overwhelmed. w19.11 29 ¶13-14

^ (Prov. 21:5) The plans of the diligent surely lead to success,* But all who are hasty surely head for poverty.

Or “advantage.”

^ (Phil. 2:13) For God is the one who for the sake of his good pleasure energizes you, giving you both the desire and the power to act.

^ (Luke 11:9) So I say to you, keep on asking, and it will be given you; keep on seeking, and you will find; keep on knocking, and it will be opened to you.

^ (Luke 11:13) Therefore, if you, although being wicked, know how to give good gifts to your children, how much more so will the Father in heaven give holy spirit to those asking him!”

^ (1 Cor. 16:2) On the first day of every week, each of you should set something aside according to his own means, so that collections will not take place when I arrive.

Saturday, July 24

Those knowing your name will trust in you; you will never abandon those seeking you, O Jehovah.—[Ps. 9:10].

We can say that a person knows about Jehovah if he is aware of God’s name or is familiar with some of the things that He has said or done. But to know Jehovah well involves more. We need to spend time learning about Jehovah and his wonderful qualities. Only then can we begin to understand what motivates him to speak and to act. That will help us to discern whether he approves of our opinions, decisions, and actions. Once we have discerned Jehovah’s will for us, we need to act on what we have learned. Some people may ridicule us for wanting to serve Jehovah, and they may oppose us even more when we start to associate with his people. Yet, if we trust in Jehovah, he will never let us down. We will be laying a foundation for friendship with God that will last a lifetime. Can we really know Jehovah that well? Yes, we can! w19.12 16-17 ¶3-4

^ (Ps. 9:10) Those knowing your name will trust in you; You will never abandon those seeking you, O Jehovah.

Friday, July 30

Jehovah turned his attention to Hannah.—[1 Sam. 2:21].

The cause of Hannah’s anxiety did not go away immediately. She still had to live in the same household as Peninnah did. And the Bible does not indicate that Peninnah’s attitude changed. So Hannah likely had to continue enduring her rival’s stabbing words. But Hannah was able to regain and maintain her inner peace. After leaving the matter in Jehovah’s hands, Hannah was no longer overwhelmed by worry. She allowed Jehovah to comfort and soothe her. Sometime later, Hannah was even blessed with children of her own! ([1 Sam. 1:2,][6, 7,][17-20]) We can regain our peace even if the cause of our anxiety remains. Even though we pray intensely and attend meetings regularly, some problems may persist. But from Hannah’s example, we learn that nothing can stop Jehovah from soothing our troubled heart. Jehovah will never forget us, and sooner or later he will reward our faithfulness.—[Heb. 11:6]. w20.02 22 ¶9-10

^ (1 Sam. 2:21) Jehovah turned his attention to Hanʹnah, so that she could conceive; and she gave birth to three more sons and two daughters. And the boy Samuel continued growing up before Jehovah.

^ (1 Sam. 1:2) He had two wives; one was named Hanʹnah, and the other was named Pe·ninʹnah. Pe·ninʹnah had children, but Hanʹnah had no children.

^ (1 Sam. 1:6, 7) Moreover, her rival wife taunted her relentlessly in order to upset her because Jehovah had not given her children. 7 That is what she would do year after year; whenever Hanʹnah went up to the house of Jehovah, her rival would taunt her so much that she would weep and not eat.

^ (1 Sam. 1:17-20) Then Eʹli answered: “Go in peace, and may the God of Israel grant your petition that you have asked of him.” 18 To this she said: “Let your servant find favor in your eyes.” And the woman went on her way and ate, and her face was no longer downcast. 19 Then they got up early in the morning and bowed before Jehovah, after which they returned to their house in Raʹmah. El·kaʹnah had sexual relations with his wife Hanʹnah, and Jehovah gave attention to* her. 20 Within a year* Hanʹnah became pregnant and gave birth to a son and named him Samuel,* because, as she said, “it is from Jehovah that I have asked him.”

Lit., “remembered.”

Or possibly, “In due time.”

Meaning “Name of God.”

^ (Heb. 11:6) Moreover, without faith it is impossible to please God well, for whoever approaches God must believe that he is* and that he becomes the rewarder of those earnestly seeking him.

Or “exists.”

Saturday, July 31

Share with a wise person, and he will become wiser.—[Prov. 9:9].

Elders do not hold back from sharing Bible principles that can help others to act wisely. Why is it so important that they speak up when necessary? Consider the case of Eli: High Priest Eli had two sons for whom he had deep affection. Those sons, however, had no respect for Jehovah. They held important positions as priests serving at the tabernacle. But they abused their authority, showed gross disrespect for the offerings given to Jehovah, and brazenly committed sexual immorality. (1 Sam. 2:12-17,[22]) According to the Mosaic Law, Eli’s sons deserved to die, but permissive Eli merely reproved them mildly and allowed them to continue serving at the tabernacle. (Deut. 21:18-21) How did Jehovah view the way that Eli handled matters? He said to Eli: “Why do you keep honoring your sons more than me?” Jehovah then determined to put those two wicked men to death.—[1 Sam. 2:29,][34]. w20.03 19 ¶4-5

^ (Prov. 9:9) Share with a wise person, and he will become wiser. Teach someone righteous, and he will add to his learning.

^ (1 Sam. 2:12-17) Now the sons of Eʹli were wicked men; they had no regard for Jehovah. 13 This is what they did with the due right of the priests from the people: Whenever any man was offering a sacrifice, an attendant of the priest came with a three-pronged fork in his hand when the meat was boiling, 14 and he would thrust it into the basin, the two-handled cooking pot, the cauldron, or the one-handled cooking pot. Whatever the fork brought up, the priest would take for himself. That is what they would do in Shiʹloh to all the Israelites coming there. 15 Also, even before the man sacrificing could make the fat smoke, an attendant of the priest would come and say to him: “Give the priest meat to roast. He will not take boiled meat from you, only raw meat.” 16 When the man would say to him: “Let them first be sure to make the fat smoke, then take for yourself whatever you desire,”* he would say: “No, give it to me now; if not, I will take it by force!” 17 Thus the sin of the attendants came to be very great before Jehovah, for the men treated the offering of Jehovah with disrespect.

Or “your soul craves.”

^ (1 Sam. 2:22) Now Eʹli was very old, but he had heard about everything that his sons were doing to all Israel and how they would lie down with the women who served at the entrance of the tent of meeting.

^ (Deut. 21:18-21) “If a man has a son who is stubborn and rebellious and he does not obey his father or his mother, and they have tried to correct him but he refuses to listen to them, 19 his father and his mother should take hold of him and bring him out to the elders at the gate of his city 20 and say to the elders of his city, ‘This son of ours is stubborn and rebellious, and he refuses to obey us. He is a glutton and a drunkard.’ 21 Then all the men of his city must stone him to death. So you must remove what is bad from your midst, and all Israel will hear and become afraid.

^ (1 Sam. 2:29) Why do you men scorn* my sacrifice and my offering that I have commanded in my place of dwelling? Why do you keep honoring your sons more than me by fattening yourselves from the best portions of every offering of my people Israel?

Lit., “kick at.”

^ (1 Sam. 2:34) And what happens to your two sons, Hophʹni and Phinʹe·has, will be the sign for you: On one day both of them will die.

August

Sunday, August 1

The One who sent me is with me; he did not abandon me.—[John 8:29].

Even while being persecuted, Jesus had inner peace because he knew that he was making his Father happy. He remained obedient when it was difficult for him to do so. He loved his Father and built his whole life around serving Jehovah. Before he came to earth, he was God’s “master worker.” ([Prov. 8:30]) And while on earth, he zealously taught others about his Father. ([Matt. 6:9;][John 5:17]) That work brought Jesus great joy. ([John 4:34-36]) We can imitate Jesus by obeying Jehovah and “always having plenty to do in the work of the Lord.” ([1 Cor. 15:58]) When we are “intensely occupied” in the preaching work, we are better able to put our troubles into perspective. ([Acts 18:5]) For example, those we meet in our ministry often face worse problems than we do. Yet, when they learn to love Jehovah and apply his counsel, their lives improve and they become happier. Each time we see that happen, we feel more confident that Jehovah will care for us. w19.04 10-11 ¶8-9

^ (John 8:29) And the One who sent me is with me; he did not abandon me to myself, because I always do the things pleasing to him.”

^ (Prov. 8:30) Then I was beside him as a master worker. I was the one he was especially fond of day by day; I rejoiced before him all the time;

^ (Matt. 6:9) “You must pray, then, this way: “‘Our Father in the heavens, let your name be sanctified.

^ (John 5:17) But he answered them: “My Father has kept working until now, and I keep working.”

^ (John 4:34-36) Jesus said to them: “My food is to do the will of him who sent me and to finish his work. 35 Do you not say that there are yet four months before the harvest comes? Look! I say to you: Lift up your eyes and view the fields, that they are white for harvesting. Already 36 the reaper is receiving wages and gathering fruit for everlasting life, so that the sower and the reaper may rejoice together.

^ (1 Cor. 15:58) Therefore, my beloved brothers, be steadfast, immovable, always having plenty to do in the work of the Lord, knowing that your labor is not in vain* in connection with the Lord.

Lit., “empty.”

^ (Acts 18:5) When, now, both Silas and Timothy came down from Mac·e·doʹni·a, Paul began to be intensely occupied with the word, witnessing to the Jews to prove that Jesus is the Christ.

Thursday, August 5

Men will be lovers of themselves.—[2 Tim. 3:2].

The world has encouraged an inflated view of self. One reference work says that during the 1970’s “self-help books proliferated.” Some books “urged readers to know and accept themselves and to celebrate who they were.” Consider, for example, the statement made in one such book: “Be in love with the most beautiful, exciting, worthy person ever—you.” The book advocates a “religion of the self in which an individual determines his own behavior based upon his own conscience and the laws of his culture that work for him.” Does that idea sound familiar to you? Satan encouraged Eve to do something similar. He said that she could “be like God, knowing good and bad.” ([Gen. 3:5]) Today, many think so highly of themselves that in their opinion no one—not even God—can tell them what is right and what is wrong. For example, that attitude has become especially evident in the way people view marriage. w19.05 23 ¶10-11

^ (2 Tim. 3:2) For men will be lovers of themselves, lovers of money, boastful, haughty, blasphemers, disobedient to parents, unthankful, disloyal,

^ (Gen. 3:5) For God knows that in the very day you eat from it, your eyes will be opened and you will be like God, knowing good and bad.”

Friday, August 6

I am distressed and extremely downcast; I walk around sad all day long.—[Ps. 38:6].

At times, King David was overwhelmed by stress. Think of the challenges he faced. He was weighed down with guilt for the many mistakes he had made. ([Ps. 40:12]) His beloved son Absalom rebelled against him, leading to Absalom’s death. (2 Sam. 15:13, 14;[18:33]) And one of David’s closest friends betrayed him. (2 Sam. 16:23–17:2; Ps. 55:12-14) Many of the psalms David wrote convey his feelings of discouragement as well as his unshakable trust in Jehovah. ([Ps. 38:5-10;][94:17-19]) Later a psalmist began to envy the lifestyle of wicked people. He may have been a descendant of the Levite Asaph, and he served at “the grand sanctuary of God.” This psalmist suffered emotional stress, causing him to become unhappy and discontented. He even started to doubt the blessings that come from serving God.—[Ps. 73:2-5,][7,][12-14,][16, 17,][21]. w19.06 17 ¶12-13

^ (Ps. 38:6) I am distressed and extremely downcast; I walk around sad all day long.

^ (Ps. 40:12) The calamities surrounding me are too many to count. So many of my errors overwhelm me that I cannot see my way; They are more numerous than the hairs of my head, And I have lost heart.

^ (2 Sam. 15:13, 14) In time an informer came to David, saying: “The heart of the men of Israel has turned to Abʹsa·lom.” 14 At once David said to all his servants with him in Jerusalem: “Get up, and let us run away, for none of us will escape from Abʹsa·lom! Hurry, for fear he may quickly overtake us and bring disaster on us and strike the city with the sword!”

^ (2 Sam. 18:33) This disturbed the king, and he went up to the roof chamber over the gateway and wept, saying as he walked: “My son Abʹsa·lom, my son, my son Abʹsa·lom! If only I had died instead of you, Abʹsa·lom my son, my son!”

^ (2 Sam. 16:23-17:2) In those days the advice that A·hithʹo·phel gave was considered as* the word of the true God. That was how all the advice of A·hithʹo·phel was esteemed, both by David and by Abʹsa·lom.

17 A·hithʹo·phel then said to Abʹsa·lom: “Please let me choose 12,000 men and rise up and chase after David tonight. 2 I will come upon him when he is weary and powerless,* and I will throw him into a panic; and all the people who are with him will flee, and I will strike down only the king.

Or “was as if someone were inquiring of.”

Or “feeble in both hands.”

^ (Ps. 55:12-14) For it is not an enemy who taunts me; Otherwise I could put up with it. It is not a foe who has risen up against me; Otherwise I could conceal myself from him. 13 But it is you, a man like me,* My own companion whom I know well. 14 We used to enjoy a warm friendship together; Into the house of God we used to walk along with the multitude.

Or “a man, my equal.”

^ (Ps. 38:5-10) My wounds stink and fester Because of my foolishness.  6 I am distressed and extremely downcast; I walk around sad all day long.  7 There is a burning within me;* My whole body is sick.  8 I have grown numb and become completely crushed; My anguished heart makes me groan aloud.*  9 O Jehovah, all my desires are before you, And my sighing is not hidden from you. 10 My heart pounds, my strength is gone, And the light of my eyes has left me.

Lit., “My loins are full of burning.”

Or “roar.”

^ (Ps. 94:17-19) If Jehovah had not been my helper, I* would soon have perished.* 18 When I said: “My foot is slipping,” Your loyal love, O Jehovah, kept supporting me. 19 When anxieties* overwhelmed me,* You comforted and soothed me.*

Or “My soul.”

Lit., “resided in silence.”

Or “disquieting thoughts.”

Or “became many inside of me.”

Or “Your consolations soothed my soul.”

^ (Ps. 73:2-5) As for me, my feet had almost strayed; My steps had nearly slipped.  3 For I became envious of the arrogant* When I would see the peace of the wicked.  4 For they have no pain in their death; Their bodies are healthy.*  5 They are not troubled like other humans, Nor do they suffer like other men.

Or “boasters.”

Or “Their paunch is fat.”

^ (Ps. 73:7) Their prosperity* makes their eyes bulge; They have exceeded the imaginations of the heart.

Lit., “fat.”

^ (Ps. 73:12-14) Yes, these are the wicked, who always have it easy. They keep increasing their wealth. 13 Surely in vain I have kept my heart pure And washed my hands in innocence. 14 And I was troubled all day long; Every morning I was chastised.

^ (Ps. 73:16, 17) When I tried to understand it, It was troubling to me 17 Until I entered the grand sanctuary of God, And I discerned their future.

^ (Ps. 73:21) But my heart was sour, And deep inside* I felt sharp pain.

Lit., “in my kidneys.”

Saturday, August 7

We are not ignorant of [Satan’s] designs.—[2 Cor. 2:11].

Satan appeals to natural desires. We have a natural desire to learn skills that can help us provide for ourselves and our families. ([1 Tim. 5:8]) Often, we can gain those skills by attending school and being diligent students. But we must be cautious. The educational system in many countries teaches students not only practical skills but also human philosophy. Students are encouraged to question the existence of God and to disregard the Bible. They are told that the theory of evolution is the only intelligent explanation for the origin of life. ([Rom. 1:21-23]) Such teachings are opposed to “the wisdom of God.” (1 Cor. 1:19-21;[3:18-20]) Be determined never to be taken captive “by means of the philosophy and empty deception” of Satan’s world. ([Col. 2:8]) Continually guard against Satan’s tactics. ([1 Cor. 3:18]) Never allow him to blur your view of Jehovah. Live by Jehovah’s high moral standards. And do not let Satan trick you into ignoring Jehovah’s advice. w19.06 5 ¶13; 7 ¶17

^ (2 Cor. 2:11) so that we may not be overreached by Satan, for we are not ignorant of his designs.

^ (1 Tim. 5:8) Certainly if anyone does not provide for those who are his own, and especially for those who are members of his household, he has disowned the faith and is worse than a person without faith.

^ (Rom. 1:21-23) For although they knew God, they did not glorify him as God nor did they thank him, but they became empty-headed in their reasonings and their senseless hearts became darkened. 22 Although claiming they were wise, they became foolish 23 and turned the glory of the incorruptible God into something like the image of corruptible man and birds and four-footed creatures and reptiles.*

Or “creeping things.”

^ (1 Cor. 1:19-21) For it is written: “I will make the wisdom of the wise men perish, and the intelligence of the intellectuals I will reject.”* 20 Where is the wise man? Where is the scribe? Where is the debater of this system of things? Has not God made the wisdom of the world foolish? 21 For since, in the wisdom of God, the world did not get to know God through its wisdom, God was pleased through the foolishness of what is preached to save those believing.

Or “shove aside.”

^ (1 Cor. 3:18-20) Let no one deceive himself: If anyone among you thinks he is wise in this system of things, let him become a fool, so that he may become wise. 19 For the wisdom of this world is foolishness with God, for it is written: “He catches the wise in their own cunning.” 20 And again: “Jehovah knows that the reasonings of the wise men are futile.”

^ (Col. 2:8) Look out that no one takes you captive* by means of the philosophy and empty deception according to human tradition, according to the elementary things of the world and not according to Christ;

Or “carries you off as his prey.”

^ (1 Cor. 3:18) Let no one deceive himself: If anyone among you thinks he is wise in this system of things, let him become a fool, so that he may become wise.

Sunday, August 8

[Teach] them to observe all the things I have commanded you.—[Matt. 28:20].

Whatever subject you choose to discuss, think about the people who will hear you. Imagine how they will benefit from learning what the Bible really teaches. When talking with them, it is important that you listen to them and respect their viewpoint. That way you will understand them better, and they will be more likely to listen to you. Before a person decides to study the Bible, you may need to invest time and effort in making return visits. Why? Because people may not be available when we call on them again. Also, you may need to return several times before the householder feels comfortable enough with you to accept a Bible study. Remember, a plant is more likely to grow when it is watered regularly. Similarly, an interested person’s love for Jehovah and Christ is more likely to grow when we regularly discuss God’s Word with that person. w19.07 14 ¶1; 15-16 ¶7-8

^ (Matt. 28:20) teaching them to observe all the things I have commanded you. And look! I am with you all the days until the conclusion of the system of things.”

Thursday, August 12

Make sure of the more important things, so that you may be flawless and not stumbling others.—[Phil. 1:10].

How could we stumble someone? Consider this scenario. A Bible student is finally able to control his addiction to alcohol. He realizes that he must abstain from it completely, makes progress, and gets baptized. Later, a well-meaning host of a Christian gathering urges the new brother to accept an alcoholic beverage, saying: “If you exercise self-control, you should be able to make moderate use of alcohol.” We can only imagine what the consequences would be if the new brother were to listen to that misguided advice! Our Christian meetings help us to apply the instructions given in today’s text. They remind us of what Jehovah considers to be more important and how to apply what we learn so that we may be flawless. They also encourage us to love God and our brothers. When these two great loves fill our heart, we will do our very best to avoid stumbling our brothers. w19.08 10 ¶9; 11 ¶13-14

^ (Phil. 1:10) that you may make sure of the more important things, so that you may be flawless and not stumbling others up to the day of Christ;

Saturday, August 14

Should we not more readily submit ourselves to the Father?—[Heb. 12:9].

One reason why we might find it a challenge to submit to Jehovah is that we all inherited sin and are imperfect. So we have rebellious tendencies. After Adam and Eve rebelled against God and ate the forbidden fruit, they set their own standards. ([Gen. 3:22]) Today, most of mankind still prefer to ignore Jehovah and decide for themselves what is right and what is wrong. Even those who know and love Jehovah may struggle to submit fully to him. The apostle Paul faced this challenge. ([Rom. 7:21-23]) Like Paul, we want to do what is right in Jehovah’s eyes. But we must constantly fight the tendency to do wrong things. Another reason why it can be a challenge to submit to Jehovah is that we are influenced by the culture in which we were raised. Many human ideas are in conflict with Jehovah’s will, and it can be a constant struggle to free ourselves from common ways of thinking. w19.09 15 ¶4-6

^ (Heb. 12:9) Furthermore, our human fathers* used to discipline us, and we gave them respect. Should we not more readily submit ourselves to the Father of our spiritual life and live?

Lit., “the fathers of our flesh.”

^ (Gen. 3:22) Jehovah God then said: “Here the man has become like one of us in knowing good and bad. Now in order that he may not put his hand out and take fruit also from the tree of life and eat and live forever,*—”

Or “to time indefinite.”

^ (Rom. 7:21-23) I find, then, this law in my case: When I wish to do what is right, what is bad is present with me. 22 I really delight in the law of God according to the man I am within, 23 but I see in my body another law warring against the law of my mind and leading me captive to sin’s law that is in my body.

Monday, August 16

In all the nations, the good news has to be preached first.—[Mark 13:10].

Our Kingdom-preaching work will not be finished until Jehovah says it is over. How much time is left for people to come to know Jehovah God and Jesus Christ? ([John 17:3]) We cannot say. We do know that until the great tribulation begins, any who are “rightly disposed for everlasting life” can still respond to the good news. ([Acts 13:48]) How can we help these people before it is too late? Through his organization, Jehovah is giving us all that we need to teach people the truth. For example, we receive training each week at the midweek meeting. This meeting helps us know what to say on initial calls and return visits. And if after a refreshing conversation with an interested person, you leave him a tract or magazine, he will be able to do further reading until you are able to contact him again. It is our personal responsibility to keep busy every month in the Kingdom-preaching work. w19.10 9 ¶7; 10 ¶9-10

^ (Mark 13:10) Also, in all the nations, the good news has to be preached first.

^ (John 17:3) This means everlasting life, their coming to know you, the only true God, and the one whom you sent, Jesus Christ.

^ (Acts 13:48) When those of the nations heard this, they began to rejoice and to glorify the word of Jehovah, and all those who were rightly disposed for everlasting life became believers.

Tuesday, August 17

Do not forget to do good and to share what you have with others, for God is well-pleased with such sacrifices.—[Heb. 13:16].

Jehovah promised Simeon, a loyal older man in Jerusalem, that he would not see death before he laid eyes on the Messiah. That promise must have encouraged Simeon greatly, since he had been waiting many years for the Messiah. His faith and endurance were rewarded. One day, “under the power of the spirit,” he came into the temple. There he saw the infant Jesus, and Jehovah used Simeon to deliver a prophecy about this child who would become the Christ. (Luke 2:25-35) Although Simeon likely did not live long enough to see Jesus carry out his earthly ministry, Simeon was grateful for the privilege he had, and the best is yet to come for him! In the new world, that faithful man will see how Jesus’ rulership will be a blessing to all the families of the earth. ([Gen. 22:18]) We too can be grateful for any privilege Jehovah gives us in his service. w19.10 22 ¶7; 23 ¶12

^ (Heb. 13:16) Moreover, do not forget to do good and to share what you have with others, for God is well-pleased with such sacrifices.

^ (Gen. 22:18) And by means of your offspring* all nations of the earth will obtain a blessing for themselves because you have listened to my voice.’”

Lit., “seed.”

Thursday, August 19

As iron sharpens iron, so one man sharpens his friend.—[Prov. 27:17].

When we work alongside fellow believers and observe firsthand their endearing qualities, we learn from them and draw closer to them. For example, how do you feel when you are in the ministry and you hear your friend boldly defend his faith or speak with heartfelt conviction about Jehovah and his purposes? Likely you feel drawn to him even more. Adeline, a 23-year-old sister, asked one of her friends, Candice, to go with her to preach in seldom-worked territory. “We wanted to be more motivated and to enjoy the ministry more,” she says. “We both needed a spiritual boost.” How did they benefit from working together? “At the end of each day,” says Adeline, “we discussed how we felt, what touched us about the conversations we had, and how we sensed Jehovah’s direction in our ministry. We both enjoyed these deep discussions and got to know each other even better.” w19.11 5 ¶10-11

^ (Prov. 27:17) As iron sharpens iron, So one man sharpens his friend.*

Lit., “the face of his friend.”

Friday, August 20

Take up the large shield of faith.—[Eph. 6:16].

In ancient times, a soldier would feel humiliated if he returned home without his shield. The Roman historian Tacitus wrote: “To have abandoned one’s shield is the height of disgrace.” That is one reason why soldiers made sure to keep a firm hold on their shields. We keep a firm hold on our shield of faith by regularly attending Christian meetings and by speaking about Jehovah’s name and his Kingdom to others. (Heb. 10:23-25) In addition, we prayerfully read God’s Word every day and apply its counsel and direction in all that we do. (2 Tim. 3:16, 17) Then, no weapon that Satan uses against us will cause us any lasting harm. ([Isa. 54:17]) Our “large shield of faith” will protect us. We will stand firm, shoulder to shoulder with our brothers and sisters. And we will do more than win our daily battles—we will have the honor of being on Jesus’ side when he wins the war against Satan and his followers.—[Rev. 17:14;][20:10]. w19.11 19 ¶18-19

^ (Eph. 6:16) Besides all of this, take up the large shield of faith, with which you will be able to extinguish all the wicked one’s burning arrows.*

Or “missiles; darts.”

^ (Heb. 10:23-25) Let us hold firmly the public declaration of our hope without wavering, for the one who promised is faithful. 24 And let us consider* one another so as to incite* to love and fine works, 25 not forsaking our meeting together, as some have the custom, but encouraging one another, and all the more so as you see the day drawing near.

Or “be concerned about; pay attention to.”

Or “motivate; stir up.”

^ (2 Tim. 3:16, 17) All Scripture is inspired of God and beneficial for teaching, for reproving, for setting things straight,* for disciplining in righteousness, 17 so that the man of God may be fully competent, completely equipped for every good work.

Or “correcting.”

^ (Isa. 54:17) No weapon formed against you will have any success, And you will condemn any tongue that rises up against you in the judgment. This is the heritage* of the servants of Jehovah, And their righteousness is from me,” declares Jehovah.

Or “inheritance.”

^ (Rev. 17:14) These will battle with the Lamb, but because he is Lord of lords and King of kings, the Lamb will conquer them. Also, those with him who are called and chosen and faithful will do so.”

^ (Rev. 20:10) And the Devil who was misleading them was hurled into the lake of fire and sulfur, where both the wild beast and the false prophet already were; and they will be tormented* day and night forever and ever.

Or “restrained; imprisoned.”

Saturday, August 21

The way I am aiming my blows is so as not to be striking the air.—[1 Cor. 9:26].

A clear plan that you put in writing can help you turn your decisions into action. ([1 Cor. 14:40]) For instance, bodies of elders are directed to assign an elder to record each decision of the body of elders, including who is assigned to follow through and the suggested date for completion. Elders who follow this direction are more likely to carry out their decisions. You could try to do something similar with your personal affairs. For example, you could prepare a daily to-do list and arrange the items in the order you intend to handle them. This can help you not only to complete what you start but also to get more done in less time. But you will need to exert yourself. It takes effort to follow your plan and complete what you start. ([Rom. 12:11]) The apostle Paul told Timothy to “continue applying” himself and to “persevere” in becoming a better teacher. That advice applies equally to other spiritual goals.—[1 Tim. 4:13,][16]. w19.11 29-30 ¶15-16

^ (1 Cor. 9:26) Therefore, the way I am running is not aimlessly; the way I am aiming my blows is so as not to be striking the air;

^ (1 Cor. 14:40) But let all things take place decently and by arrangement.

^ (Rom. 12:11) Be industrious, not lazy.* Be aglow with the spirit. Slave for Jehovah.

Or “Do not loiter at your business.”

^ (1 Tim. 4:13) Until I come, continue applying yourself to public reading, to exhortation,* to teaching.

Or “encouragement.”

^ (1 Tim. 4:16) Pay constant attention to yourself and to your teaching. Persevere in these things, for by doing this you will save both yourself and those who listen to you.

Wednesday, August 25

You must not prophesy in the name of Jehovah, or you will die by our hand.—[Jer. 11:21].

For at least 40 years, Jeremiah lived among disloyal people, including neighbors and possibly some relatives from his hometown of Anathoth. ([Jer. 12:6]) However, he did not isolate himself. In fact, he expressed his feelings to his loyal secretary Baruch and ultimately to us. ([Jer. 8:21;][9:1;][20:14-18;][45:1]) We can well imagine that as Baruch wrote down Jeremiah’s eventful story, the two developed deep affection and respect for each other. (Jer. 20:1, 2;[26:7-11]) For many years, Jeremiah had boldly warned the Israelites about what was going to happen to Jerusalem. ([Jer. 25:3]) In a further attempt to move the people to repentance, Jehovah asked Jeremiah to write His warnings on a scroll. ([Jer. 36:1-4]) As Jeremiah and Baruch worked closely together on this God-given task, which probably lasted several months, they no doubt had faith-strengthening conversations. w19.11 2-3 ¶3-4

^ (Jer. 11:21) Therefore this is what Jehovah says against the men of Anʹa·thoth who are seeking to take your life* and who say: “You must not prophesy in the name of Jehovah, or you will die by our hand”;

Or “seeking your soul.”

^ (Jer. 12:6) For even your own brothers, the household of your own father, Have dealt treacherously with you. They have raised a loud cry against you. Do not put faith in them, Even if they speak good things to you.

^ (Jer. 8:21) I am shattered over the breakdown of the daughter of my people; I am dejected. Horror has seized me.

^ (Jer. 9:1) O that my head were waters, My eyes a fountain of tears! Then I would weep day and night For the slain ones of my people.

^ (Jer. 20:14-18) Cursed be the day I was born! May the day my mother gave birth to me not be blessed! 15 Cursed be the man who brought good news to my father, saying: “A son has been born to you, a boy!” Making him rejoice greatly. 16 May that man become like cities that Jehovah overthrew without regret. May he hear an outcry in the morning and the sound of alarm at midday. 17 Why did he not put me to death in the womb, So that my mother would become my burial place And her womb would always remain pregnant? 18 Why did I have to come out of the womb To see trouble and grief, To end my days in shame?

^ (Jer. 45:1) This is the word that Jeremiah the prophet spoke to Barʹuch the son of Ne·riʹah when he wrote in a book these words dictated by Jeremiah in the fourth year of Je·hoiʹa·kim son of Jo·siʹah, the king of Judah:

^ (Jer. 20:1, 2) Now Pashʹhur the son of Imʹmer, the priest, who was also the leading commissioner in the house of Jehovah, was listening when Jeremiah prophesied these things. 2 Then Pashʹhur struck Jeremiah the prophet and put him in the stocks that were at the Upper Gate of Benjamin, which was in the house of Jehovah.

^ (Jer. 26:7-11) And the priests and the prophets and all the people heard Jeremiah speaking these words in the house of Jehovah. 8 So when Jeremiah had finished speaking all that Jehovah had commanded him to speak to all the people, then the priests and the prophets and all the people seized him and said: “You will surely die. 9 Why have you prophesied in the name of Jehovah, saying, ‘This house will become like Shiʹloh, and this city will be devastated and left without an inhabitant’?” And all the people gathered around Jeremiah in the house of Jehovah. 10 When the princes of Judah heard these words, they came up from the house* of the king to the house of Jehovah and sat down at the entrance of the new gate of Jehovah. 11 The priests and the prophets said to the princes and to all the people: “This man deserves the death penalty, because he has prophesied against this city just as you have heard with your own ears.”

Or “palace.”

^ (Jer. 25:3) “From the 13th year of Jo·siʹah son of Aʹmon, the king of Judah, to this day, these 23 years, the word of Jehovah has come to me, and I kept speaking to you again and again,* but you would not listen.

Lit., “rising up early and speaking.”

^ (Jer. 36:1-4) Now in the fourth year of Je·hoiʹa·kim son of Jo·siʹah, the king of Judah, this word came to Jeremiah from Jehovah, saying: 2 “Take a scroll* and write in it all the words that I have spoken to you against Israel and Judah and all the nations, from the first day I spoke to you in the days of Jo·siʹah to this day. 3 Perhaps when those of the house of Judah hear of all the calamity that I intend to bring on them, they may turn back from their evil ways, so that I may forgive their error and their sin.” 4 Jeremiah then called Barʹuch the son of Ne·riʹah, and Jeremiah dictated all the words that Jehovah had spoken to him, and Barʹuch wrote them in the scroll.*

Lit., “a scroll of a book.”

Lit., “the scroll of the book.”

Saturday, August 28

Children, be obedient to your parents.—[Eph. 6:1].

Jehovah also expects us to obey him. He deserves our obedience because he is our Creator, the Sustainer of our life, and the wisest of all parents. However, the primary reason why we obey Jehovah is that we love him. ([1 John 5:3]) Although there are many reasons why we should obey Jehovah, he does not force us to do so. Jehovah gave us the gift of free will, so he is happy when we choose to obey him out of love for him. Parents want their children to be safe. That is why they establish standards of behavior. When children obey those guidelines, they show that they put trust in their parents and respect them. How much more important it is, then, that we know our heavenly Father’s standards and live by them. When we do, we show Jehovah that we love and respect him and we also benefit ourselves. (Isa. 48:17, 18) By contrast, those who reject Jehovah and his standards end up hurting themselves.—[Gal. 6:7, 8]. w20.02 9-10 ¶8-9

^ (Eph. 6:1) Children, be obedient to your parents in union with the Lord, for this is righteous.

^ (1 John 5:3) For this is what the love of God means, that we observe his commandments; and yet his commandments are not burdensome,

^ (Isa. 48:17, 18) This is what Jehovah says, your Repurchaser, the Holy One of Israel: “I, Jehovah, am your God, The One teaching you to benefit yourself,* The One guiding you in the way you should walk. 18 If only you would pay attention to my commandments! Then your peace would become just like a river And your righteousness like the waves of the sea.

Or “for your own good.”

^ (Gal. 6:7, 8) Do not be misled: God is not one to be mocked. For whatever a person is sowing, this he will also reap; 8 because the one sowing with a view to his flesh will reap corruption from his flesh, but the one sowing with a view to the spirit will reap everlasting life from the spirit.

Tuesday, August 31

I have called you friends.—[John 15:15].

Good friends will help us to stay loyal to Jehovah. And the best way to make good friends is to be a good friend. ([Matt. 7:12]) For example, the Bible encourages us to expend ourselves in behalf of others, especially those who are “in need.” ([Eph. 4:28]) When we are absorbed in helping others, we are more likely to be happy. ([Acts 20:35]) The friends we make will support us when we face trials, helping us to maintain our inner peace. Just as Elihu listened when Job spoke about his trials, our friends help us by patiently listening as we put our concerns into words. ([Job 32:4]) We should not expect our friends to make decisions for us, but we are wise if we listen to their Bible-based advice. ([Prov. 15:22]) And just as King David humbly accepted the help of his friends, we should not be too proud to accept the help our friends offer when we are in need. (2 Sam. 17:27-29) Really, such good friends are a gift from Jehovah.—[Jas. 1:17]. w19.04 11 ¶12; 12 ¶14-15

^ (John 15:15) I no longer call you slaves, because a slave does not know what his master does. But I have called you friends, because I have made known to you all the things I have heard from my Father.

^ (Matt. 7:12) “All things, therefore, that you want men to do to you, you also must do to them. This, in fact, is what the Law and the Prophets mean.

^ (Eph. 4:28) Let the one who steals steal no more; rather, let him do hard work, doing good work with his hands, so that he may have something to share with someone in need.

^ (Acts 20:35) I have shown you in all things that by working hard in this way, you must assist those who are weak and must keep in mind the words of the Lord Jesus, when he himself said: ‘There is more happiness in giving than there is in receiving.’”

^ (Job 32:4) E·liʹhu had been waiting to respond to Job, because they were older than he was.

^ (Prov. 15:22) Plans fail when there is no consultation,* But there is accomplishment through many advisers.*

Or “confidential talk.”

Or “counselors.”

^ (2 Sam. 17:27-29) As soon as David came to Ma·ha·naʹim, Shoʹbi the son of Naʹhash from Rabʹbah of the Amʹmon·ites, Maʹchir the son of Amʹmi·el from Lo-deʹbar, and Bar·zilʹlai the Gilʹe·ad·ite from Ro·geʹlim 28 brought beds, basins, clay pots, wheat, barley, flour, roasted grain, broad beans, lentils, parched grain, 29 honey, butter, sheep, and cheese.* They brought all of this out for David and the people with him to eat, for they said: “The people are hungry and tired and thirsty in the wilderness.”

Lit., “curds of cattle.”

^ (Jas. 1:17) Every good gift and every perfect present is from above, coming down from the Father of the celestial lights, who does not vary or change like the shifting shadows.*

Or “with whom there is not a variation of the turning of the shadow.”

September

Wednesday, September 1

My Father has kept working until now, and I keep working.—[John 5:17].

Do the examples set by Jehovah and Jesus in working hard imply that it is not necessary for us to rest? Not at all. Jehovah never gets tired, so he does not need physical rest. The Bible does say that after Jehovah created the heavens and the earth, “he rested and refreshed himself.” ([Ex. 31:17]) However, that evidently means that Jehovah paused and found satisfaction in what he had made. And although Jesus worked hard while he lived on earth, he still made time to rest and to enjoy meals with his friends. ([Matt. 14:13;][Luke 7:34]) The Bible encourages God’s people to be workers. His servants are to be industrious rather than lazy. ([Prov. 15:19]) Perhaps you work secularly to care for your family. And all disciples of Christ have the responsibility to share in the work of preaching the good news. Still, you also need to get sufficient rest. w19.12 2 ¶2; 3 ¶4-5

^ (John 5:17) But he answered them: “My Father has kept working until now, and I keep working.”

^ (Ex. 31:17) It is an enduring sign between me and the people of Israel, for in six days Jehovah made the heavens and the earth and on the seventh day he rested and refreshed himself.’”

^ (Matt. 14:13) At hearing this, Jesus departed from there by boat into an isolated place to be alone. But the crowds, getting to hear of it, followed him on foot from the cities.

^ (Luke 7:34) The Son of man has come eating and drinking, but you say: ‘Look! A man who is a glutton and is given to drinking wine, a friend of tax collectors and sinners!’

^ (Prov. 15:19) The way of the lazy one is like a hedge of thorns, But the path of the upright is like a level highway.

Thursday, September 2

Christ suffered for you, leaving a model for you to follow his steps closely.—[1 Pet. 2:21].

Avoid telling stories about the demons. In this regard, we want to imitate the example set by Jesus. Before he came to earth, Jesus lived in heaven, and he knew a lot about Satan and the demons. But he did not relate stories about what those wicked spirits had done. Jesus wanted to be a witness of Jehovah, not a publicity agent for Satan. We can imitate Jesus by not spreading stories about the demons. Instead, we show by our words that our “heart is stirred by something good,” that is, the truth. ([Ps. 45:1]) Do not be terrified of wicked spirits. In this imperfect world, bad things may happen to us. Accidents, sickness, or even death may come without warning. But we should not think that invisible spirits are responsible. The Bible explains that “time and unexpected events” can overtake anyone. ([Eccl. 9:11]) As for the demons, Jehovah has shown that he is far more powerful than they are. w19.04 23-24 ¶13-14

^ (1 Pet. 2:21) In fact, to this course you were called, because even Christ suffered for you, leaving a model for you to follow his steps closely.

^ (Ps. 45:1) My heart is stirred by something good. I say: “My song is* about a king.” May my tongue be the stylus* of a skilled copyist.*

Lit., “My works are.”

Or “pen.”

Or “scribe.”

^ (Eccl. 9:11) I have seen something further under the sun, that the swift do not always win the race, nor do the mighty win the battle, nor do the wise always have the food, nor do the intelligent always have the riches, nor do those with knowledge always have success, because time and unexpected events* overtake them all.

Or “unforeseen occurrence.”

Friday, September 3

The existing authorities stand placed in their relative positions by God.—[Rom. 13:1].

Do elders comply with secular laws about reporting an allegation of child abuse to the secular authorities? Yes. In places where such laws exist, elders endeavor to comply with secular laws about reporting allegations of abuse. Such laws do not conflict with God’s law. (Acts 5:28, 29) So when they learn of an allegation, elders immediately seek direction on how they can comply with laws about reporting it. Elders assure victims and their parents and others with knowledge of the matter that they are free to report an allegation of abuse to the secular authorities. But what if the report is about someone who is a part of the congregation and the matter then becomes known in the community? Should the Christian who reported it feel that he has brought reproach on God’s name? No. The abuser is the one who brings reproach on God’s name. w19.05 10 ¶13-14

^ (Rom. 13:1) Let every person be in subjection to the superior authorities, for there is no authority except by God; the existing authorities stand placed in their relative positions by God.

^ (Acts 5:28, 29) and said: “We strictly ordered you not to keep teaching on the basis of this name, and yet look! you have filled Jerusalem with your teaching, and you are determined to bring the blood of this man upon us.” 29 In answer Peter and the other apostles said: “We must obey God as ruler rather than men.

Sunday, September 5

Stop being molded by this system of things.—[Rom. 12:2].

Paul was concerned because some Christians were apparently being influenced by the unwholesome reasonings and philosophies promoted by Satan’s world. ([Eph. 4:17-19]) That can happen to any one of us. In a desperate attempt to turn us away from Jehovah, Satan, the god of this system of things, uses various tactics. One of them is that of exploiting any tendency we may have toward selfish ambition or self-promotion. He may even use certain aspects of our background, our culture, or our education to bring us over to his way of thinking. Is it possible for us to root out things that are “strongly entrenched” in our minds? ([2 Cor. 10:4]) Notice how Paul answers: “We are overturning reasonings and every lofty thing raised up against the knowledge of God, and we are bringing every thought into captivity to make it obedient to the Christ.” ([2 Cor. 10:5]) Yes, with Jehovah’s help we can actually gain control over wrong reasonings. w19.06 8 ¶1-3

^ (Rom. 12:2) And stop being molded by this system of things, but be transformed by making your mind over, so that you may prove to yourselves the good and acceptable and perfect will of God.

^ (Eph. 4:17-19) So this is what I say and bear witness to in the Lord, that you should no longer go on walking just as the nations also walk, in the futility* of their minds. 18 They are in darkness mentally and alienated from the life that belongs to God, because of the ignorance that is in them, because of the insensitivity* of their hearts. 19 Having gone past all moral sense, they gave themselves over to brazen conduct* to practice every sort of uncleanness with greediness.

Or “emptiness; vanity.”

Lit., “dulling.”

Or “shameless conduct.” Greek, a·selʹgei·a. See Glossary.

^ (2 Cor. 10:4) For the weapons of our warfare are not fleshly, but powerful by God for overturning strongly entrenched things.

^ (2 Cor. 10:5) For we are overturning reasonings and every lofty thing raised up against the knowledge of God, and we are bringing every thought into captivity to make it obedient to the Christ;

Monday, September 6

As for me, drawing near to God is good for me. I have made the Sovereign Lord Jehovah my refuge.—[Ps. 73:28].

Although deeply distressed, Hannah, David, and a psalmist all relied on Jehovah for help. They shared their anxiety with him through fervent prayer. They spoke freely to him about the reasons why they were so stressed. And they continued to go to Jehovah’s place of worship. (1 Sam. 1:9, 10;[Ps. 55:22;][73:17;][122:1]) Jehovah compassionately responded to each one of them. Hannah gained peace of mind. ([1 Sam. 1:18]) David wrote: “Many are the hardships of the righteous one, but Jehovah rescues him from them all.” ([Ps. 34:19]) And the psalmist later felt that Jehovah had “taken hold of [his] right hand,” guiding him with loving advice. (Ps. 73:23, 24) What do we learn from these examples? At times, we will be burdened with problems that cause us stress. But we can cope if we meditate on how Jehovah has helped others, rely on him in prayer, and obey him by doing what he asks us to do.—[Ps. 143:1,][4-8]. w19.06 17 ¶14-15

^ (Ps. 73:28) But as for me, drawing near to God is good for me. I have made the Sovereign Lord Jehovah my refuge, To declare all your works.

^ (1 Sam. 1:9, 10) Then Hanʹnah got up after they had finished eating and drinking in Shiʹloh. At the time, Eʹli the priest was sitting on the seat by the doorpost of the temple* of Jehovah. 10 Hanʹnah was extremely bitter,* and she began to pray to Jehovah and to weep uncontrollably.

That is, the tabernacle.

Or “bitter of soul.”

^ (Ps. 55:22) Throw your burden on Jehovah, And he will sustain you. Never will he allow the righteous one to fall.*

Or “stagger; totter.”

^ (Ps. 73:17) Until I entered the grand sanctuary of God, And I discerned their future.

^ (Ps. 122:1) I rejoiced when they said to me: “Let us go to the house of Jehovah.”

^ (1 Sam. 1:18) To this she said: “Let your servant find favor in your eyes.” And the woman went on her way and ate, and her face was no longer downcast.

^ (Ps. 34:19) Many are the hardships* of the righteous one, But Jehovah rescues him from them all.

Or “calamities.”

^ (Ps. 73:23, 24) But now I am continually with you; You have taken hold of my right hand. 24 You guide me with your advice, And afterward you will lead me to glory.

^ (Ps. 143:1) O Jehovah, hear my prayer; Listen to my plea for help. In your faithfulness and in your righteousness, answer me.

^ (Ps. 143:4-8) My spirit* is failing; My heart is numb within me.  5 I remember the days of old; I meditate on all your activity; I eagerly ponder over* the work of your hands.  6 I spread out my hands to you; I am* like a parched land that thirsts for you. (Selah)  7 Do answer me quickly, O Jehovah; My strength* has come to an end. Do not hide your face from me, Or I will be like those going down into the pit.*  8 Let me hear your loyal love in the morning, For I trust in you. Make known to me the way I should walk, For to you I turn.*

Or “strength.”

Or “study.”

Or “My soul is.”

Lit., “spirit.”

Or “grave.”

Or “For I lift up my soul to you.”

Tuesday, September 7

Even if you should suffer for the sake of righteousness, you are happy.—[1 Pet. 3:14].

Never allow anything that mere humans say or do to make you feel ashamed of being one of Jehovah’s Witnesses. ([Mic. 4:5]) Consider the example set by the apostles in Jerusalem just after Jesus was put to death. They knew how much the Jewish religious leaders hated them. (Acts 5:17, 18,[27, 28]) Yet, every day they continued to go to the temple and publicly identify themselves as disciples of Jesus. ([Acts 5:42]) They refused to cower in fear. We too can defeat our own fear of man by regularly and publicly identifying ourselves as Jehovah’s Witnesses—at work, at school, and in our neighborhood. ([Acts 4:29;][Rom. 1:16]) Why were the apostles happy? They knew why they were hated, and they considered it an honor to be mistreated for doing Jehovah’s will. ([Luke 6:23;][Acts 5:41;] 1 Pet. 2:19-21) When we understand that we are hated for doing what is right, we will never allow the hatred of men to paralyze us with fear. w19.07 7 ¶19-20

^ (1 Pet. 3:14) But even if you should suffer for the sake of righteousness, you are happy. However, do not fear what they fear,* nor be disturbed.

Or possibly, “do not fear their threats.”

^ (Mic. 4:5) For all the peoples will walk, each in the name of its god, But we will walk in the name of Jehovah our God forever and ever.

^ (Acts 5:17, 18) But the high priest rose, and all those with him, who were of the sect of the Sadducees, and they were filled with jealousy. 18 And they seized* the apostles and put them in the public jail.

Or “arrested.” Lit., “laid hands on.”

^ (Acts 5:27, 28) So they brought them and stood them before the Sanʹhe·drin. Then the high priest questioned them 28 and said: “We strictly ordered you not to keep teaching on the basis of this name, and yet look! you have filled Jerusalem with your teaching, and you are determined to bring the blood of this man upon us.”

^ (Acts 5:42) And every day in the temple and from house to house they continued without letup teaching and declaring the good news about the Christ, Jesus.

^ (Acts 4:29) And now, Jehovah, give attention to their threats, and grant to your slaves to keep speaking your word with all boldness,

^ (Rom. 1:16) For I am not ashamed of the good news; it is, in fact, God’s power for salvation to everyone having faith, to the Jew first and also to the Greek.

^ (Luke 6:23) Rejoice in that day and leap for joy, for look! your reward is great in heaven, for those are the same things their forefathers used to do to the prophets.

^ (Acts 5:41) So they went out from before the Sanʹhe·drin, rejoicing because they had been counted worthy to be dishonored in behalf of his name.

^ (1 Pet. 2:19-21) For it is agreeable when someone endures hardship* and suffers unjustly because of conscience toward God. 20 For what merit is there if you are beaten for sinning and you endure it? But if you endure suffering because of doing good, this is an agreeable thing to God. 21 In fact, to this course you were called, because even Christ suffered for you, leaving a model for you to follow his steps closely.

Or “grief; pain.”

Saturday, September 11

Be filled with righteous fruit.—[Phil. 1:11].

No doubt this “righteous fruit” included love for Jehovah and his people. That would also include speaking to others about our faith in Jesus and our wonderful hope. We bear “righteous fruit” when we actively share in the most important work of making disciples. (Matt. 28:18-20) No matter what our circumstances, we can shine as illuminators. In some cases, what seems to be an obstacle to declaring the good news may turn out to be an opportunity for us to preach. The apostle Paul, for example, was under house arrest in Rome when he wrote his letter to the Philippians. But his chains did not hold him back from preaching to his captors and to visitors. Paul preached zealously under these circumstances, and this gave the brothers confidence and courage “to speak the word of God fearlessly.”—Phil. 1:12-14;[4:22]. w19.08 12 ¶15-16

^ (Phil. 1:11) and that you may be filled with righteous fruit, which is through Jesus Christ, to God’s glory and praise.

^ (Matt. 28:18-20) Jesus approached and spoke to them, saying: “All authority has been given me in heaven and on the earth. 19 Go, therefore, and make disciples of people of all the nations, baptizing them in the name of the Father and of the Son and of the holy spirit, 20 teaching them to observe all the things I have commanded you. And look! I am with you all the days until the conclusion of the system of things.”

^ (Phil. 1:12-14) Now I want you to know, brothers, that my situation has actually turned out for the advancement of the good news, 13 so that my prison bonds for the sake of Christ have become public knowledge among all the Prae·toʹri·an Guard and all the rest. 14 Now most of the brothers in the Lord have gained confidence because of my prison bonds, and they are showing all the more courage to speak the word of God fearlessly.

^ (Phil. 4:22) All the holy ones, but especially those of the household of Caesar, send you their greetings.

Monday, September 13

Everyone proud in heart is detestable to Jehovah.—[Prov. 16:5].

Elders work hard for the benefit of their brothers and sisters. And they do not let their authority make them unduly proud. Instead, they treat the congregation tenderly. (1 Thess. 2:7, 8) Their deep love and humble attitude affect how they speak to others. Andrew, an experienced elder, says: “I have found that the brothers and sisters generally respond well to an elder’s kindness and genuine warmth. These qualities motivate the congregation to cooperate with the elders.” Another longtime elder, named Tony, comments: “I try to apply the counsel found at Philippians 2:3 and constantly work at viewing others as superior to me. This helps me to avoid acting like a dictator.” Elders must be humble, just as Jehovah is humble. Although Jehovah is the Sovereign of the universe, he “stoops down” to raise “the lowly from the dust.” ([Ps. 18:35;][113:6, 7]) In fact, Jehovah detests those who are proud and arrogant. w19.09 16-17 ¶11-12

^ (Prov. 16:5) Everyone proud in heart is detestable to Jehovah. Be assured* that he will not go unpunished.

Lit., “Hand to hand.”

^ (1 Thess. 2:7, 8) On the contrary, we became gentle in your midst, as when a nursing mother tenderly cares for* her own children. 8 So having tender affection for you, we were determined* to impart to you, not only the good news of God but also our very selves,* because you became so beloved to us.

Or “cherishes.”

Lit., “well-pleased.”

Or “souls.”

^ (Phil. 2:3) Do nothing out of contentiousness or out of egotism, but with humility* consider others superior to you,

Or “lowliness of mind.”

^ (Ps. 18:35) You give me your shield of salvation, Your right hand supports* me, And your humility makes me great.

Or “sustains.”

^ (Ps. 113:6, 7) He stoops down to look on heaven and earth,  7 Raising the lowly from the dust. He lifts up the poor from the ash heap*

Or possibly, “garbage dump.”

Thursday, September 16

Barnabas came to his aid.—[Acts 9:27].

In the first century C.E., a generous man named Joseph (surnamed Barnabas) made himself available to be used by Jehovah. (Acts 4:36, 37) After Saul became a believer, many of the brothers were afraid to approach him because of his reputation as a persecutor of the congregations. However, warmhearted Barnabas came to Saul’s aid. ([Acts 9:21,][26-28]) Later, the elders in Jerusalem saw the need to provide encouragement to the brothers as far as Antioch of Syria. Whom did they send? Barnabas! They chose well. We are told that Barnabas “began to encourage them all to continue in the Lord with heartfelt resolve.” (Acts 11:22-24) Likewise today, Jehovah can help us to become a “son of comfort” to fellow Christians. For example, he might use us to comfort those who have lost loved ones in death. Or he may move us to visit or make a phone call to someone who is sick or depressed to share a few kind words. Will you allow Jehovah to use you as he did Barnabas?—1 Thess. 5:14. w19.10 22 ¶8

^ (Acts 9:27) So Barʹna·bas came to his aid and led him to the apostles, and he told them in detail how on the road he had seen the Lord, and that he had spoken to him, and how in Damascus he had spoken boldly in the name of Jesus.

^ (Acts 4:36, 37) So Joseph, who was also called by the apostles Barʹna·bas (which means, when translated, “Son of Comfort”), a Levite, a native of Cyʹprus, 37 owned a piece of land, and he sold it and brought the money and deposited it at the feet of the apostles.

^ (Acts 9:21) But all those hearing him were astonished and were saying: “Is this not the man who ravaged those in Jerusalem who call on this name? Did he not come here for the purpose of arresting them and taking them* to the chief priests?”

Lit., “come here in order that he might lead them bound.”

^ (Acts 9:26-28) On arriving in Jerusalem, he made efforts to join the disciples, but they were all afraid of him, because they did not believe he was a disciple. 27 So Barʹna·bas came to his aid and led him to the apostles, and he told them in detail how on the road he had seen the Lord, and that he had spoken to him, and how in Damascus he had spoken boldly in the name of Jesus. 28 So he remained with them, moving about freely in Jerusalem, speaking boldly in the name of the Lord.

^ (Acts 11:22-24) The report about them reached the ears of the congregation in Jerusalem, and they sent out Barʹna·bas as far as Antioch. 23 When he arrived and saw the undeserved kindness of God, he rejoiced and began to encourage them all to continue in the Lord with heartfelt resolve; 24 for he was a good man and full of holy spirit and faith. And a considerable crowd was added to the Lord.

^ (1 Thess. 5:14) On the other hand, we urge you, brothers, to warn* the disorderly, speak consolingly to those who are depressed,* support the weak, be patient toward all.

Or “admonish.”

Or “those who are discouraged.” Lit., “those of little soul.”

Saturday, September 18

Make disciples of people of all the nations, . . . teaching them to observe all the things I have commanded you.—Matt. 28:19, 20.

As we conduct Bible studies, we have to try our best to “make disciples . . . , teaching them to observe all the things [Jesus has] commanded.” We need to help people understand how important it is for them to take their stand for Jehovah and his Kingdom. This means trying to motivate people to make the truth their own by applying what they learn, dedicating their life to Jehovah, and getting baptized. Only then will they survive Jehovah’s day. ([1 Pet. 3:21]) There is very little time between now and the end of this system of things. For this reason, we cannot afford to keep studying the Bible with people who have no clear intention of becoming Christ’s disciples. ([1 Cor. 9:26]) Our work is urgent! There are many people who have yet to hear the Kingdom message before it is too late. w19.10 11-12 ¶14-15

^ (Matt. 28:19, 20) Go, therefore, and make disciples of people of all the nations, baptizing them in the name of the Father and of the Son and of the holy spirit, 20 teaching them to observe all the things I have commanded you. And look! I am with you all the days until the conclusion of the system of things.”

^ (1 Pet. 3:21) Baptism, which corresponds to this, is also now saving you (not by the removing of the filth of the flesh, but by the request to God for a good conscience), through the resurrection of Jesus Christ.

^ (1 Cor. 9:26) Therefore, the way I am running is not aimlessly; the way I am aiming my blows is so as not to be striking the air;

Tuesday, September 21

I have found David . . . a man agreeable to my heart.—[Acts 13:22].

How did David come to be so close to Jehovah? David learned about Jehovah from creation. When David was young, he spent many hours outdoors, caring for his father’s sheep. Perhaps it was then that he began to meditate on the things Jehovah had made. For example, as David gazed up at night, not only would he have seen a canopy of stars but he would also have discerned the qualities of the One who made them. ([Ps. 19:1, 2]) When David reflected on the way humans were made, he saw Jehovah’s wonderful wisdom at work. ([Ps. 139:14]) As David tried to comprehend Jehovah’s works, he felt humbled. ([Ps. 139:6]) What is the lesson for us? In your daily life, meditate on what the creation around you—the plants, animals, and people—teaches you about Jehovah. Then each new day will be full of lessons about your loving Father. ([Rom. 1:20]) And each day you will see your love for him grow more intense. w19.12 19-20 ¶15-17

^ (Acts 13:22) After removing him, he raised up for them David as king, about whom he bore witness and said: ‘I have found David the son of Jesʹse a man agreeable to my heart; he will do all the things I desire.’

^ (Ps. 19:1, 2) The heavens are declaring the glory of God; The skies above* proclaim the work of his hands.  2 Day after day their speech bubbles forth, And night after night they reveal knowledge.

Or “expanse.”

^ (Ps. 139:14) I praise you because in an awe-inspiring way I am wonderfully made. Your works are wonderful, I know* this very well.

Or “My soul knows.”

^ (Ps. 139:6) Such knowledge is beyond my comprehension.* It is too high for me to reach.*

Or “is too amazing for me.”

Or “too much for me to fathom.”

^ (Rom. 1:20) For his invisible qualities are clearly seen from the world’s creation onward, because they are perceived by the things made, even his eternal power and Godship, so that they are inexcusable.

Thursday, September 23

Jehovah God went on to form the man out of dust from the ground and to blow into his nostrils the breath of life.—[Gen. 2:7].

Even though we are made from the dust of the earth, we are worth far more than a handful of dirt. Consider just some of the reasons why we know that we are valuable to Jehovah. He created humans with the ability to reflect his qualities. ([Gen. 1:27]) In doing so, he elevated us above the rest of physical creation, putting us in charge of the earth and the animals. ([Ps. 8:4-8]) Even after Adam sinned, Jehovah continued to value humans. He values us so highly that he gave his beloved Son, Jesus, as a ransom for our sins. (1 John 4:9, 10) Applying the benefits of the ransom, Jehovah will resurrect those who have died as a result of Adam’s sin, “both the righteous and the unrighteous.” ([Acts 24:15]) His Word shows that we are precious to him no matter what our health condition, financial situation, or age may be.—Acts 10:34, 35. w20.01 15 ¶5-6

^ (Gen. 2:7) And Jehovah God went on to form the man out of dust from the ground and to blow into his nostrils the breath of life, and the man became a living person.*

Or “soul.” Hebrew, neʹphesh, which literally means “a breathing creature.” See Glossary.

^ (Gen. 1:27) And God went on to create the man in his image, in God’s image he created him; male and female he created them.

^ (Ps. 8:4-8) What is mortal man that you keep him in mind, And a son of man that you take care of him?  5 You made him a little lower than godlike ones,* And you crowned him with glory and splendor.  6 You gave him dominion over the works of your hands; You have put everything under his feet:  7 All the flocks and cattle, As well as the wild animals,*  8 The birds of the heavens and the fish of the sea, Whatever passes through the paths of the seas.

Or “than angels.”

Lit., “the beasts of the field.”

^ (1 John 4:9, 10) By this the love of God was revealed in our case, that God sent his only-begotten Son into the world so that we might gain life through him. 10 The love is in this respect, not that we have loved God, but that he loved us and sent his Son as a propitiatory sacrifice* for our sins.

Or “an atoning sacrifice; a means of appeasement.”

^ (Acts 24:15) And I have hope toward God, which hope these men also look forward to, that there is going to be a resurrection of both the righteous and the unrighteous.

^ (Acts 10:34, 35) At this Peter began to speak, and he said: “Now I truly understand that God is not partial, 35 but in every nation the man who fears him and does what is right is acceptable to him.

Friday, September 24

Mind your own business.—1 Thess. 4:11.

A person does not inherit his heavenly hope from his family. He receives it from God. (1 Thess. 2:12) So avoid asking questions that could hurt others. For example, we would not ask the wife of an anointed brother how she feels about the prospect of living forever on earth without her husband. After all, we can be absolutely sure that in the new world, Jehovah will “satisfy the desire of every living thing.” ([Ps. 145:16]) If we do not treat anointed ones as more important than others, we also protect ourselves. How? The Bible tells us that some anointed ones might not remain faithful. (Matt. 25:10-12; 2 Pet. 2:20, 21) But if we avoid “admiring personalities,” we will never follow others, even those who are anointed or well-known or those who have served Jehovah for a long time. ([Jude 16], ftn.) Then, if they become unfaithful or leave the congregation, we will not lose our faith in Jehovah or stop serving him. w20.01 29 ¶9-10

^ (1 Thess. 4:11) Make it your aim to live quietly and to mind your own business and to work with your hands, just as we instructed you,

^ (1 Thess. 2:12) so that you would go on walking worthily of God, who is calling you to his Kingdom and glory.

^ (Ps. 145:16) You open your hand And satisfy the desire of every living thing.

^ (Matt. 25:10-12) While they were going off to buy it, the bridegroom came. The virgins who were ready went in with him to the marriage feast, and the door was shut. 11 Afterward, the rest of the virgins also came, saying, ‘Sir, Sir, open to us!’ 12 In answer he said, ‘I tell you the truth, I do not know you.’

^ (2 Pet. 2:20, 21) Certainly if after escaping from the defilements of the world by an accurate knowledge of the Lord and Savior Jesus Christ, they get involved again with these very things and are overcome, their final state has become worse for them than the first. 21 It would have been better for them not to have accurately known the path of righteousness than after knowing it to turn away from the holy commandment they had received.

^ (Jude 16) These men are murmurers, complainers about their lot in life, following their own desires, and their mouths make grandiose boasts, while they are flattering others* for their own benefit.

Or “admiring personalities.”

Sunday, October 3

Everyone proud in heart is detestable to Jehovah.—[Prov. 16:5].

Why does Jehovah detest proud people? One reason is that those who develop and promote an inflated love of self reflect Satan’s own arrogance. Imagine, Satan believed that Jesus—the one whom God used to create all things—should bow down and worship him! (Matt. 4:8, 9; Col. 1:15, 16) Those with such an inflated view of their own importance confirm that the wisdom of the world is foolishness with God. ([1 Cor. 3:19]) The Bible, though, helps us to have a balanced view of ourselves. It acknowledges that a degree of self-love is proper. Jesus said: “Love your neighbor as yourself,” which indicates that we should give a reasonable amount of attention to our needs. ([Matt. 19:19]) However, the Bible does not teach that we should elevate ourselves above others. Rather, it states: “Do nothing out of contentiousness or out of egotism, but with humility consider others superior to you.”—[Phil. 2:3;][Rom. 12:3]. w19.05 24 ¶13-14

^ (Prov. 16:5) Everyone proud in heart is detestable to Jehovah. Be assured* that he will not go unpunished.

Lit., “Hand to hand.”

^ (Matt. 4:8, 9) Again the Devil took him along to an unusually high mountain and showed him all the kingdoms of the world and their glory. 9 And he said to him: “All these things I will give you if you fall down and do an act of worship to me.”

^ (Col. 1:15, 16) He is the image of the invisible God, the firstborn of all creation; 16 because by means of him all other things were created in the heavens and on the earth, the things visible and the things invisible, whether they are thrones or lordships or governments or authorities. All other things have been created through him and for him.

^ (1 Cor. 3:19) For the wisdom of this world is foolishness with God, for it is written: “He catches the wise in their own cunning.”

^ (Matt. 19:19) honor your father and your mother, and you must love your neighbor as yourself.”

^ (Phil. 2:3) Do nothing out of contentiousness or out of egotism, but with humility* consider others superior to you,

Or “lowliness of mind.”

^ (Rom. 12:3) For through the undeserved kindness given to me, I tell everyone there among you not to think more of himself than it is necessary to think, but to think so as to have a sound mind, each one as God has given* to him a measure of faith.

Or “apportioned; distributed.”

Monday, October 4

Stop being molded by this system of things, but be transformed by making your mind over.—[Rom. 12:2].

Think back to the changes you needed to make when you first accepted the truth of God’s Word and decided to serve Jehovah. For many of us, this involved giving up some form of wrong conduct. (1 Cor. 6:9-11) How grateful we are for Jehovah’s help in overcoming such sinful practices! However, we must never become complacent. Even though we stopped committing serious sins that we engaged in before baptism, we still need to be diligent about avoiding anything that would tempt us to return to those former deeds. A twofold action is required. First, we need to “stop being molded,” or shaped, by this world. Second, we need to “be transformed” by making our mind over. The transformation involves more than a superficial change in appearance. It touches every fiber of our being. We need to make over our mind—our innermost attitudes, feelings, and inclinations. w19.06 9 ¶4-6

^ (Rom. 12:2) And stop being molded by this system of things, but be transformed by making your mind over, so that you may prove to yourselves the good and acceptable and perfect will of God.

^ (1 Cor. 6:9-11) Or do you not know that unrighteous people will not inherit God’s Kingdom? Do not be misled.* Those who are sexually immoral, idolaters, adulterers, men who submit to homosexual acts, men who practice homosexuality, 10 thieves, greedy people, drunkards, revilers, and extortioners will not inherit God’s Kingdom. 11 And yet that is what some of you were. But you have been washed clean; you have been sanctified; you have been declared righteous in the name of the Lord Jesus Christ and with the spirit of our God.

Or “Do not be deceived.”

Wednesday, October 6

Go, report to my brothers so that they may go to Galilee, and there they will see me.—[Matt. 28:10].

Jesus must have some very important instructions to give his disciples, for this meeting is the first thing he arranges after his resurrection! At the meeting that Jesus organized, he outlined the vital work that his disciples would accomplish throughout the first century—the same work that we are accomplishing today. Jesus said: “Go, therefore, and make disciples of people of all the nations, . . . teaching them to observe all the things I have commanded you.” (Matt. 28:19, 20) Jesus wants all his followers to preach. He did not limit this command to the 11 faithful apostles. How can we be so sure? Well, were only the apostles present when the command to make disciples was given on that mountain in Galilee? Recall that the angel said to the women: “You will see him [in Galilee].” ([Matt. 28:7]) So faithful women must also have been present on that occasion. w20.01 2-3 ¶1-4

^ (Matt. 28:10) Then Jesus said to them: “Have no fear! Go, report to my brothers so that they may go to Galʹi·lee, and there they will see me.”

^ (Matt. 28:19, 20) Go, therefore, and make disciples of people of all the nations, baptizing them in the name of the Father and of the Son and of the holy spirit, 20 teaching them to observe all the things I have commanded you. And look! I am with you all the days until the conclusion of the system of things.”

^ (Matt. 28:7) Then go quickly and tell his disciples that he was raised up from the dead, for look! he is going ahead of you into Galʹi·lee. You will see him there. Look! I have told you.”

Thursday, October 7

Because you are no part of the world, but I have chosen you out of the world, for this reason the world hates you.—[John 15:19].

Jesus explained why we should expect opposition. He said that we would be hated because we are no part of the world. Persecution is not a sign that we lack Jehovah’s blessing. Instead, it indicates that we are doing what is right! Mere human opposers cannot stamp out the worship of the almighty God, Jehovah. Many have tried and failed. Consider what happened during World War II. At that time, governments in many countries intensely persecuted God’s people. The work of Jehovah’s Witnesses was banned not only by the Nazi party in Germany but also by governments in Australia, Canada, and other lands. Yet, note what took place. In 1939 when the war began, there were 72,475 publishers worldwide. Reports showed that by the end of the war in 1945, with Jehovah’s blessing, there were 156,299 publishers. The number of publishers had more than doubled! w19.07 9 ¶4-5

^ (John 15:19) If you were part of the world, the world would be fond of what is its own. Now because you are no part of the world, but I have chosen you out of the world, for this reason the world hates you.

Friday, October 8

By this all will know that you are my disciples—if you have love among yourselves.—[John 13:35].

Even if you are not presently conducting a Bible study, you can assist in making disciples in other ways. For example, you can welcome new ones and befriend them when they come to the Kingdom Hall. In that way, you can help to convince them that love identifies us as true Christians. The answers you give during the meetings, though brief, can teach newly associated ones to express their convictions in a sincere and respectful manner. You can also accompany a new publisher in the ministry and help him to use the Scriptures to reason with people. By doing that, you will be teaching him to imitate Christ. (Luke 10:25-28) Many Christians are very busy caring for important responsibilities. Still, they make time for conducting Bible studies, and they get much joy from it. w19.07 17 ¶11, 13

^ (John 13:35) By this all will know that you are my disciples—if you have love among yourselves.”

^ (Luke 10:25-28) Now look! a man versed in the Law stood up to test him and said: “Teacher, what do I need to do to inherit everlasting life?” 26 He said to him: “What is written in the Law? How do you read?” 27 In answer he said: “‘You must love Jehovah your God with your whole heart and with your whole soul and with your whole strength and with your whole mind’ and ‘your neighbor as yourself.’” 28 He said to him: “You answered correctly; keep doing this and you will get life.”

Wednesday, October 13

Welcome [Mark] if he comes to you.—[Col. 4:10].

Mark was happy to serve others. At various times he served alongside both the apostle Paul and the apostle Peter as they fulfilled their responsibilities, with Mark possibly attending to their physical needs. ([Acts 13:2-5;][1 Pet. 5:13]) Paul described Mark as one of his “fellow workers for the Kingdom of God” and as “a strengthening aid” to him. ([Col. 4:11], ftn.) Mark became one of Paul’s close friends. For example, when Paul was imprisoned for the last time in Rome, about 65 C.E., he wrote his second letter to Timothy. In that letter, Paul asked Timothy to come to Rome and to bring Mark along. ([2 Tim. 4:11]) Paul no doubt appreciated Mark’s past faithful service, so he asked for Mark’s presence at that crucial time. Mark helped Paul in practical ways, perhaps supplying him with food or items for his writing. The support and encouragement that Paul received likely helped him to endure the final days leading up to his execution. w20.01 11 ¶12-13

^ (Col. 4:10) Ar·is·tarʹchus, my fellow captive, sends you his greetings, and so does Mark, the cousin of Barʹna·bas (concerning whom you received instructions to welcome him if he comes to you),

^ (Acts 13:2-5) As they were ministering to Jehovah and fasting, the holy spirit said: “Set aside for me Barʹna·bas and Saul for the work to which I have called them.” 3 Then after fasting and praying, they laid their hands on them and sent them off. 4 So these men, sent out by the holy spirit, went down to Se·leuʹcia, and from there they sailed away to Cyʹprus. 5 When they arrived in Salʹa·mis, they began proclaiming the word of God in the synagogues of the Jews. They also had John as an attendant.*

Or “an assistant.”

^ (1 Pet. 5:13) She who is in Babylon, a chosen one like you, sends you her greetings, and so does Mark, my son.

^ (Col. 4:11) and Jesus who is called Justus, who are of those circumcised. Only these are my fellow workers for the Kingdom of God, and they have become a source of great comfort* to me.

Or “a strengthening aid.”

^ (2 Tim. 4:11) Only Luke is with me. Bring Mark along with you, for he is helpful to me in the ministry.

Friday, October 15

By wisdom a house is built up, and by discernment it is made secure.—[Prov. 24:3].

Needing help, David’s men asked a wealthy Israelite named Nabal for a little food. They felt free to ask because they had been protecting Nabal’s flocks in the wilderness. But selfish Nabal refused to give them anything. David became furious and intended to wipe out Nabal and every male of his household. (1 Sam. 25:3-13,[22]) However, Nabal’s wife, Abigail, was as discerning as she was beautiful. Showing great courage, she fell at David’s feet and urged him not to incur bloodguilt by taking revenge. She tactfully advised him to leave matters in Jehovah’s hands. Abigail’s humble words and discreet actions touched David’s heart. He rightly concluded that Jehovah had sent her. (1 Sam. 25:23-28,[32-34]) Abigail had cultivated qualities that made her useful to Jehovah. Similarly, Christian sisters who develop tact and discernment can be used by Jehovah to build up their families and others in the congregation.—[Titus 2:3-5]. w19.10 23 ¶10

^ (Prov. 24:3) By wisdom a house* is built up, And by discernment it is made secure.

Or “household.”

^ (1 Sam. 25:22) May God do the same and more to the enemies of David* if I allow a single male* of his to survive until the morning.”

Or possibly, “to David.”

Lit., “anyone urinating against a wall.” A Hebrew expression of contempt referring to males.

^ (1 Sam. 25:23-28) When Abʹi·gail caught sight of David, she hurried down off the donkey and threw herself facedown before David, bowing to the ground. 24 She then fell at his feet and said: “My lord, let the blame be on me; let your servant girl speak to you, and listen to the words of your servant girl. 25 Please, do not let my lord pay attention to this worthless Naʹbal, for he is just like his name. Naʹbal* is his name, and senselessness is with him. But I, your servant girl, did not see my lord’s young men whom you sent. 26 And now, my lord, as surely as Jehovah is living and as you are* living, it is Jehovah who has held you back from incurring bloodguilt and from taking revenge* with your own hand. May your enemies and those seeking injury to my lord become like Naʹbal. 27 Now let this gift* that your servant girl has brought to my lord be given to the young men who are following my lord. 28 Pardon, please, the transgression of your servant girl, for Jehovah will without fail make for my lord a lasting house, because my lord is fighting the wars of Jehovah, and no evil has been found in you all your days.

Meaning “Senseless; Stupid.”

Or “your soul is.”

Or “bringing salvation.”

Lit., “blessing.”

^ (1 Sam. 25:32-34) At this David said to Abʹi·gail: “Praise Jehovah the God of Israel, who sent you this day to meet me! 33 And blessed be your good sense! May you be blessed for restraining me this day from incurring bloodguilt and from taking revenge* with my own hands. 34 Otherwise, as surely as Jehovah the God of Israel who held me back from harming you is living, if you had not come quickly to meet me, by morning there would not have remained a single male* belonging to Naʹbal.”

Or “bringing salvation.”

Lit., “anyone urinating against a wall.” A Hebrew expression of contempt referring to males.

^ (Titus 2:3-5) Likewise, let the older women be reverent in behavior, not slanderous, not enslaved to a lot of wine, teachers of what is good, 4 so that they may advise* the younger women to love their husbands, to love their children, 5 to be sound in mind, chaste, working at home,* good, subjecting themselves to their own husbands, so that the word of God may not be spoken of abusively.

Or “recall to their senses; train.”

Or “caring for their homes.”

Sunday, October 17

Jehovah is merciful and compassionate . . . He will not always find fault, nor will he stay resentful forever.—[Ps. 103:8, 9].

Jeremiah wrote the book named after him, and he likely also wrote the Bible books of 1 and 2 Kings. That assignment no doubt made him especially aware of Jehovah’s mercy toward imperfect humans. For example, he knew that when King Ahab repented of his bad deeds, Jehovah spared him from seeing his entire family destroyed during his lifetime. (1 Ki. 21:27-29) Similarly, Jeremiah knew that Manasseh did even more to offend Jehovah than Ahab did. Even so, Jehovah forgave Manasseh because he repented. (2 Ki. 21:16, 17; 2 Chron. 33:10-13) Those accounts must have helped Jeremiah to imitate God’s patience and mercy. Consider how Jeremiah dealt with Baruch when he temporarily became distracted in his assignment. Instead of quickly giving up on his friend, Jeremiah helped Baruch by sharing God’s kind but frank message with him.—[Jer. 45:1-5]. w19.11 6 ¶14-15

^ (Ps. 103:8, 9) Jehovah is merciful and compassionate,* Slow to anger and abundant in loyal love.*  9 He will not always find fault, Nor will he stay resentful forever.

Or “gracious.”

Or “loving-kindness.”

^ (1 Ki. 21:27-29) As soon as Aʹhab heard these words, he ripped his garments apart and put sackcloth on his body; and he went on a fast and kept lying down in sackcloth and walking despondently. 28 Jehovah’s word then came to E·liʹjah the Tishʹbite: 29 “Have you seen how Aʹhab has humbled himself on my account? Because he has humbled himself before me, I will not bring the calamity during his lifetime. I will bring the calamity upon his house in the days of his son.”

^ (2 Ki. 21:16, 17) Ma·nasʹseh also shed innocent blood in very great quantity until he had filled Jerusalem from one end to the other, besides his sin of causing Judah to sin by doing what was bad in the eyes of Jehovah. 17 As for the rest of the history of Ma·nasʹseh and all that he did and the sins that he committed, are they not written in the book of the history of the times of the kings of Judah?

^ (2 Chron. 33:10-13) Jehovah kept speaking to Ma·nasʹseh and his people, but they paid no attention. 11 So Jehovah brought against them the army chiefs of the king of As·syrʹi·a, and they captured Ma·nasʹseh with hooks* and bound him with two copper fetters and took him to Babylon. 12 In his distress, he begged Jehovah his God for favor* and kept humbling himself greatly before the God of his forefathers. 13 He kept praying to Him, and He was moved by his entreaty and heard his request for favor, and He restored him to Jerusalem to his kingship. Then Ma·nasʹseh came to know that Jehovah is the true God.

Or possibly, “in the hollows.”

Or “softened the face of Jehovah his God.”

^ (Jer. 45:1-5) This is the word that Jeremiah the prophet spoke to Barʹuch the son of Ne·riʹah when he wrote in a book these words dictated by Jeremiah in the fourth year of Je·hoiʹa·kim son of Jo·siʹah, the king of Judah: 2 “This is what Jehovah the God of Israel says concerning you, Barʹuch, 3 ‘You have said: “Woe to me, for Jehovah has added grief to my pain! I am weary from my groaning, and I have found no resting-place.”’ 4 “You should say to him, ‘This is what Jehovah says: “Look! What I have built up I am tearing down, and what I have planted I am uprooting—the entire land. 5 But you are seeking* great things for yourself. Stop seeking such things.”’ “‘For I am about to bring a calamity on all flesh,’* declares Jehovah, ‘and wherever you may go, I will grant you your life* as a spoil.’”*

Or “expecting.”

Or “people.”

Or “soul.”

Or “will let you escape with your life.”

Monday, October 18

God is not unrighteous so as to forget your work and the love you showed for his name.—[Heb. 6:10].

In the book of Leviticus, we learn that an Israelite could offer a communion sacrifice “as an expression of thanksgiving.” (Lev. 7:11-13,[16-18]) He made this offering, not because he had to, but because he wanted to. Like those communion sacrifices, our service to Jehovah is a voluntary expression of how we feel about him. We give Jehovah our best, and we do so because we love him with all our heart. How pleased Jehovah must be to see millions of willing worshippers serve him out of deep love for him and his ways! Jehovah sees and values not only our actions but also our motives. For example, if you are elderly and can no longer do as much as you would like, be assured that Jehovah sees beyond your limitations. You may feel that you have little to offer, but Jehovah sees the love deep within you that motivates you to do what you can do. He is pleased to accept the best that you can give. w19.11 22 ¶9; 23 ¶11-12

^ (Heb. 6:10) For God is not unrighteous so as to forget your work and the love you showed for his name by ministering and continuing to minister to the holy ones.

^ (Lev. 7:11-13) “‘Now this is the law of the communion sacrifice that one may present to Jehovah: 12 If he presents it as an expression of thanksgiving, he will present along with the thanksgiving sacrifice unleavened ring-shaped loaves mixed with oil, unleavened wafers spread with oil, and ring-shaped loaves made with fine flour, well-mixed and blended with oil. 13 He will present his offering along with ring-shaped loaves of leavened bread and the thanksgiving sacrifice of his communion sacrifices.

^ (Lev. 7:16-18) “‘If the sacrifice of his offering is a vow or a voluntary offering, it is to be eaten on the day he presents his sacrifice, and what is left of it may also be eaten on the next day. 17 But whatever is left of the flesh of the sacrifice on the third day is to be burned with fire. 18 However, if any of the flesh of his communion sacrifice is eaten on the third day, the one presenting it will not be accepted with approval. It will not be credited to him; it is an offensive thing, and the person* who eats some of it will answer for his error.

Or “soul.”

Thursday, October 21

Jehovah . . . takes note of the humble.—[Ps. 138:6].

When David defended his father’s sheep from a lion and from a bear, he recognized that it was Jehovah who was helping him overcome those powerful predators. When he defeated the giant warrior Goliath, David saw clearly that it was Jehovah who was guiding him. ([1 Sam. 17:37]) And when he escaped from jealous King Saul, David acknowledged that it was Jehovah who had saved him. (Ps. 18, superscription) A proud man might have taken credit for those accomplishments. But David was humble, so he was able to recognize Jehovah’s hand in his life. What is the lesson for us? We need to do more than just ask for Jehovah’s help. We must also try to recognize when and how he gives us help. If we humbly acknowledge our limitations, we will clearly see that Jehovah makes up for what we lack. And each time we see Jehovah help us, our relationship with him will grow stronger. w19.12 20 ¶18-19

^ (Ps. 138:6) Though Jehovah is high, he takes note of the humble, But the haughty he knows only from a distance.

^ (1 Sam. 17:37) Then David added: “Jehovah, who rescued me from the claws of the lion and the bear, he is the one who will rescue me from the hand of this Phi·lisʹtine.” At this Saul said to David: “Go, and may Jehovah be with you.”

Saturday, October 23

[Teach] them to observe all the things I have commanded you.—[Matt. 28:20].

When conducting a Bible study, start the session with prayer. Generally speaking, it is best to begin opening and closing the study with prayer as soon as possible, usually within the first few weeks after starting a regular study. We must help the student to realize that we can understand God’s Word only with the help of God’s spirit. Some Bible teachers raise the subject of prayer by reading [James 1:5], which states: “If any one of you is lacking in wisdom, let him keep asking God.” The conductor then asks the student, “How can we ask God for wisdom?” The student will likely agree that we should pray to God. Teach your student how to pray. Reassure him that Jehovah wants to hear his heartfelt prayers. Explain that in our private prayers, we can really open our heart to Jehovah—expressing feelings that we might hesitate to share with any human. After all, Jehovah already knows our innermost thoughts.—[Ps. 139:2-4]. w20.01 2 ¶3; 5 ¶11-12

^ (Matt. 28:20) teaching them to observe all the things I have commanded you. And look! I am with you all the days until the conclusion of the system of things.”

^ (Jas. 1:5) So if any one of you is lacking in wisdom, let him keep asking God, for he gives generously to all and without reproaching,* and it will be given him.

Or “finding fault.”

^ (Ps. 139:2-4) You know when I sit down and when I rise up. You discern my thoughts from afar.  3 You observe* me when I travel and when I lie down; You are familiar with all my ways.  4 There is not a word on my tongue, But look! O Jehovah, you already know it well.

Lit., “measure.”

Sunday, October 24

It depends, not on a person’s desire or on his effort, but on God.—[Rom. 9:16].

Jehovah decides when he will choose anointed ones. ([Rom. 8:28-30]) Jehovah began choosing anointed ones after Jesus was resurrected. It seems that in the first century, all true Christians were anointed. In the centuries that followed, most of those who claimed that they were Christians did not really follow Christ. Even so, during those years, Jehovah anointed the few who were true Christians. They were like the wheat that Jesus said would grow among the weeds. (Matt. 13:24-30) During the last days, Jehovah has continued to choose people who will be part of the 144,000. So if God decides to choose some of these just before the end, surely we should not question his wisdom. ([Rom. 9:11]) We must be careful not to react like the workers whom Jesus described in one of his illustrations. They complained about the way their master treated those who started working in the last hour.—Matt. 20:8-15. w20.01 30 ¶14

^ (Rom. 9:16) So, then, it depends, not on a person’s desire or on his effort, but on God, who has mercy.

^ (Rom. 8:28-30) We know that God makes all his works cooperate together for the good of those who love God, those who are the ones called according to his purpose; 29 because those whom he gave his first recognition he also foreordained to be patterned after the image of his Son, so that he might be the firstborn among many brothers. 30 Moreover, those whom he foreordained are the ones he also called; and those whom he called are the ones he also declared to be righteous. Finally those whom he declared righteous are the ones he also glorified.

^ (Matt. 13:24-30) He presented another illustration to them, saying: “The Kingdom of the heavens may be likened to a man who sowed fine seed in his field. 25 While men were sleeping, his enemy came and oversowed weeds in among the wheat and left. 26 When the stalk sprouted and produced fruit, then the weeds also appeared. 27 So the slaves of the master of the house came and said to him, ‘Master, did you not sow fine seed in your field? How, then, does it have weeds?’ 28 He said to them, ‘An enemy, a man, did this.’ The slaves said to him, ‘Do you want us, then, to go out and collect them?’ 29 He said, ‘No, for fear that while collecting the weeds, you uproot the wheat with them. 30 Let both grow together until the harvest, and in the harvest season, I will tell the reapers: First collect the weeds and bind them in bundles to burn them up; then gather the wheat into my storehouse.’”

^ (Rom. 9:11) for when they had not yet been born and had not practiced anything good or bad, so that God’s purpose respecting the choosing might continue dependent, not on works, but on the One who calls,

^ (Matt. 20:8-15) “When evening came, the master of the vineyard said to his man in charge, ‘Call the workers and pay them their wages, starting with the last and ending with the first.’ 9 When the 11th-hour men came, they each received a de·narʹi·us. 10 So when the first came, they assumed that they would receive more, but they too were paid at the rate of a de·narʹi·us. 11 On receiving it, they began to complain against the master of the house 12 and said, ‘These last men put in one hour’s work; still you made them equal to us who bore the burden of the day and the burning heat!’ 13 But he said in reply to one of them, ‘Fellow, I do you no wrong. You agreed with me for a de·narʹi·us, did you not? 14 Take what is yours and go. I want to give to this last one the same as to you. 15 Do I not have the right to do what I want with my own things? Or is your eye envious because I am good?’

Tuesday, October 26

Against you—you above all—I have sinned.—[Ps. 51:4].

If you commit a serious sin, do not try to cover the error. Instead, openly confess your sin to Jehovah in prayer. You will then begin to feel some relief from the anxiety caused by a guilty conscience. But if you want to restore your friendship with Jehovah, you need to do more than pray. You need to accept discipline. When Jehovah sent the prophet Nathan to expose King David’s sin with Bath-sheba, David did not justify himself or try to minimize the sin. He immediately acknowledged that he had sinned not only against Bath-sheba’s husband but, above all, against Jehovah. David accepted the discipline from Jehovah, and Jehovah forgave him. (2 Sam. 12:10-14) If we have committed a serious sin, we need to talk to those whom Jehovah has appointed to shepherd us. (Jas. 5:14, 15) And we must avoid the urge to justify ourselves. The sooner we accept and apply whatever discipline we receive, the sooner we will regain our peace and joy. w20.02 24-25 ¶17-18

^ (Ps. 51:4) Against you—you above all*—I have sinned; What is bad in your eyes I have done. Therefore, you are righteous when you speak, You are right in your judgment.

Lit., “only you.”

^ (2 Sam. 12:10-14) Now a sword will never depart from your own house, because you despised me by taking the wife of U·riʹah the Hitʹtite as your wife.’ 11 This is what Jehovah says: ‘Here I am bringing against you calamity from within your own house; and before your own eyes, I will take your wives and give them to another man,* and he will lie down with your wives in broad daylight.* 12 Although you acted in secret, I will do this in front of all Israel and in broad daylight.’”* 13 David then said to Nathan: “I have sinned against Jehovah.” Nathan replied to David: “Jehovah, in turn, forgives your sin.* You will not die. 14 Nevertheless, because you have treated Jehovah with utter disrespect in this matter, the son just born to you will certainly die.”

Or “to your fellow man.”

Lit., “to the eyes of this sun.”

Lit., “before the sun.”

Or “lets your sin pass by.”

^ (Jas. 5:14, 15) Is there anyone sick among you? Let him call the elders of the congregation to him, and let them pray over him, applying oil to him in the name of Jehovah.* 15 And the prayer of faith will make the sick one* well, and Jehovah* will raise him up. Also, if he has committed sins, he will be forgiven.

See App. A5.

Or possibly, “tired one.”

See App. A5.

Wednesday, October 27

Ten men out of all the languages of the nations . . . will take firm hold of the robe of a Jew, saying: “We want to go with you, for we have heard that God is with you people.”—[Zech. 8:23].

The “ten men” represent those who have the hope of living forever on earth. They know that Jehovah has blessed the group of anointed ones represented by the “Jew” and feel that it is an honor to worship him along with them. Even though it is not possible to know the name of each individual member of the anointed on earth today, those who hope to live on earth can “go with” the anointed. How? Today’s text answers. Note that the Bible verse mentions one Jew. But “you” and “you people” refer to more than one person. This means that this Jew is not just one person but represents the whole group of anointed ones. Those who are not anointed serve Jehovah along with the anointed. However, they do not view the anointed as their leaders, realizing that Jesus fills the role of Leader.—[Matt. 23:10]. w20.01 26 ¶1-2

^ (Zech. 8:23) “This is what Jehovah of armies says, ‘In those days ten men out of all the languages of the nations will take hold, yes, they will take firm hold of the robe* of a Jew,* saying: “We want to go with you, for we have heard that God is with you people.”’”

Or “extremity of the garment.”

Lit., “a Jewish man.”

^ (Matt. 23:10) Neither be called leaders, for your Leader is one, the Christ.

Thursday, October 28

By this all will know that you are my disciples—if you have love among yourselves.—[John 13:35].

Jesus said that his true disciples would be clearly identifiable if they showed the same sort of love that he displayed. That statement was true in the first century, and it is true today. How important it is that we overcome any challenges and show love for one another! Ask yourself: ‘What can I learn from brothers and sisters who have continued to show love for one another despite challenges?’ Human imperfection makes it difficult for us to show intense love for one another. Even so, we must try to imitate Christ. Jesus taught us the importance of making peace with a brother who has something against us. (Matt. 5:23, 24) He emphasized that we need to maintain good relations with others if we are to please God. Jehovah is happy when we do our best to make peace with our brothers. He will not accept our worship if we hang on to resentment and refuse even to try to make peace.—[1 John 4:20]. w20.03 24 ¶1-4

^ (John 13:35) By this all will know that you are my disciples—if you have love among yourselves.”

^ (Matt. 5:23, 24) “If, then, you are bringing your gift to the altar and there you remember that your brother has something against you, 24 leave your gift there in front of the altar, and go away. First make your peace with your brother, and then come back and offer your gift.

^ (1 John 4:20) If anyone says, “I love God,” and yet is hating his brother, he is a liar. For the one who does not love his brother, whom he has seen, cannot love God, whom he has not seen.

Friday, November 5

We are going to destroy this place.—[Gen. 19:13].

Jehovah compassionately sent angels to rescue Lot and his family. However, Lot “kept lingering.” The angels had to seize hold of his hand and help him and his family flee the city. (Gen. 19:15, 16) The angels then told him to run to the mountainous region. But instead of obeying Jehovah, Lot asked to go to a nearby town. (Gen. 19:17-20) Jehovah patiently listened and allowed Lot to go to that town. Lot later became afraid of living there and moved to the mountainous region, the very area Jehovah had told him to go to in the first place. ([Gen. 19:30]) What remarkable patience Jehovah showed! Like Lot, a member of our spiritual family may make poor decisions and cause serious problems for himself. If that were to happen, how would we respond? We might be tempted to point out that he is reaping what he has sown, which would be true. ([Gal. 6:7]) However, we can do better. We can imitate the way that Jehovah helped Lot. w19.06 20-21 ¶3-5

^ (Gen. 19:13) For we are going to destroy this place, because the outcry against them has indeed grown great* before Jehovah, so that Jehovah sent us to destroy the city.”

Or “loud.”

^ (Gen. 19:15, 16) As dawn was breaking, the angels became urgent with Lot, saying: “Get up! Take your wife and your two daughters who are here with you, so that you will not be swept away in the error of the city!” 16 When he kept lingering, then because of Jehovah’s compassion for him, the men seized hold of his hand and the hand of his wife and the hands of his two daughters, and they brought him out and stationed him outside the city.

^ (Gen. 19:17-20) As soon as they had brought them to the outskirts, he said: “Escape for your life!* Do not look behind you and do not stand still in any part of the district! Escape to the mountainous region so that you may not be swept away!” 18 Then Lot said to them: “Not there, please, Jehovah! 19 Please, now, your servant has found favor in your eyes and you are showing great kindness* to me by preserving me* alive, but I am not able to flee to the mountainous region because I am afraid that disaster may overtake me and I will die. 20 Please, now, this town is nearby and I can flee there; it is only a small place. May I, please, escape there? It is only a small place. Then I will survive.”*

Or “soul.”

Or “loyal love.”

Or “my soul.”

Or “my soul will live on.”

^ (Gen. 19:30) Later Lot went up from Zoʹar with his two daughters and began living in the mountainous region, because he was afraid to live in Zoʹar. So he began living in a cave with his two daughters.

^ (Gal. 6:7) Do not be misled: God is not one to be mocked. For whatever a person is sowing, this he will also reap;

Saturday, November 6

Jehovah is my helper; I will not be afraid.—[Heb. 13:6].

When our enemies ban our worship, they hope to make us afraid to serve Jehovah. In addition to the ban, they may circulate false stories, send officials to search our homes, drag us to court, or even imprison some of us. They hope that we will be terrified because they managed to put a small number of us in prison. If we were to allow them to instill fear in our heart, we might even begin to “ban” our own worship. We would not want to become like those described at Leviticus 26:36, 37. We will not allow fear to cause us to reduce or to stop our spiritual activities. We trust completely in Jehovah and refuse to panic. ([Isa. 28:16]) We prayerfully seek Jehovah’s guidance. We know that with his backing, not even the most powerful human government can prevent us from faithfully worshipping our God. Rather than intimidate us, opposition can motivate us to serve Jehovah more fully. w19.07 9-10 ¶6-7

^ (Heb. 13:6) So that we may be of good courage and say: “Jehovah* is my helper; I will not be afraid. What can man do to me?”

See App. A5.

^ (Lev. 26:36, 37) “‘As for those who survive, I will fill their hearts with despair in the lands of their enemies; and the sound of a blowing leaf will cause them to flee, and they will flee like someone running from the sword and fall without anyone pursuing them. 37 They will stumble over one another like those running from a sword, though no one is pursuing them. You will not be able to resist your enemies.

^ (Isa. 28:16) Therefore this is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah says: “Here I am laying as a foundation in Zion a tested stone, The precious cornerstone of a sure foundation. No one exercising faith will panic.

Sunday, November 7

Preach the word.—[2 Tim. 4:2].

Even if your ministry seems to be unproductive, do not give up hope of finding potential disciples. Remember that Jesus likened disciple-making to fishing. Fishermen may spend many hours before they catch any fish. Often they work late at night or early in the morning, and sometimes they have to sail long distances. ([Luke 5:5]) In like manner, some disciple-makers spend many hours patiently “fishing” at different times and in various locations. Why? To improve their chances of meeting people. Those who put in the extra effort are often rewarded by meeting people who are interested in our message. Could you try preaching at a time of day when you are more likely to meet people or at a location where you are more likely to find them? Why does conducting Bible studies require patience? One reason is that we need to do more than help the student come to know and love the doctrines found in the Bible. We need to help the student come to know and love the Author of the Bible, Jehovah. w19.07 18-19 ¶14-15

^ (2 Tim. 4:2) Preach the word; be at it urgently in favorable times and difficult times; reprove, reprimand, exhort, with all patience and art of teaching.

^ (Luke 5:5) But in reply Simon said: “Instructor, we toiled all night and caught nothing, but at your word I will lower the nets.”

Monday, November 8

[I am] forgetting the things behind.—[Phil. 3:13].

Some of us may need to overcome feelings of guilt because of past sins. If so, why not start a personal study project that focuses on Christ’s ransom sacrifice? If we study, meditate, and pray about that upbuilding subject, we may do much to relieve unnecessary guilt. We may even stop punishing ourselves for sins that Jehovah has forgiven. Consider another lesson we can learn from Paul. Some may have given up a potentially lucrative career in order to pursue Kingdom interests. If so, can we forget the things behind by refusing to look back longingly at material opportunities we might have missed? ([Num. 11:4-6;][Eccl. 7:10]) “The things behind” might even include things that we accomplished or trials that we endured in the past. Of course, looking back on the way Jehovah has blessed and supported us over the years can draw us closer to our Father. However, we never want to become self-satisfied, imagining that our work is done.—[1 Cor. 15:58]. w19.08 3 ¶5-6

^ (Phil. 3:13) Brothers, I do not yet consider myself as having taken hold of it; but one thing is certain: Forgetting the things behind and stretching forward to the things ahead,

^ (Num. 11:4-6) The mixed crowd* who were in their midst then expressed selfish longing, and the Israelites too began to weep again and say: “Who will give us meat to eat? 5 How fondly we remember the fish that we used to eat without cost in Egypt, also the cucumbers, the watermelons, the leeks, the onions, and the garlic! 6 But now we* are withering away. We see nothing at all except this manna.”

Apparently the non-Israelites among them.

Or “our souls.”

^ (Eccl. 7:10) Do not say, “Why were the former days better than these?” for it is not out of wisdom that you ask this.

^ (1 Cor. 15:58) Therefore, my beloved brothers, be steadfast, immovable, always having plenty to do in the work of the Lord, knowing that your labor is not in vain* in connection with the Lord.

Lit., “empty.”

Monday, November 15

Sudden destruction is to be instantly on them, . . . and they will by no means escape.—[1 Thess. 5:3].

Imagine that the nations have just made their long-awaited proclamation of “peace and security.” They may boast that the world has never been so safe. The nations will want us to think that they have the world situation under control. But they have absolutely no control over what will follow. “Babylon the Great” will be destroyed! ([Rev. 17:5,][15-18]) “God [will] put it into their hearts to carry out his thought.” What is that thought? To destroy the world empire of false religion, including Christendom. God will put his thought into the hearts of “the ten horns” of the “scarlet-colored wild beast.” The ten horns represent all the political powers that support “the wild beast”—the United Nations. ([Rev. 17:3,][11-13;][18:8]) When those political powers turn on false religion, that will mark the beginning of the great tribulation. It will be a truly catastrophic world event. w19.10 14 ¶1, 3

^ (1 Thess. 5:3) Whenever it is that they are saying, “Peace and security!” then sudden destruction is to be instantly on them, just like birth pains on a pregnant woman, and they will by no means escape.

^ (Rev. 17:5) On her forehead was written a name, a mystery: “Babylon the Great, the mother of the prostitutes and of the disgusting things of the earth.”

^ (Rev. 17:15-18) He said to me: “The waters that you saw, where the prostitute is sitting, mean peoples and crowds and nations and tongues.* 16 And the ten horns that you saw and the wild beast, these will hate the prostitute and will make her devastated and naked, and they will eat up her flesh and completely burn her with fire. 17 For God put it into their hearts to carry out his thought, yes, to carry out their one thought by giving their kingdom to the wild beast, until the words of God will have been accomplished. 18 And the woman whom you saw means the great city that has a kingdom over the kings of the earth.”

Or “languages.”

^ (Rev. 17:3) And he carried me away in the power of the spirit into a wilderness. And I saw a woman sitting on a scarlet-colored wild beast that was full of blasphemous names and that had seven heads and ten horns.

^ (Rev. 17:11-13) And the wild beast that was but is not, it is also an eighth king, but it springs from the seven, and it goes off into destruction. 12 “The ten horns that you saw mean ten kings who have not yet received a kingdom, but they do receive authority as kings for one hour with the wild beast. 13 These have one thought, so they give their power and authority to the wild beast.

^ (Rev. 18:8) That is why in one day her plagues will come, death and mourning and famine, and she will be completely burned with fire, because Jehovah* God, who judged her, is strong.

See App. A5.

Wednesday, November 17

I was given a thorn in the flesh.—[2 Cor. 12:7].

The apostle Paul was saying that he faced a painful personal trial of some sort. He called this trial “an angel of Satan” that kept “slapping” (“beating,” ftn.) him. Satan or his demon angels may not directly have caused Paul’s trials, as if driving a thorn into his flesh. But when those wicked spirits noticed the “thorn,” they may have been eager to push it in deeper, so to speak, to increase Paul’s pain. What did Paul do? At first, Paul wanted to be rid of the “thorn.” He admits: “Three times I begged the Lord [Jehovah] . . . that it would depart from me.” Yet, despite Paul’s prayers, the thorn in the flesh remained. Does this mean that Jehovah did not answer Paul’s prayers? Not at all. He did answer them. Jehovah did not remove the problem, but he did give Paul the strength to endure it. Jehovah said: “My power is being made perfect in weakness.” (2 Cor. 12:8, 9) And with God’s help, Paul was able to maintain his joy and inner peace!—[Phil. 4:4-7]. w19.11 9 ¶4-5

^ (2 Cor. 12:7) just because of receiving such extraordinary revelations. To keep me from becoming overly exalted, I was given a thorn in the flesh, an angel of Satan, to keep slapping me, so that I might not be overly exalted.

^ (2 Cor. 12:8, 9) Three times I begged the Lord about this, that it would depart from me. 9 But he said to me: “My undeserved kindness is sufficient for you, for my power is being made perfect in weakness.” Most gladly, then, I will boast about my weaknesses, in order that the power of the Christ may remain over me like a tent.

^ (Phil. 4:4-7) Always rejoice in the Lord. Again I will say, Rejoice! 5 Let your reasonableness become known to all men. The Lord is near. 6 Do not be anxious over anything, but in everything by prayer and supplication along with thanksgiving, let your petitions be made known to God; 7 and the peace of God that surpasses all understanding will guard your hearts and your mental powers* by means of Christ Jesus.

Or “your minds; your thoughts.”

Thursday, November 18

Jehovah is a God who requires exclusive devotion.—[Nah. 1:2].

Jehovah deserves our exclusive devotion because he is our Creator and Life-Giver. ([Rev. 4:11]) However, we face a challenge. Even though we love and respect Jehovah, we might be lured away from giving him the exclusive devotion he deserves. In the Bible, being devoted to God implies having a deep love for him. When we are exclusively devoted to Jehovah, we will worship only him. We will not allow anyone or anything to take his place in our heart. ([Ex. 34:14]) Our devotion to Jehovah is not blind. Why not? Because it is based on the facts we have learned about him. We have come to admire his beautiful qualities. We know and agree with his likes and dislikes. We understand and support his purpose for us. We feel honored that he allows us the opportunity to be his friend. ([Ps. 25:14]) Every detail we learn about our Creator draws us closer to him.—[Jas. 4:8]. w19.10 26 ¶1-3

^ (Nah. 1:2) Jehovah is a God who requires exclusive devotion and takes vengeance; Jehovah takes vengeance and is ready to express his wrath. Jehovah takes vengeance against his foes, And he stores up wrath for his enemies.

^ (Rev. 4:11) “You are worthy, Jehovah* our God, to receive the glory and the honor and the power, because you created all things, and because of your will they came into existence and were created.”

See App. A5.

^ (Ex. 34:14) You must not bow down to another god, for Jehovah is known for* requiring exclusive devotion.* Yes, he is a God who requires exclusive devotion.

Lit., “Jehovah, his name is.”

Or “not tolerating rivals.”

^ (Ps. 25:14) Close friendship with Jehovah belongs to those who fear him, And he makes his covenant known to them.

^ (Jas. 4:8) Draw close to God, and he will draw close to you. Cleanse your hands, you sinners, and purify your hearts, you indecisive ones.

Sunday, November 21

The seventh day is a sabbath of complete rest. It is something holy to Jehovah.—[Ex. 31:15].

God’s Word states that after six “days” of creating, God paused from his works as regards the earth. ([Gen. 2:2]) Yet, Jehovah loves to work, and in other respects he “has kept working.” ([John 5:17]) The provision for the weekly Sabbath follows a pattern similar to that of Jehovah’s day of rest described in Genesis. God said that the Sabbath was a sign between him and Israel. ([Ex. 31:12-14]) The prohibition against work applied to everyone, including children, slaves, and even domestic animals. ([Ex. 20:10]) It allowed the people to give more attention to spiritual matters. Many religious leaders in Jesus’ time took an extreme, rigid view of the Sabbath day. They claimed that it was unlawful on the Sabbath even to pluck some heads of grain or to heal a person who was ill. (Mark 2:23-27;[3:2-5]) Such views did not reflect God’s thinking, and Jesus made that clear to those who would listen. w19.12 3-4 ¶8-9

^ (Ex. 31:15) Six days work may be done, but on the seventh day is a sabbath of complete rest. It is something holy to Jehovah. Anyone doing work on the Sabbath day must be put to death.

^ (Gen. 2:2) And by the seventh day, God had completed the work that he had been doing,* and he began to rest on the seventh day from all his work that he had been doing.*

Or “making.”

Or “making.”

^ (John 5:17) But he answered them: “My Father has kept working until now, and I keep working.”

^ (Ex. 31:12-14) Jehovah said further to Moses: 13 “Speak to the Israelites and tell them, ‘Especially, you are to keep my sabbaths, for it is a sign between me and you during your generations in order that you may know that I, Jehovah, am sanctifying you. 14 You must keep the Sabbath, for it is something holy to you. Whoever profanes it must be put to death. If anyone does any work on it, then that person* must be cut off* from among his people.

Or “soul.”

Or “put to death.”

^ (Ex. 20:10) but the seventh day is a sabbath to Jehovah your God. You must not do any work, neither you nor your son nor your daughter nor your slave man nor your slave girl nor your domestic animal nor your foreign resident who is inside your settlements.*

Lit., “gates.”

^ (Mark 2:23-27) Now as he was passing through the grainfields on the Sabbath, his disciples started to pluck the heads of grain as they went. 24 So the Pharisees said to him: “Look here! Why are they doing what is not lawful on the Sabbath?” 25 But he said to them: “Have you never read what David did when he was in need and he and the men with him were hungry? 26 How, in the account about A·biʹa·thar the chief priest, he entered into the house of God and ate the loaves of presentation, which it is not lawful for anybody to eat except the priests, and he also gave some to the men who were with him?” 27 Then he said to them: “The Sabbath came into existence for the sake of man, and not man for the sake of the Sabbath.

^ (Mark 3:2-5) So they were watching him closely to see whether he would cure the man on the Sabbath, in order to accuse him. 3 He said to the man with the withered* hand: “Get up and come to the center.” 4 Next he said to them: “Is it lawful on the Sabbath to do good or to do harm, to save a life or to kill?” But they kept silent. 5 After looking around at them with indignation, being thoroughly grieved at the insensibility of their hearts, he said to the man: “Stretch out your hand.” And he stretched it out, and his hand was restored.

Or “paralyzed.” Lit., “dried-up.”

Monday, November 22

Become imitators of God, as beloved children.—[Eph. 5:1].

The more we learn about the qualities that make up Jehovah’s personality, the better we will be able to imitate him. David came to know his heavenly Father well, so he was able to imitate Him when dealing with others. Because David had such a good relationship with Jehovah, he became one of Israel’s most beloved kings and the standard by which Jehovah measured other kings of Israel. ([1 Ki. 15:11;] 2 Ki. 14:1-3) What is the lesson for us? We need to be “imitators of God.” When we model our personality after his, we prove that we are his children. ([Eph. 4:24]) We will never stop learning about Jehovah. ([Eccl. 3:11]) The important thing is, not how much we know about him, but what we do with what we know. If we apply what we learn and try to imitate our loving Father, he will continue to draw close to us. ([Jas. 4:8]) Through his Word, he assures us that he will never abandon those seeking him. w19.12 20 ¶20; 21 ¶21, 23

^ (Eph. 5:1) Therefore, become imitators of God, as beloved children,

^ (1 Ki. 15:11) Aʹsa did what was right in the eyes of Jehovah, like David his forefather.

^ (2 Ki. 14:1-3) In the second year of Je·hoʹash the son of Je·hoʹa·haz the king of Israel, Am·a·ziʹah the son of King Je·hoʹash of Judah became king. 2 He was 25 years old when he became king, and he reigned for 29 years in Jerusalem. His mother’s name was Je·ho·adʹdin of Jerusalem. 3 He continued to do what was right in Jehovah’s eyes, but not like David his forefather. He did everything as Je·hoʹash his father had done.

^ (Eph. 4:24) and should put on the new personality that was created according to God’s will in true righteousness and loyalty.

^ (Eccl. 3:11) He has made everything beautiful* in its time. He has even put eternity in their heart; yet mankind will never find out the work that the true God has made from start to finish.

Or “well-arranged; proper; appropriate.”

^ (Jas. 4:8) Draw close to God, and he will draw close to you. Cleanse your hands, you sinners, and purify your hearts, you indecisive ones.

Tuesday, November 23

The heart is more treacherous than anything else.—[Jer. 17:9].

Jacob loved all his sons, but he had special affection for 17-year-old Joseph. How did Joseph’s brothers react? They became envious of him, and that envy made them bitter. So they sold Joseph into slavery and lied to their father, saying that a wild animal had killed his favorite son. Envy caused them to disrupt the peace of the family and to break their father’s heart. (Gen. 37:3, 4,[27-34]) Envy is listed among the death-dealing “works of the flesh” that can disqualify a person from inheriting God’s Kingdom. ([Gal. 5:19-21]) Envy is often the root cause of such poisonous fruits as hostility, strife, and fits of anger. The example of Joseph’s brothers shows how envy can damage relationships and disturb the peace that once existed in a family. Although we would never do what Joseph’s brothers did, we all have an imperfect and treacherous heart. Little wonder, then, that we may at times struggle with feelings of envy. w20.02 14 ¶1-3

^ (Jer. 17:9) The heart is more treacherous* than anything else and is desperate.* Who can know it?

Or “deceitful.”

Or possibly, “incurable.”

^ (Gen. 37:3, 4) Now Israel loved Joseph more than all his other sons because he was the son of his old age, and he had a special robe* made for him. 4 When his brothers saw that their father loved him more than all his brothers, they began to hate him, and they could not speak peaceably to him.

Or “a beautiful long garment.”

^ (Gen. 37:27-34) Come, now, let us sell him to the Ishʹma·el·ites, and do not let our hand be upon him. After all, he is our brother, our flesh.” So they listened to their brother. 28 And when the Midʹi·an·ite merchants were passing by, they lifted Joseph up out of the waterpit and sold him to the Ishʹma·el·ites for 20 pieces of silver. These men took Joseph into Egypt. 29 Later when Reuʹben returned to the waterpit and saw that Joseph was not in the waterpit, he ripped his garments apart. 30 When he returned to his brothers, he exclaimed: “The child is gone! And I—what am I going to do?” 31 So they took Joseph’s robe and slaughtered a male goat and dipped the robe in the blood. 32 After that they sent the special robe to their father and said: “This is what we found. Please examine whether this is your son’s robe or not.” 33 Then he examined it and exclaimed: “It is my son’s robe! A vicious wild animal must have devoured him! Joseph is surely torn to pieces!” 34 With that Jacob ripped his garments apart and put sackcloth around his waist and mourned his son for many days.

^ (Gal. 5:19-21) Now the works of the flesh are plainly seen, and they are sexual immorality,* uncleanness, brazen conduct,* 20 idolatry, spiritism,* hostility, strife, jealousy, fits of anger, dissensions, divisions, sects, 21 envy, drunkenness, wild parties,* and things like these. I am forewarning you about these things, the same way I already warned you, that those who practice such things will not inherit God’s Kingdom.

Greek, por·neiʹa. See Glossary.

Or “shameless conduct.” Greek, a·selʹgei·a. See Glossary.

Or “sorcery; druggery.”

Or “revelries.”

Wednesday, November 24

With humility consider others superior to you.—[Phil. 2:3].

On one occasion, Jehovah took away some of his holy spirit from Moses and gave it to a group of Israelite elders who were standing near the tent of meeting. Shortly thereafter, Moses heard that two elders who had not gone out to the tent of meeting had also received holy spirit and had begun to behave as prophets. How did he react when Joshua asked him to restrain the two elders? Moses did not become envious of the attention these two men were getting from Jehovah. Instead, he humbly rejoiced with them in their privilege. (Num. 11:24-29) What lesson can we learn from Moses? If you are an elder, have you ever been asked to train someone else to care for a privilege in the congregation that you have and truly love? If you are humble like Moses, you will not feel threatened if you are asked to train another brother so that, in time, he will be able to handle this privilege. Instead, you will be happy to help your brother. w20.02 15 ¶9; 17 ¶10-11

^ (Phil. 2:3) Do nothing out of contentiousness or out of egotism, but with humility* consider others superior to you,

Or “lowliness of mind.”

^ (Num. 11:24-29) So Moses went out and spoke the words of Jehovah to the people. And he gathered 70 men from the elders of the people and had them stand around the tent. 25 Then Jehovah came down in a cloud and spoke to him and took away some of the spirit that was on him and put it on each of the 70 elders. And as soon as the spirit settled down on them, they began to behave as prophets,* but they did not do it again. 26 There were two of the men still in the camp. Their names were Elʹdad and Meʹdad. And the spirit began to settle down on them, as they were among those whose names had been written down, but they had not gone out to the tent. So they began to behave as prophets in the camp. 27 And a young man ran and reported to Moses: “Elʹdad and Meʹdad are behaving as prophets in the camp!” 28 Then Joshua the son of Nun, the minister of Moses from his youth, responded and said: “My lord Moses, restrain them!” 29 But Moses said to him: “Are you jealous for me? No, I wish that all of Jehovah’s people were prophets and that Jehovah would put his spirit on them!”

Or “began to prophesy.”

Thursday, November 25

Anxiety in a man’s heart weighs it down, but a good word cheers it up.—[Prov. 12:25].

Illness can take an emotional toll on us. We may feel embarrassed when people notice our limitations or when we must rely on others for help. Even when others are not aware of our illness, we may fight feelings of shame because of how limited we have become. At such distressing times, Jehovah lifts us up. How? In the Bible, Jehovah has stored up good words that remind us that we matter to him despite our sickness. ([Ps. 31:19;][41:3]) Through those inspired words, Jehovah will help us to deal with the negative emotions that our illness brings. Be assured that Jehovah knows what you are going through. Beg him for help so that you can develop a wholesome view of your situation. Then use the Bible to retrieve the good words Jehovah has stored up for you. Focus on passages that show how much Jehovah values his servants. As you do, you will see that Jehovah is good to all those who serve him faithfully.—[Ps. 84:11]. w20.01 15-16 ¶9-10; 17 ¶12

^ (Prov. 12:25) Anxiety in a man’s heart weighs it down,* But a good word cheers it up.

Or “depresses him.”

^ (Ps. 31:19) How abundant your goodness is! You have stored it up for those who fear you, And you have shown it before all men, in behalf of those taking refuge in you.

^ (Ps. 41:3) Jehovah will sustain him on his sickbed; During his sickness you will completely change his bed.

^ (Ps. 84:11) For Jehovah God is a sun and a shield; He gives favor and glory. Jehovah will not hold back anything good From those walking in integrity.

Saturday, November 27

He is to be put to death.—[Esther 4:11].

Imagine that you are living some 2,500 years ago in Persia and want to speak to the king. You would not even think of approaching the monarch without first receiving his permission. To do otherwise could very well cost you your life! How thankful we are that Jehovah is not like that Persian king! He welcomes us at any time. He wants us to feel free to approach him. For example, although Jehovah bears such lofty titles as Grand Creator, Almighty, and Sovereign Lord, we are invited to call on him using the familiar term “Father.” ([Matt. 6:9]) How touching that Jehovah wants us to view him in such a warm and intimate way! We can rightly call Jehovah “Father”—he is the Source of our life. ([Ps. 36:9]) Because he is our Father, we have a responsibility to obey him. When we do what he asks of us, we will enjoy marvelous blessings. ([Heb. 12:9]) Those blessings include everlasting life, whether in heaven or on earth. w20.02 2 ¶1-3

^ (Esther 4:11) “All the king’s servants and the people of the king’s provinces* are aware that if any man or woman goes into the king’s inner courtyard without being summoned, there is only one law that applies: He is to be put to death; he may live only if the king holds out to him the golden scepter. And I have not been summoned to the king now for 30 days.”

Or “jurisdictional districts.”

^ (Matt. 6:9) “You must pray, then, this way: “‘Our Father in the heavens, let your name be sanctified.

^ (Ps. 36:9) With you is the source of life; By your light we can see light.

^ (Heb. 12:9) Furthermore, our human fathers* used to discipline us, and we gave them respect. Should we not more readily submit ourselves to the Father of our spiritual life and live?

Lit., “the fathers of our flesh.”

Monday, November 29

I confessed my sin to you; I did not cover my error. . . . And you pardoned the error of my sins.—[Ps. 32:5].

We show that we appreciate Jehovah’s forgiveness when we pray for it, accept discipline, and work hard to avoid repeating our mistakes. When we take these steps, we will regain our inner peace. How encouraging it is to know that “Jehovah is close to the brokenhearted; he saves those who are crushed in spirit”! ([Ps. 34:18]) As these last days come to a close, the causes of anxiety are likely to increase. When you have anxious thoughts, do not delay in seeking Jehovah’s help. Study the Bible diligently. Learn from the examples set by Hannah, the apostle Paul, and King David. Ask your heavenly Father to help you identify the cause of your anxiety. ([Ps. 139:23]) Let him carry your burdens, especially those over which you have little or no control. If you do, you can be like the psalmist who sang to Jehovah: “When anxieties overwhelmed me, you comforted and soothed me.”—[Ps. 94:19]. w20.02 24 ¶17; 25 ¶20-21

^ (Ps. 32:5) Finally I confessed my sin to you; I did not cover my error. I said: “I will confess my transgressions to Jehovah.” And you pardoned the error of my sins. (Selah)

^ (Ps. 34:18) Jehovah is close to the brokenhearted; He saves those who are crushed in spirit.*

Or “are discouraged.”

^ (Ps. 139:23) Search through me, O God, and know my heart. Examine me, and know my anxious* thoughts.

Or “disquieting.”

^ (Ps. 94:19) When anxieties* overwhelmed me,* You comforted and soothed me.*

Or “disquieting thoughts.”

Or “became many inside of me.”

Or “Your consolations soothed my soul.”

Friday, December 3

When I was a child, I used to speak as a child, to think as a child, to reason as a child.—[1 Cor. 13:11].

Children are not fully developed in their ability to think, to reason, or to recognize and avoid danger. So it is all too easy for devious abusers to deceive children. Abusers teach children dangerous lies, such as the idea that the child is to blame, that the abuse must be kept secret, that no one will listen or care if the child reports the abuse, or that sexual acts between an adult and a child are actually normal expressions of sincere love. Such lies can distort a child’s thinking ability and perception of truth for many years. Such a child may grow up thinking of herself or himself as damaged, defiled, and unworthy of love or comfort. It is not surprising, then, that sexual abuse can cause lasting harm. We are living in the last days, a time when many have “no natural affection” and when “wicked men and impostors will advance from bad to worse.”—2 Tim. 3:1-5,[13]. w19.05 15 ¶7-8

^ (1 Cor. 13:11) When I was a child, I used to speak as a child, to think as a child, to reason as a child; but now that I have become a man, I have done away with the traits of a child.

^ (2 Tim. 3:1-5) But know this, that in the last days critical times hard to deal with will be here. 2 For men will be lovers of themselves, lovers of money, boastful, haughty, blasphemers, disobedient to parents, unthankful, disloyal, 3 having no natural affection, not open to any agreement, slanderers, without self-control, fierce, without love of goodness, 4 betrayers, headstrong, puffed up with pride, lovers of pleasures rather than lovers of God, 5 having an appearance of godliness but proving false to its power; and from these turn away.

^ (2 Tim. 3:13) But wicked men and impostors will advance from bad to worse, misleading and being misled.

Sunday, December 5

Make sure of the more important things.—[Phil. 1:10].

It takes a great deal of effort to earn a living these days. Many of our brothers work long hours just to provide the necessities of life for their families. Countless others spend several hours each workday traveling to and from their place of employment. Many support themselves by doing hard physical labor. By the end of the day, these hardworking brothers and sisters are exhausted! The last thing many are inclined to do is study. The fact is, though, that we must find time to study—really study—God’s Word and our Christian publications. Our relationship with Jehovah and our everlasting life depend on it! ([1 Tim. 4:15]) Some rise early every day and study when their home is quiet and their mind is fresh after a night’s rest. Others set aside a few tranquil minutes at the end of the day to take in spiritual food and meditate on it. w19.05 26 ¶1-2

^ (Phil. 1:10) that you may make sure of the more important things, so that you may be flawless and not stumbling others up to the day of Christ;

^ (1 Tim. 4:15) Ponder over* these things; be absorbed in them, so that your advancement may be plainly seen by all people.

Or “Meditate on.”

Monday, December 6

Stop being molded by this system of things, but be transformed by making your mind over.—[Rom. 12:2].

These changes do not take place overnight; nor do they occur automatically. We may need to exert “earnest effort” over a period of years. ([2 Pet. 1:5]) We must do our utmost to change our inner self. Prayer is the important first step. We need to pray as did the psalmist: “Create in me a pure heart, O God, and put within me a new spirit, a steadfast one.” ([Ps. 51:10]) We must acknowledge the need to change our dominant mental attitude and ask Jehovah for help. Meditation is the second vital step. As we peer into God’s Word each day, we need to take the time to meditate, or to think deeply, on what thoughts and feelings we need to change. ([Ps. 119:59;][Heb. 4:12;][Jas. 1:25]) We must identify any tendencies we may have to be attracted to human philosophies. We need to admit honestly what our weaknesses are and then work hard to get rid of those weaknesses. w19.06 8 ¶1; 10 ¶10; 12 ¶11-12

^ (Rom. 12:2) And stop being molded by this system of things, but be transformed by making your mind over, so that you may prove to yourselves the good and acceptable and perfect will of God.

^ (2 Pet. 1:5) For this very reason, put forth all earnest effort to supply to your faith virtue, to your virtue knowledge,

^ (Ps. 51:10) Create in me a pure heart, O God, And put within me a new spirit, a steadfast one.

^ (Ps. 119:59) I have examined my ways, In order to turn my feet back to your reminders.

^ (Heb. 4:12) For the word of God is alive and exerts power and is sharper than any two-edged sword and pierces even to the dividing of soul* and spirit,* and of joints from the marrow, and is able to discern thoughts and intentions of the heart.

See Glossary.

See Glossary.

^ (Jas. 1:25) But the one who peers into the perfect law that belongs to freedom and continues in it has become, not a forgetful hearer, but a doer of the work; and he will be happy in what he does.

Tuesday, December 7

[Make] the best use of your time.—[Eph. 5:16].

When making decisions, you must choose a time to implement your decision and stick to it. Avoid waiting for the perfect time to act; the perfect time is not likely to come. ([Eccl. 11:4]) Be careful not to allow less important things to consume your time and rob you of the energy you need for the more important things. ([Phil. 1:10]) If possible, set aside time during which you have few interruptions. Let others know that you need time to concentrate. Consider turning off your phone and checking your e-mail or social media at a later time. The result, or outcome, of your decision is like the destination of a journey. If you really want to reach that destination, you will keep going even if a road is closed and you thus must change your route. In the same way, if we focus on the outcome of our decisions, we will not give up easily when we encounter setbacks or detours.—[Gal. 6:9]. w19.11 30 ¶17-18

^ (Eph. 5:16) making the best use of your time,* because the days are wicked.

Lit., “buying out the appointed time.”

^ (Eccl. 11:4) The one who watches the wind will not sow seed, and the one who looks at the clouds will not reap.

^ (Phil. 1:10) that you may make sure of the more important things, so that you may be flawless and not stumbling others up to the day of Christ;

^ (Gal. 6:9) So let us not give up in doing what is fine, for in due time we will reap if we do not tire out.*

Or “give up.”

Wednesday, December 8

The word of God . . . is able to discern thoughts and intentions of the heart.—[Heb. 4:12].

What should be the basis for your decision to get baptized? As a result of your careful study of the Bible, you have learned much about Jehovah—his personality and his ways. What you have learned about him has warmed your heart and moved you to love him very much. Your love for Jehovah must be the primary basis for your decision to get baptized. Your decision to get baptized is also based on the Bible truths you have accepted. Consider what Jesus said when he gave the commission to make disciples. (Matt. 28:19, 20) According to Jesus, those who get baptized must do so “in the name of the Father and of the Son and of the holy spirit.” What did this mean? You must believe with all your heart the Bible truths about Jehovah; his Son, Jesus; and the holy spirit. These truths are very powerful and can deeply touch your heart. w20.03 9 ¶8-9

^ (Heb. 4:12) For the word of God is alive and exerts power and is sharper than any two-edged sword and pierces even to the dividing of soul* and spirit,* and of joints from the marrow, and is able to discern thoughts and intentions of the heart.

See Glossary.

See Glossary.

^ (Matt. 28:19, 20) Go, therefore, and make disciples of people of all the nations, baptizing them in the name of the Father and of the Son and of the holy spirit, 20 teaching them to observe all the things I have commanded you. And look! I am with you all the days until the conclusion of the system of things.”

Friday, December 10

Each one will carry his own load.—[Gal. 6:5].

If the government where you live bans our worship, you may wonder if you should move to a country where you can serve Jehovah freely. This is a personal decision that no one else can make for you. Some might find it helpful to consider what Christians in the first century did when they were persecuted. The disciples in Jerusalem moved throughout Judea and Samaria and even as far as Phoenicia, Cyprus, and Antioch. ([Matt. 10:23;][Acts 8:1;][11:19]) However, after another wave of persecution afflicted the first-century Christians, the apostle Paul decided not to move away from areas where the preaching work was opposed. (Acts 14:19-23) What do we learn from these accounts? Each family head must make a personal decision about moving. Before deciding, he should prayerfully and carefully consider his family’s circumstances and the positive and negative effects a move might have on them. We should not judge others for the decision that they make. w19.07 10 ¶8-9

^ (Gal. 6:5) For each one will carry his own load.*

Or “load of responsibility.”

^ (Matt. 10:23) When they persecute you in one city, flee to another; for truly I say to you, you will by no means complete the circuit of the cities of Israel until the Son of man arrives.

^ (Acts 8:1) Saul, for his part, approved of his murder. On that day great persecution arose against the congregation that was in Jerusalem; all except the apostles were scattered throughout the regions of Ju·deʹa and Sa·marʹi·a.

^ (Acts 11:19) Now those who had been scattered by the tribulation that arose over Stephen went as far as Phoe·niʹcia, Cyʹprus, and Antioch, but they spoke the word only to the Jews.

^ (Acts 14:19-23) But Jews arrived from Antioch and I·coʹni·um and persuaded the crowds, and they stoned Paul and dragged him outside the city, imagining that he was dead. 20 However, when the disciples surrounded him, he got up and entered the city. On the next day he left with Barʹna·bas for Derʹbe. 21 After declaring the good news to that city and making quite a few disciples, they returned to Lysʹtra, I·coʹni·um, and Antioch. 22 There they strengthened the disciples, encouraging them to remain in the faith and saying: “We must enter into the Kingdom of God through many tribulations.” 23 Moreover, they appointed elders for them in each congregation, offering prayer with fasting, and they entrusted them to Jehovah, in whom they had become believers.

Saturday, December 11

This means everlasting life, their coming to know you, the only true God, and the one whom you sent, Jesus Christ.—[John 17:3].

Jesus told us to “go . . . make disciples of people of all the nations.” ([Matt. 28:19]) And in addition to teaching a student what Jesus requires of his disciples, we need to help the student come to know how to live as a true Christian. We must patiently assist him as he struggles to put Bible principles into practice. Some are able to change their thinking and habits in just a few months; others take longer. A missionary in Peru had an experience that illustrates the benefit of being patient. “I had studied two books with a Bible student named Raúl,” says the missionary. “But he still faced serious challenges in his life. He had a stormy marriage, used foul language, and had children who found it difficult to respect him. He came to the meetings regularly, so I continued visiting him to help him and his family. More than three years after I met him, he qualified for baptism.” w19.07 15 ¶3; 19 ¶15-17

^ (John 17:3) This means everlasting life, their coming to know you, the only true God, and the one whom you sent, Jesus Christ.

^ (Matt. 28:19) Go, therefore, and make disciples of people of all the nations, baptizing them in the name of the Father and of the Son and of the holy spirit,

Sunday, December 12

Exert yourselves vigorously.—[Luke 13:24].

Consider how the apostle Paul was exerting himself when he wrote to the Philippians. He was under house arrest in Rome. His freedom to preach was severely limited. Yet, he kept busy by witnessing to visitors and writing letters to distant congregations. Paul knew that, like Christ, he must exert himself to the very end. He thus compared the Christian course to a race. (1 Cor. 9:24-27) A runner in a race stays focused on the finish line and avoids distractions. For example, runners in an urban race today may follow a course that is lined with businesses and other potential diversions. Can you imagine that a runner would stop to examine the goods displayed in the store windows? Not if he wants to win! In the race for life, we too must avoid distractions. If we stay focused on our goal, exerting ourselves vigorously as Paul did, we will win the prize! w19.08 3 ¶4; 4 ¶7

^ (Luke 13:24) “Exert yourselves vigorously to get in through the narrow door, because many, I tell you, will seek to get in but will not be able.

^ (1 Cor. 9:24-27) Do you not know that the runners in a race all run, but only one receives the prize? Run in such a way that you may win it. 25 Now everyone competing in a contest exercises self-control in all things. Of course, they do it to receive a crown that can perish, but we, one that does not perish. 26 Therefore, the way I am running is not aimlessly; the way I am aiming my blows is so as not to be striking the air; 27 but I pummel my body and lead it as a slave, so that after I have preached to others, I myself should not become disapproved* somehow.

Or “disqualified.”

Monday, December 13

Pay constant attention to yourself and to your teaching. . . . By doing this you will save both yourself and those who listen to you.—[1 Tim. 4:16].

When we conform our life to God’s standards, our relatives may find it difficult to adjust to our new beliefs and lifestyle. Often, the first thing they notice is that we no longer join with them in celebrating religious festivals and no longer engage in political activities. Some relatives might initially be angry with us. (Matt. 10:35, 36) But we should not give up on them. If we stop trying to help them understand our beliefs, we have, in effect, judged them as being unworthy of gaining everlasting life. Jehovah has not given us the job of judging—he has assigned that task to Jesus. ([John 5:22]) If we are patient, our relatives may eventually be willing to listen to our message. We need to be firm but tactful, even if we must endure trials. ([1 Cor. 4:12b]) It may take time before our relatives fully understand just how serious we are about serving Jehovah. w19.08 17 ¶10, 13; 18 ¶14

^ (1 Tim. 4:16) Pay constant attention to yourself and to your teaching. Persevere in these things, for by doing this you will save both yourself and those who listen to you.

^ (Matt. 10:35, 36) For I came to cause division, with a man against his father, and a daughter against her mother, and a daughter-in-law against her mother-in-law. 36 Indeed, a man’s enemies will be those of his own household.

^ (John 5:22) For the Father judges no one at all, but he has entrusted all the judging to the Son,

^ (1 Cor. 4:12) and to toil, working with our own hands. When insulted, we bless; when persecuted, we patiently endure;

Tuesday, December 14

For all things I have the strength through the one who gives me power.—[Phil. 4:13].

“When I think about the trial I have gone through, I know that I could not have faced it on my own.” Have you ever said something like that? Many of us have. Perhaps you said it after reflecting on how you were able to cope with a serious illness or the death of a loved one. Looking back, you feel that you were able to go on from day to day only because Jehovah’s holy spirit provided you with “power beyond what is normal.” ([2 Cor. 4:7-9]) We also rely on holy spirit to deal with the influence of this wicked world. ([1 John 5:19]) In addition, we have to struggle against “wicked spirit forces.” ([Eph. 6:12]) Jehovah’s holy spirit helps us by giving us the power, or strength, to fulfill our responsibilities despite trials. The apostle Paul felt that he was able to keep working and to accomplish his ministry despite his trials because he relied on “the power of the Christ.”—[2 Cor. 12:9]. w19.11 8 ¶1-3

^ (Phil. 4:13) For all things I have the strength through the one who gives me power.

^ (2 Cor. 4:7-9) However, we have this treasure in earthen vessels, so that the power beyond what is normal may be God’s and not from us. 8 We are hard-pressed in every way, but not cramped beyond movement; we are perplexed, but not absolutely with no way out;* 9 we are persecuted, but not abandoned; we are knocked down, but not destroyed.

Or possibly, “but not left in despair.”

^ (1 John 5:19) We know that we originate with God, but the whole world is lying in the power of the wicked one.

^ (Eph. 6:12) because we have a struggle,* not against blood and flesh, but against the governments, against the authorities, against the world rulers of this darkness, against the wicked spirit forces in the heavenly places.

Lit., “wrestling.”

^ (2 Cor. 12:9) But he said to me: “My undeserved kindness is sufficient for you, for my power is being made perfect in weakness.” Most gladly, then, I will boast about my weaknesses, in order that the power of the Christ may remain over me like a tent.

Wednesday, December 15

Whoever has seen me has seen the Father also.—[John 14:9].

The Bible is the only accurate record that explains what Jesus has done for you. Learn to love Jesus, and your love for Jehovah will grow. Why? Because Jesus reflects his Father’s qualities perfectly. So the more you learn about Jesus, the better you will understand and appreciate Jehovah. Think of the compassion Jesus showed for those who were looked down on by others—the poor, the sick, and the vulnerable. Think, too, of the practical advice he gives you and how your life improves when you listen to him. (Matt. 5:1-11;[7:24-27]) Your affection for Jesus is likely to become stronger as you think deeply about the sacrifice he made so that our sins can be forgiven. ([Matt. 20:28]) When you understand that Jesus was willing to die for you, you may feel moved to repent and seek Jehovah’s forgiveness. (Acts 3:19, 20;[1 John 1:9]) And as you come to love Jesus and Jehovah, you will naturally be drawn to others who feel the same way. w20.03 5-6 ¶10-12

^ (John 14:9) Jesus said to him: “Even after I have been with you men for such a long time, Philip, have you not come to know me? Whoever has seen me has seen the Father also. How is it you say, ‘Show us the Father’?

^ (Matt. 7:24-27) “Therefore, everyone who hears these sayings of mine and does them will be like a discreet man who built his house on the rock. 25 And the rain poured down and the floods came and the winds blew and lashed against that house, but it did not cave in, for it had been founded on the rock. 26 Furthermore, everyone hearing these sayings of mine and not doing them will be like a foolish man who built his house on the sand. 27 And the rain poured down and the floods came and the winds blew and struck against that house, and it caved in, and its collapse was great.”

^ (Matt. 20:28) Just as the Son of man came, not to be ministered to, but to minister and to give his life as a ransom in exchange for many.”

^ (Acts 3:19, 20) “Repent, therefore, and turn around so as to get your sins blotted out, so that seasons of refreshing may come from Jehovah himself 20 and he may send the Christ appointed for you, Jesus.

^ (1 John 1:9) If we confess our sins, he is faithful and righteous so as to forgive us our sins and to cleanse us from all unrighteousness.

Friday, December 17

Jehovah protects the faithful.—[Ps. 31:23].

We do not know what reasons the nations might give to justify their attack on Babylon the Great. They might say that the world’s religions are an obstacle to peace and that they constantly meddle in politics. Or they might say that those religious organizations have accumulated too much wealth and property. ([Rev. 18:3,][7]) It seems reasonable that this attack will not mean that all the members of those religions will be destroyed. Rather, it seems that the nations will get rid of the religious organizations. Once those organizations are gone, the former members will realize that their religious leaders failed them and will likely try to distance themselves from those religions. The destruction of Babylon the Great will take place within a relatively brief time. ([Rev. 18:10,][21]) Jehovah has promised that he will “cut short the days” of the tribulation so that his “chosen ones” and true religion will survive.—Mark 13:19, 20. w19.10 15 ¶4-5

^ (Ps. 31:23) Love Jehovah, all you who are loyal to him! Jehovah protects the faithful, But he repays exceedingly anyone showing haughtiness.

^ (Rev. 18:3) For because of the wine of the passion* of her sexual immorality,* all the nations have fallen victim, and the kings of the earth committed sexual immorality with her, and the merchants* of the earth became rich owing to the power of her shameless luxury.”

Or “anger.”

Greek, por·neiʹa. See Glossary.

Or “traveling merchants.”

^ (Rev. 18:7) To the extent that she glorified herself and lived in shameless luxury, to that extent give her torment and mourning. For she keeps saying in her heart: ‘I sit as queen, and I am not a widow, and I will never see mourning.’

^ (Rev. 18:10) They will stand at a distance because of their fear of her torment and say: ‘Too bad, too bad, you great city, Babylon you strong city, because in one hour your judgment has arrived!’

^ (Rev. 18:21) And a strong angel lifted up a stone like a great millstone and hurled it into the sea, saying: “Thus with a swift pitch will Babylon the great city be hurled down, and she will never be found again.

^ (Mark 13:19, 20) for those days will be days of a tribulation such as has not occurred from the beginning of the creation that God created until that time,* and will not occur again. 20 In fact, unless Jehovah had cut short the days, no flesh would be saved. But on account of the chosen ones whom he has chosen, he has cut short the days.

Lit., “until the present time; until now.”

Saturday, December 18

Advise the younger women . . . to love their children.—[Titus 2:4].

Mothers, you may have been raised by parents who easily lost their temper and spoke harshly to their children. So you may have grown up thinking that this was a normal way to raise a family. Even after learning Jehovah’s standards, you might find it a challenge to remain calm and patient with your children, especially if they misbehave when you are tired. ([Eph. 4:31]) At such times, you need more than ever to rely on Jehovah in prayer. ([Ps. 37:5]) Some mothers find it difficult to express their love for their children. They may have been raised in a household where their parents did not have a warm relationship with their children. If that is how you were raised, you do not have to repeat your parents’ mistakes. A mother who submits to Jehovah’s will may have to learn how to express love for her children. It may be difficult for her to make the change. But it can be done, and it will benefit both her and her family. w19.09 18-19 ¶19-20

^ (Titus 2:4) so that they may advise* the younger women to love their husbands, to love their children,

Or “recall to their senses; train.”

^ (Eph. 4:31) Put away from yourselves every kind of malicious bitterness, anger, wrath, screaming, and abusive speech, as well as everything injurious.

^ (Ps. 37:5) Commit your way to* Jehovah; Rely on him, and he will act in your behalf.

Lit., “Roll your way upon.”

Tuesday, December 21

If you become discouraged in the day of distress, your strength will be meager.—[Prov. 24:10].

At times we may feel discouraged. But we must not allow our problems to dominate our thinking. If we do, we might lose sight of the marvelous hope that Jehovah has given us. ([Rev. 21:3, 4]) Feelings of discouragement could then drain our strength and cause us to give up. Consider how a sister in the United States is maintaining her faith while caring for her seriously ill husband. She wrote: “Our situation has been stressful and discouraging at times, but our hope is strong. I am so very impressed with the information we have been getting to strengthen our faith and lift our spirits. We really need this counsel and encouragement. It keeps us going and helps us to endure.” We learn from this sister’s comments that we can overcome discouragement! How? View your trials as being a test from Satan. Recognize Jehovah as being the Source of comfort. And appreciate the spiritual food he provides. w19.11 16 ¶9-10

^ (Prov. 24:10) If you become discouraged in the day of distress,* Your strength will be meager.

Or “in times of trouble.”

^ (Rev. 21:3, 4) With that I heard a loud voice from the throne say: “Look! The tent of God is with mankind, and he will reside with them, and they will be his people. And God himself will be with them. 4 And he will wipe out every tear from their eyes, and death will be no more, neither will mourning nor outcry nor pain be anymore. The former things have passed away.”

Thursday, December 23

Jehovah will appear to you.—[Lev. 9:4].

In 1512 B.C.E., when the tabernacle was set up at the foot of Mount Sinai, Moses presided over a ceremony to install Aaron and his sons as priests. ([Ex. 40:17;][Lev. 9:1-5]) How did Jehovah show his approval of the newly installed priesthood? As Aaron and Moses blessed the people, Jehovah caused fire to consume the remainder of the sacrifice on the altar. (Lev. 9:23, 24) What was accomplished by the awesome display at the installation of the high priest? Jehovah thereby showed his full support of the Aaronic priesthood. When the Israelites saw this clear evidence of Jehovah’s backing of the priests, they had good reason to give them full support. Is that relevant to us? Yes! The priesthood in Israel was just a shadow of a much greater priesthood—the 144,000, who will serve alongside Christ in heaven. ([Heb. 4:14;][8:3-5;][10:1]) Without a doubt, Jehovah is guiding and generously blessing his organization today. w19.11 23 ¶13; 24 ¶14, 16

^ (Lev. 9:4) and a bull and a ram for communion sacrifices, to sacrifice them before Jehovah, and a grain offering mixed with oil, for today Jehovah will appear to you.’”

^ (Ex. 40:17) In the first month, in the second year, on the first day of the month, the tabernacle was set up.

^ (Lev. 9:1-5) On the eighth day, Moses called Aaron and his sons and the elders of Israel. 2 He said to Aaron: “Take for yourself a young calf for a sin offering and a ram for a burnt offering, sound ones, and present them before Jehovah. 3 But you will say to the Israelites, ‘Take a male goat for a sin offering and a calf and a young ram, each a year old, sound ones, for a burnt offering, 4 and a bull and a ram for communion sacrifices, to sacrifice them before Jehovah, and a grain offering mixed with oil, for today Jehovah will appear to you.’” 5 So they took what Moses had commanded before the tent of meeting. Then the whole assembly came forward and stood before Jehovah.

^ (Lev. 9:23, 24) Finally Moses and Aaron went into the tent of meeting and came out and blessed the people. Jehovah’s glory now appeared to all the people, 24 and fire came out from Jehovah and began consuming the burnt offering and the pieces of fat on the altar. When all the people saw it, they started shouting and they fell with their faces to the ground.

^ (Heb. 4:14) Therefore, since we have a great high priest who has passed through the heavens, Jesus the Son of God, let us hold on to our public declaration of him.

^ (Heb. 8:3-5) For every high priest is appointed to offer both gifts and sacrifices; so it was necessary for this one also to have something to offer. 4 If he were on earth, he would not be a priest, since there are already men who offer the gifts according to the Law. 5 These men are offering sacred service in a typical representation and a shadow of the heavenly things; just as Moses, when about to construct the tent, was given the divine command: For He says: “See that you make all things after their pattern that was shown to you in the mountain.”

^ (Heb. 10:1) For since the Law has a shadow of the good things to come, but not the very substance of the things, it* can never, by the same sacrifices that are continually offered year after year, make those who approach perfect.

Or possibly, “men.”

Sunday, December 26

You must pray, then, this way: “Our Father.”—[Matt. 6:9].

Do you find it difficult to think of God as your Father? Some may feel small and insignificant in comparison to Jehovah. They doubt that Almighty God cares about them as individuals. Yet, our loving Father does not want us to feel that way. He gave us life and wants us to have a relationship with him. After stating this truth, the apostle Paul explained to his listeners in Athens that Jehovah “is not far off from each one of us.” (Acts 17:24-29) God wants each one of us to go to him just as a child naturally goes to a loving and caring parent. Others may find it hard to view Jehovah as their Father because their own human father showed them little or no love and affection. One Christian sister says: “My father was very abusive. When I first began to study the Bible, it was difficult for me to relate to a heavenly Father.” Do you have similar feelings? If so, be assured that you too can come to see Jehovah as the best possible Father. w20.02 3 ¶4-5

^ (Matt. 6:9) “You must pray, then, this way: “‘Our Father in the heavens, let your name be sanctified.

^ (Acts 17:24-29) The God who made the world and all the things in it, being, as he is, Lord of heaven and earth, does not dwell in handmade temples; 25 nor is he served by human hands as if he needed anything, because he himself gives to all people life and breath and all things. 26 And he made out of one man every nation of men to dwell on the entire surface of the earth, and he decreed the appointed times and the set limits of where men would dwell, 27 so that they would seek God, if they might grope for him and really find him, although, in fact, he is not far off from each one of us. 28 For by* him we have life and move and exist, even as some of your own poets have said, ‘For we are also his children.’* 29 “Therefore, since we are the children* of God, we should not think that the Divine Being is like gold or silver or stone, like something sculptured by the art and design of humans.

Or “because of.” Lit., “in.”

Or “progeny.”

Or “progeny.”

Monday, December 27

Do not abandon me when my strength fails.—[Ps. 71:9].

Jesus taught us that no matter how limited our abilities or how small our efforts seem to us as we get older, Jehovah treasures whatever we can do in his service. (Ps. 92:12-15;[Luke 21:2-4]) So focus on what you can do. You can, for example, speak about Jehovah, pray for your brothers, and encourage others to stay faithful. Jehovah considers you to be his fellow worker, not because of what you accomplish, but because of your willing obedience to him. ([1 Cor. 3:5-9]) How grateful we are to worship Jehovah, a God who truly values those who serve him! He created us to do his will, and it is true worship that adds real meaning to our lives. ([Rev. 4:11]) Though the world may view us as worthless, Jehovah is not ashamed of us. ([Heb. 11:16,][38]) When we feel weighed down by illness, economic hardship, or old age, let us remember that nothing can separate us from the love of our heavenly Father.—Rom. 8:38, 39. w20.01 18 ¶16; 19 ¶18-19

^ (Ps. 71:9) Do not cast me off in my old age; Do not abandon me when my strength fails.

^ (Ps. 92:12-15) But the righteous will flourish like a palm tree And grow big like a cedar in Lebʹa·non. 13 They are planted in the house of Jehovah; They flourish in the courtyards of our God. 14 Even in old age* they will still be thriving; They will remain vigorous* and fresh, 15 Declaring that Jehovah is upright. He is my Rock, in whom there is no unrighteousness.

Or “during gray-headedness.”

Lit., “fat.”

^ (Luke 21:2-4) Then he saw a needy widow drop in two small coins of very little value, 3 and he said: “Truly I say to you that this poor widow put in more than they all did. 4 For all of these put in gifts* out of their surplus, but she, out of her want,* put in all the means of living she had.”

Or “contributed to the gifts.”

Or “poverty.”

^ (1 Cor. 3:5-9) What, then, is A·polʹlos? Yes, what is Paul? Ministers through whom you became believers, just as the Lord granted each one. 6 I planted, A·polʹlos watered, but God kept making it grow, 7 so that neither is the one who plants anything nor is the one who waters, but God who makes it grow. 8 Now the one who plants and the one who waters are one, but each person will receive his own reward according to his own work. 9 For we are God’s fellow workers. You are God’s field under cultivation, God’s building.

^ (Rev. 4:11) “You are worthy, Jehovah* our God, to receive the glory and the honor and the power, because you created all things, and because of your will they came into existence and were created.”

See App. A5.

^ (Heb. 11:16) But now they are reaching out for a better place, that is, one belonging to heaven. Therefore, God is not ashamed of them, to be called on as their God, for he has prepared a city for them.

^ (Heb. 11:38) and the world was not worthy of them. They wandered about in deserts and mountains and caves and dens of the earth.

^ (Rom. 8:38, 39) For I am convinced that neither death nor life nor angels nor governments nor things now here nor things to come nor powers 39 nor height nor depth nor any other creation will be able to separate us from God’s love that is in Christ Jesus our Lord.

Tuesday, December 28

Create in me a pure heart, O God, and put within me a new spirit, a steadfast one.—[Ps. 51:10].

We can fight envy by cultivating humility and contentment. When our heart is full of these good qualities, envy will have no room to grow. Humility will help us not to think too highly of ourselves. A humble person does not feel that he deserves more than everyone else. ([Gal. 6:3, 4]) Someone who is content is satisfied with what he has and does not compare himself with others. (1 Tim. 6:7, 8) When a person who is humble and content sees someone receive something good, he is happy for him. We need the help of God’s holy spirit if we are to avoid the fleshly trait of envy and instead cultivate humility and contentment. ([Gal. 5:16;] Phil. 2:3, 4) Jehovah’s holy spirit can help us to examine our innermost thoughts and motives. With God’s help, we can replace harmful thoughts and feelings with upbuilding ones.—[Ps. 26:2]. w20.02 15 ¶8-9

^ (Ps. 51:10) Create in me a pure heart, O God, And put within me a new spirit, a steadfast one.

^ (Gal. 6:3, 4) For if anyone thinks he is something when he is nothing, he is deceiving himself. 4 But let each one examine his own actions, and then he will have cause for rejoicing in regard to himself alone, and not in comparison with the other person.

^ (1 Tim. 6:7, 8) For we have brought nothing into the world, and neither can we carry anything out. 8 So, having food* and clothing,* we will be content with these things.

Or “sustenance.”

Or “shelter.” Lit., “covering.”

^ (Gal. 5:16) But I say, Keep walking by spirit and you will carry out no fleshly desire at all.

^ (Phil. 2:3, 4) Do nothing out of contentiousness or out of egotism, but with humility* consider others superior to you, 4 as you look out not only for your own interests, but also for the interests of others.

Or “lowliness of mind.”

^ (Ps. 26:2) Examine me, O Jehovah, and put me to the test; Refine my innermost thoughts* and my heart.

Or “my deepest emotions.” Lit., “my kidneys.”